<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<BaseGameText>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_INTRO_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
      <Text>Acquired from [ICON_Culture] Culture, every Civic will unlock new social policies, governments, buildings, districts, or wonders. Progressing through the Civic Tree is a powerful way to advance your civilization through time.</Text>
    </Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CAPITALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the black hole of history (i.e., before written records) humans established various complex economies that involved elements of labor, trade and investment. Things economic remained fairly primitive until the 14th Century AD, when the Great Famine (1315-1317) and Black Death (1348-1350) led to a collapse of the manorial system due to a labor shortage, first in England and then throughout Europe. The feudal lords needed serfs to keep their estates running, and so began to hire workers; meanwhile, in towns and cities where entire guilds had been wiped out, the advent of wages encouraged craftsmen to move there to work for money rather than mere subsistence. All of which laid the foundations for colonialism and mercantilism, the precursors to capitalism. It was Adam Smith who first argued that mercantilism was not a force for economic progress but a hindrance in a civilization where labor was the most important currency of exchange.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CAPITALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The ideas of theorists such as Smith were well timed, for the Industrial Revolution was just beginning and a new economic order of free markets and paid labor was erupting. It was apparent that colonialism wasn’t the gold mine that investors had hoped; rather, a new gold mine was found in the mechanization of industry. Industrial capitalists investing in new forms of production and transport were able to amass great individual wealth in a single lifetime, outpacing the landed nobility and international banking families. For the first time in civilization, commoners could become wealthy without being born into it … with empires built on the sweaty backs of thousands of other commoners willing to be paid for their labor.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CAPITALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Modern capitalism was the first system to benefit all levels of society; wages increased, aided by the formation of labor unions, and the standards of living in industrial nations increased exponentially with the glut of affordable products being mass produced in factories. Despite hiccups such as the Great Depression and the 1970s Oil Crisis, which brought Keynesian-style government regulation to some economic endeavors, capitalism has become the new world order.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CIVIL_ENGINEERING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Around 2550 BC, Imhotep built a stepped pyramid for Dioser at the Saqqara necropolis; thus was founded “civil” (as opposed to military) engineering, the construction of things for the good (loosely defined) of the public. Although the combination of mathematics, physics and management wasn’t labelled as such yet, civil engineering projects of the ancients were legendary – the Qanat water system, the Parthenon, the Appian Way, the Great Wall, the Jetavanaramaya stupas. The busy Roman civil engineers were particularly skilled building the physical infrastructure that made Rome an empire: roads, aqueducts (such as the Pont du Gard at Nimes), bridges (the pons Fabricius in Rome for example), dams, docks, and irrigation systems. The treatise De Architectura libri decem by Marcus Vitruvius, written around 15 BC, was the first work on civil engineering, and served throughout the Middle Ages as the standard for the construction of public works … there not being much original thought in Europe for many years.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CIVIL_ENGINEERING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But things picked up with the Industrial Revolution and the discovery of new building materials, tools and needs. In the early 18th Century the term “civil engineering” was first used. And in 1747 civilization’s first civil engineering school opened: the École Nationale des Ponts et Chaussées (“National School of Bridges and Highways”). Soon those busy civil engineers were putting things up all over the landscape, changing city skylines and cluttering the countryside. The first self-proclaimed civil engineer was John Smeaton (who built the Eddystone Lighthouse), and in 1818 the world’s first engineering society – the Institution of Civil Engineers – was founded in London, mostly as an excuse to get together to drink and argue. The first degree in civil engineering in the United States was awarded in 1835 by the Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute. And in 1905 the first civil engineering degree to a woman was granted by Cornell University to one Nora Stanton Blatch Barney.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CIVIL_ENGINEERING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The genie of progress was now surely out of the bottle …</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CIVIL_SERVICE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Civil Service” is a relatively new term to describe a relatively old concept – a bureaucracy composed of trained officials to “efficiently” run the government (since the overworked monarch obviously couldn’t be expected to do it him/herself). The phrase was first bandied about by the British administration in India and popularized by Sir Charles Trevelyan a century ago when Great Britain established an examination for those who wanted to serve the Crown (other than in the military that is).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CIVIL_SERVICE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The origins of a civil service can be traced back to China (they did invent paper, after all). The Qin dynasty established the first centralized Chinese empire, and thus the need for a bureaucratic administration. Recruitment into the civil service was based on recommendations from local officials, and in 124 BC the Han Emperor Wudi established an imperial university to train and test would-be officials. By the time of the Tang dynasty appointment decreasingly relied on recommendation and increasingly on examination. The whole system expanded during the reign of Wu Zetian and reached its apex during the Song dynasty. The examination tested the candidate’s memorization of the Nine Classics of Confucianism and his ability to compose poetry and use calligraphy … obviously it helps if bureaucrats can read and write.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CIVIL_SERVICE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In the West, it was the well-organized Romans who set the standard for successive bureaucracies. By drawing upon the educated equestrian class, drafting them into responsible positions in his administration, Emperor Augustus founded the imperial civil service. Their business background made them particularly suited to run the far-flung provinces and make sure that Roman rule didn’t waver. By the time of Claudius, equestrians could reasonably expect a fine career – eventually becoming a procurator (“agent of the emperor”) and then a prefect, who might serve abroad or at home, in charge of anything from the fire brigades to the grain supply. While details vary across the centuries since, things haven’t changed much in the civil service since.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CLASS_STRUGGLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“The history of all hitherto existing society,” wrote Marx in the opening of his 1848 Communist Manifesto, “is the history of class struggle.” To which Engels added the caveat “all written history” in the 1888 English edition to account for the fact that for millennia primitive peoples lived in classless collectives. In their interpretation of history, civilized peoples live in a state of tension due to the competing socioeconomic interests between the differing classes. This view that the class struggle provides the impetus for radical change is central to the work of both Marxists and anarchists such as Mikhail Bakunin.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CLASS_STRUGGLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As with everything, there are at least two ways to understand the term “class struggle” – each popular with competing Marxist-Socialists. One approach understands it to mean a political movement where one or the other of contending groups considers itself to be a “class” (hence, having a class consciousness) consciously pursuing its interests. In the other, the class struggle inevitably breaks out wherever there is exploitation of one class by another. Thus, the slave who refuses to work hard and the master who whips him or her are both engaged in a class struggle, even if neither considers themselves to belong to a class. In the latter, the class struggle is a permanent, daily fixture in any industrial society.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CLASS_STRUGGLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>All of this was just intellectual posturing until the inequities of industrial capitalism made it clear that there was a ruling class which controlled the state and owned the means of production – the land and its resources, the workshops and factories, the banks and schools. At the other end of the spectrum were the “actual producers” of wealth, those who own little but their ability to work hard for minimal wages. It was the inequities between the capitalist class and the working class that fueled the great ideological divide of the 20th Century and so shaped modern civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CODE_OF_LAWS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Code of Laws – a (more-or-less) systematic compilation of pronouncements that purports to (more-or-less) exhaustively cover what is and isn’t acceptable in a society – have been a feature of civilization since the ancient kingdoms of the Middle East. The Sumerian Code of Ur-Nammu (c. 2100 BC) and the Babylonian Code of Hammurabi (c. 1760 BC) are the earliest known codes, letting the citizens know how their ruler felt about misbehavior. The old Hebrew Written and Oral Torah (c. 1330 BC) laid out the law – religious and civil – for God’s Chosen People. But it was those paragons of organization that really formalized the concept, with the Corpus Juris Civilis (drafted 529 to 534 AD) of the emperor Justinian, of setting down how to deal with every dispute or … well, everything. In China, the last exclusive imperial code of laws was the Great Qing Legal Code with its 1907 statutes; despite some 30 revisions, it held sway over the civilization from 1644 to 1912.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CODE_OF_LAWS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>By the time the successors to Rome in Europe got around to it – rather delayed since most kings weren’t fond of the idea of anything that might limit their own high-handed judgments – in the 15th Century, most codes were city or provincial compilations of local regulations. The first national codes of law appeared in the Scandinavian countries in the 17th Century. But as feudalism faded and strange ideas of equality and nationalism percolated, a new generation of codes was spawned, exemplified by the Prussian Code (1794), the Code Napoleon (1804) and the German Civil Code (1896). The latter two have served as the model for the majority of modern codes in current use. Too, most codes now have two distinctive elements: a civil code to settle disputes between citizens, and a criminal or penal code to take care of those who won’t behave.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_COLD_WAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>No sooner did the “Big One” get over than a “cold” war erupted, marked by economic, political, ideological, social and cultural conflict … energized by the threat of the apocryphal apocalypse … between civilization’s two superpowers. The alliance between the Soviet Union and the Western democracies had been one of convenience to defeat Hitler … as Winston Churchill famously stated: “If Hitler invaded Hell I would make at least a favourable reference to the Devil in the House of Commons.” But once that was accomplished and the Soviet Union grabbed as much of Eastern Europe as it could a showdown between communism and democracy (neither in its pure form) was inevitable.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_COLD_WAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Despite calls for a shooting war to end the threat – such as “Operation Unthinkable,” code name for a plan to attack the Soviet Union developed by the British Joint Planning Staff under Churchill’s orders at the end of World War II – the new American president Truman, encouraged by advisors such as Averill Harriman and James Forrestal, decided on instead taking a hard line with Moscow … or at least, harder than Roosevelt had. In February 1946 Ambassador George Kennan’s “Long Telegram” from Moscow articulated the American policy of “containment” with which the superpower would defend itself against “Russian expansive tendencies.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_COLD_WAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Despite the never-ending crises – the Berlin Blockade, Hungarian Uprising, Chinese civil war, Cuban Missile Crisis, bloody little wars in Korea, Vietnam and Afghanistan – neither power was quite willing to take the last step … primarily because both had the atomic bomb in their arsenal. Russia had tested an atomic bomb of its own in 1949; Truman announced that the United States would build a “superbomb” (hydrogen bomb); and Stalin promptly followed suit. The world stumbled along on the brink of MAD (Mutually Assured Destruction) until the American Richard Nixon established diplomatic relations with China in 1972, which in turn led to a policy of détente with Russia. Although thawed, the Cold War “raged” on until the Soviet Union itself broke apart and collapsed in 1991.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_COLONIALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Colonialism is a historical phenomenon that spans millennia and the globe. Both the Phoenicians and the Greeks planted colonies all around the Mediterranean, and the first step in becoming part of the Roman Empire was often for a land to be colonized by conquest. But it is during the mid- and late-16th Century AD that European powers – driven by rapid population growth, technological progress, constrained economies, military competition, religious fanaticism, and sheer curiosity – launched a concerted effort to explore and colonize new lands.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_COLONIALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>It was little Portugal, a unified kingdom since 1385 and relatively free from internal strife (unlike the bigger nations), that kicked off the age of colonization. Looking to find wealth by sailing around the continent to reach the fabled Far East, it established colonial settlements and forts along the African coasts. But it was Spain that would undertake the first great land grab. Columbus managed to underestimate the circumference of the Earth by about one-fourth and so thought he could reach the Far East by sailing 2400 miles westward. Instead, he stumbled into a couple of large, rich and relatively uninhabited continents – although he insisted until his death that he had reached Asia. For over a century the Portuguese and the Spaniards were the only ones with New World colonies, but in time the Netherlands, French and English were grabbing bits as well.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_COLONIALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>So profitable and satisfying was colonizing the Americas that the “great” powers didn’t stop there. They turned their individual attention to the known world as well, colonizing Africa, India, Southeast Asia and islands across the Pacific. Thanks to the Royal Navy and lots of good guns, the British were particularly adept at it. Eventually even former colonies (the United States) and late bloomers (Germany and Japan) busied themselves creating colonial empires. Whatever the justification – financial, religious, moral (the “White Man’s Burden”), political – every nation that could managed to find some hapless natives to “civilize” through colonization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CONSERVATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The idea of conservation of natural resources can be traced to the work Sylva, or a Discourse of Forest-Trees, presented by John Evelyn to the Royal Society in 1662 AD. Timber resources in England were seriously depleted – thanks to all those ships, buildings and bridges – and Evelyn argued that cutting should be managed and trees replanted in logged areas. No one paid any further attention to the environment, other than exploiting it, until the Progressive Age when some folks sought to convince other Americans that it was their civic duty to preserve unspoiled the land, water and wildlife for future generations. Romantics such as Henry David Thoreau idealized nature, even as pragmatists such as Gifford Pinchot (first head of the U.S. Forestry Service) sought ways to insure that renewable resources would remain renewable … to keep America strong and the economy expanding.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CONSERVATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Even as American cities were becoming more crowded, as the Western frontier was disappearing, as “nature” was being commercialized, and as the working man had more disposable income, leisure and conservation came together as more and more people took up hiking, camping, bird watching, and other outdoor recreations. With general support from the citizens, the U.S. Congress passed landmark legislation establishing Yellowstone Park in 1872, Yosemite National Park in 1890, and finally creating the National Park Service in 1916. Soon the individual states were creating parks and preserves all over the place, and establishing policies to protect fish and game from wholesale slaughter (rather too late for the poor passenger pigeon).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CONSERVATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Although efforts to protect the environment sometimes produced more problems (such as the elimination of predators in parks leading to mass die-offs), other developed nations soon leapt onto the conservation bandwagon as well. It would be some decades before developing countries would join the movement … being rather more concerned with pragmatic issues such as industrializing, avoiding famine, and raising the standard of living for their citizens.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CRAFTSMANSHIP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Craftsmanship is simply the application of skill in the making of something, be it functional or just some decorative but otherwise useless knick-knack. Since there were so many unskilled laborers, ancient craftsmen were highly valued, whether slave or free. In Athens craftsmanship interacted with art and culture in intriguing ways; Socrates, for instance, was fond of analogies concerning craftsmanship and was reputedly himself the son of a skilled stonemason. Many a Greek grew wealthy from their craftsmen-slaves, such as those Demosthenes owned: some 120 tanners, flute-makers and cutlers. So valued were the skills of slaves that craftsmen themselves became a high-priced commodity in Rome, where weavers and tailors, metal-workers and engravers, leather tanners and shoemakers, and other pairings could be brought together in urban workshops to produce high-quality goods.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CRAFTSMANSHIP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In the Middle Ages, once most craftsmen were free (if all that servitude to a lord is ignored), they began to organize themselves into guilds to promote their skills and their standards. In the guilds, those seeking to progress to being a master craftsman progressed through the stages of apprentice and journeyman first, insuring a level of excellence in their craft. But industrialization – the mass production of all those things – ended the need for craftsmanship, and in the decades after the French Revolution most of the guilds collapsed. Corporations could manufacture goods quicker and cheaper, substituting standardization for craftsmanship.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CRAFTSMANSHIP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Today, in the popular mindset, craftsmanship has come to mean “made by hand” rather than “skilled production” … and these are certainly not the same.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CULTURAL_HERITAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Even in a world concerned about "the brotherhood of man," the 20th Century saw a burst of concern about their respective and distinctive cultural heritage(s) from all sorts of people. Decolonization and immigration formed the background for contemporary concerns about where “we came from.” Whether it was seeking to redress perceived wrongs or celebrating what made a group unique, “cultural heritage” became the new hobby for millions in the developed nations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CULTURAL_HERITAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As it came to be understood in the two decades following World War II – not coincidentally, the era of the Civil Rights Movement, the “Troubles” in Northern Ireland, native American equality, and independence movements across Asia and Africa (some three dozen new states achieved autonomy between 1945 and 1960) – cultural heritage implied a shared bond, a belonging to some sort of community determined by ethnicity, location, religion and/or common beliefs. It became both a political as well as personal tool of identity.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CULTURAL_HERITAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The physical artifacts were the first items of cultural heritage to draw attention: the paintings, drawings, mosaics, sculpture, photographs, literary works, buildings, monuments and archaeological findings. With a market for cultural heritage (both legitimate and black) artifacts booming, national and international cultural property laws which protect and regulate the disposition of cultural items were passed to protect those pieces with special significance to a defined group. In tandem, regulations evolved for repatriation of art and artifacts, usually looted or ancient, to the country of origin or former owners.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CULTURAL_HERITAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Intangible heritage also became all the rage, encompassing a dizzying array of cultural traditions: music, dress, theater, cuisine, celebrations and holidays and holy processions. To recover this “authenticity” the industry of cultural tourism has sprung up, taking people to cultural attractions far away to gather information and experiences to satisfy their “cultural needs” … be this the reinforcement of one’s own cultural identity or the observation of exotic “others.” In an age of globalization and social media, the mantra of cultural heritage provides the counterbalance.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_DEFENSIVE_TACTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Besides cowering behind walls when the barbarians came, the first defensive tactics consisted of packing armored men in as tight as possible, with lots of sharp spears pointing outward to discourage attackers. The first to adopt such a phalanx formation were the Sumerians around the third millennium BC. Their densely packed infantry were armored (helmet, breastplate, and greaves) and armed (with nine-foot spears and round shields that could be overlapped). For the next few thousand years defensive tactics didn’t change much, save that archery made better armor ever more important.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_DEFENSIVE_TACTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As with so many things military, Rome improved upon the defensive tactics employed by most of their competitors. The Romans pioneered the manipular legion sometime around 300 BC, giving their formations more flexibility and support; deployed in a triple line with gaps between the maniples, the legion could react rapidly to any threat. In front before battle, elite skirmishers (the velites) covered the deployment of the legion; and during battle cavalry and auxiliaries protected the flanks. The thoughtful Romans developed defensive tactics to counter every threat conceivable: the testudo to protect from missiles, the saw to quickly plug gaps in the line, the orb for formations that had been cut off, and Fabian tactics to avoid battle when at a disadvantage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_DEFENSIVE_TACTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In the Middle Ages such cleverness was largely thrown over for simply charging at the enemy and hacking away until one side or the other had had enough. The difference in tactics between Viking berserkers and European knights is miniscule, as military thinking focused on the offensive and largely forgot the defensive (save for those towering castle walls and masses of archers). That is, until gunpowder made head-long charges a dicey proposition again. As firearms became cheaper and more effective, requiring little training to be used in defense, gunpowder dominated the battlefield. And the only real defensive tactic became to spread troops out, to use camouflage, and to dig down.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_DIPLOMATIC_SERVICE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>To “practice” diplomacy is one of the defining actions of a nation, and diplomacy has been “practiced” since the first city-states. Originally diplomacy was conducted by a ruler’s emissary, generally for a specific mission, returning home when negotiations were complete (if lucky, many an emissary’s head got sent back instead). Thus, the “diplomatic service” was composed of members of the ruling family or high-ranking nobles … a dubious honor if one failed to settle matters. Until the Renaissance, there were no permanent relations, save that between the Pope and the Byzantine Emperor through the 8th Century AD. In the Far East, relationships were more violent, although the Song dynasty would establish a pattern of resident Chinese envoys in neighboring nations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_DIPLOMATIC_SERVICE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The origins of “modern diplomacy” can be traced to the cities of Northern Italy in the early Renaissance. In the 1400s, Milan – goaded by Francesco Sforza – played a leading role in the establishment of permanent embassies in other city-states to establish trade, make defensive pacts, and present a united front to the papacy. Most of the traditions of diplomatic service – such as the presentation of an ambassador’s credentials to a head of state – began here. In 1455 Milan was the first to place a permanent representative in the court of a major power – in this case, France. The practice spread, with Spain being the first nation to “exchange” ambassadors with another sovereign state (England). By the late 16th Century permanent embassies were the standard for international relations … unless the countries were at war, of course.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_DIPLOMATIC_SERVICE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Ambassadors were usually nobles with little experience in negotiating (or much of anything else); they were supported by a large staff of specialists, from lawyers and linguists to soldiers and spies. As the European powers spread around the world, making contact with strange civilizations in distant places and carving out empires, diplomacy became too important to leave in the hands of amateurs. By the late 1600s the need for skilled professionals was increasingly met by university graduates in international law, languages, cultural history, economics and such.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_DIVINE_RIGHT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>It is fairly clear that the theory of the divine right of kings can be traced back to the Bible, as the 13th chapter of Romans begins: “For there is no authority except from God, and those that exist have been instituted by God. Therefore he who resists the authorities resists what God has appointed, and those who resist will incur judgment …” Moreover, as the apostle Paul noted, in the book of the prophet Daniel it states categorically that God “removes kings and sets them up.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_DIVINE_RIGHT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>While in other places and other times, some kings claimed to be descended from divine beings (or to be gods themselves), in early Christian Europe the notion took hold that the Merovingians held power because it was God’s will they do so, and that they were therefore blessed. Thus, when Charlemagne was crowned by the pope on Christmas Day 800 AD, it was not a conferring of authority but merely confirmation of what already existed … his divine right to rule. The ultimate root of kingly authority was spiritual (although having a big, well-trained army helped).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_DIVINE_RIGHT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>This philosophy (or theology) was quite popular among kings for many centuries. In 1597, for instance, James VI of Scotland penned the Basilikon Doron, a manual on the power of kings, in preparation for his ascension to the English throne, stating, “The state of monarchy is the supremest thing upon Earth, for kings are not only God’s lieutenants upon earth and sit upon God’s throne.” But by the 18th Century, rulers began to consolidate power in more secular ways, tending towards absolutism. The spread of Protestantism hurried things along, as the Catholic sanction of divine right came into question. The American and French revolutions, and Napoleon’s tossing all kinds of kings aside, deprived the doctrine of its last shreds of credibility.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_DRAMA_POETRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>It is unlikely that any human civilization (at any rate until the coming of those dour Puritans) has denied itself the excitement of drama or the pleasure of poetry. Drama – of a kind – is present in the rituals of most primitive cultures. While such ceremonies are certainly dramatic, they don’t evoke theater as such. Theatrical drama requires a sung or spoken text – poetry – a development which occurred in ancient Greece. Poetry itself predates literacy, back to at least the age of Homer and the oral epics of Mesopotamia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_DRAMA_POETRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>It is in Athens, around the 6th Century BC, that drama became an “art” form. During the Dionysian festivals, a chorus would sing the stories of Greek myth. At some point, a priest of Dionysus by the name of Thespis began to engage in a dialogue with the chorus. According to legend, Thespis was also the first winner of a theatrical competition, held in Athens in 534 BC. Such competitions became a regular feature of festivals throughout Greece, and innovations – now conventions – in both tragedy and comedy were the result. Aeschylus added a second actor; Sophocles a third, further extending the dramatic possibilities. Euripides introduced plots more complex, characterizations more central, and the interactions between characters became the stuff of drama.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_DRAMA_POETRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Meanwhile, poetry evolved as a way of remembering – orally – history, myth, law, genealogy, moral codes, and a host of other things important to civilization. (Only with the coming of writing was this burden lifted from mankind.) Most of the ancient works later set down, from the Vedas (c. 1700 BC) to the Odyssey (c. 800 BC), were composed in poetic form to aid memorization and transmission by word of mouth. The oldest surviving “poem” is the Tale of the Shipwrecked Sailor, written in Hieratic and ascribed to a date around 4500 BC … although some argue for the oldest being the Epic of Gilgamesh written in cuneiform.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_DRAMA_POETRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Since those early years, both drama and poetry have undergone many evolutions, in both Western and Eastern civilizations. But they remain essential cultural markers in all.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_EARLY_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The natural pattern of nations is that one state, for whatever reason, becomes more powerful than its neighbors economically and/or militarily and conquers them … creating an “empire.” The more it conquers, the stronger it gets, and so it conquers more and more of its neighbors. Eventually inertia sets in and the empire stops expanding – sometimes because it meets neighbors stronger than it is but more often simply because it has become inefficient and venal, and it is inconvenient to fight wars of conquest so far from the center. Often the expanse of the early empire is determined by the state of technology, in terms of communications and transport. At some point, the empire weakens and breaks apart into smaller states … and the cycle begins anew.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_EARLY_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The first “empire” was the Akkadian, established by Sargon in Mesopotamia c. 24th Century BC, an achievement matched later by Hammurabi of Babylon in the 17th Century BC. In the 15th Century BC the New Kingdom of Egypt, ruled by Thutmose III, was the standard for empire. Around 1500 BC arose the Shang Empire in distant China, to be followed by the Chou Empire 400 years later – its collapse was followed 550 years later by the Qin c. 221 BC. The first empire in civilization comparable to imperial Rome was the Neo-Assyrian; there followed the Median, Babylonian again, Persian, Macedonian (briefly) and so forth.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_EARLY_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>But it was Rome that set the standard. Thanks to their skill at organization, engineering infrastructure, military innovation, cultural flexibility, and economic clout, the Romans established the most influential and stable empire the world has seen. Indeed, the Latin word imperium has been used ever since to refer to empires such as the Umayyad, Ottoman, Spanish, British and even the American. And each in turn took up the claim of the Roman Cicero, who wrote that an empire exists because it has a “civilizing mission” to bring prosperity and peace to the world – whether the world wants it or not.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_EXPLORATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since man first settled in one place, there have always been those among them who have been driven to see what lies over the horizon. Whether motivated by profit, adventure, religion, necessity or just curiosity, explorers have widened our knowledge of the world and its wonders. In the process of exploring, they have also linked diverse and distant cultures, for good or ill. And they found along the way many new ways to die.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_EXPLORATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Phoenicians sailed all about the ancient Mediterranean seeking new trade goods; tin found in their artifacts indicates they may even have reached distant Britain. The Carthaginian Hanno “the Navigator” explored the coast of Africa beyond the Pillars of Heracles c. 500 BC. Restless Greeks wandered into northern Europe, maybe even to far Thule. During the 2nd Century BC the Han dispatched explorers into Central Asia to see what lay to the west of their borders, beyond those annoying Xiung-nu. Much later, the Chinese admiral Zheng He sailed past Southeast Asia, the Indonesia islands, around India, and along the east coast of Africa, lands full of barbarians and new things to trade. Around the same time, Vikings were venturing across the North Atlantic to explore and settle Iceland, Greenland, Vinland and other places.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_EXPLORATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The so-called “Age of Exploration” saw crowded and troubled Europe spew out explorers. And there was a lot to explore, for little was known about the hearts of Africa or Asia. They found the Americas, Australia, New Zealand and a bunch of islands scattered across the Pacific. Commencing in the 15th Century, they established first trading empires, and then more “forceful” ones. Later explorers such as the Portuguese Diego Cao travelled up the Congo, and the Spaniard Francisco de Orellana up the Amazon, and the Lewis and Clark expedition up the Missouri and Columbia rivers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_EXPLORATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>By 1900, not much was left to explore, save for the polar regions; both Cook and Peary claimed to have reached the North Pole in 1908 and 1909 respectively, while Amundsen’s team arrived at the South Pole in December 1911.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_FEUDALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Although decentralization of the Carolingian Empire was the impetus, the feudal system came into focus during the 8th Century AD. (“Feudalism” is simply a term historians invented around the 17th Century to label a social structure they otherwise couldn’t define in one word.) To promote the expansion of his holdings, Charlemagne began granting his nobles certain rights over tracts of land to yield the income necessary for them to provide soldiers for his adventures. In return for this largess, each noble swore an oath of loyalty to the crown. In time, this social, economic, political and judicial control of the allocated lands became hereditary, with these lords now giving fiefs to their own favored underlings who swore oaths of fealty … hence, feudalism.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_FEUDALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The classic version of feudalism was a mish-mash of reciprocal legal and military obligations among a warrior nobility, revolving around the concepts of lords, vassals and fiefs. (There were, of course, peasants tied to the land, but lords and vassals didn’t concern themselves with such much.) For the next 500 years, power and wealth passed about between the favored few as if in a vast game; the rules were complex, often mysterious, in which the Catholic Pope had special privileges and powers as God’s representative on Earth. Not only did aristocrats partake of feudalism, but so too did bishops and abbots (bishops at times could be found on the battlefields, hacking away with the best of secular lords). </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_FEUDALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Feudalism, with the rise of nationalism and absolute monarchy, decayed and effectively disappeared in most of Europe by about 1500. It lingered on in Central and Eastern Europe as late as the 1850s; a form did survive in Japan until that benighted kingdom was forced open to the West. And Russia finally abolished serfdom in 1861.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_FOREIGN_TRADE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to archaeological findings, sometime around the 19th Century BC there was an Assyrian merchant colony in Kanesh in Cappadocia – the first known instance of foreign trade. As the world got divvied up into city-states, republics, kingdoms and empires, folks learned that there were some things they wanted … just over the border. Since war was fraught with uncertainty and risk, clever sorts found a more peaceful way to obtain those things, by trading what they had in abundance (be it goods, services or slaves) for what the neighbors had. In time, trade routes were established, some spanning continents: the Silk Road, the Amber Road, the Via Maris. Exports and imports drove the rise of civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_FOREIGN_TRADE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In time, inevitably, governments came to understand that all this foreign trade could be a boon, in that taxes (tariffs, duties or other innocuous terms) on imports and exports could fill the state’s coffers. And since scarcity of a good could increase its value … and hence, the taxes … governments began regulating production, extraction, shipping and all aspects of foreign trade as well. Regulations on foreign trade existed in ancient societies centered in the Mesopotamian and Mediterranean regions. These in turn led to standardized weights and measures so merchants wouldn’t cheat, and to the use of scarce metals as a crude form of international currency. In China, paper currency (a peculiar concept) was invented so foreign trade could be conducted in a civilized manner.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_FOREIGN_TRADE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>All sorts of models and theories have been devised by economists to understand and explain foreign trade: Adam Smith’s model, the Richardian model, the Hechscher-Ohlin model, the Gravity model, the New Trade theory, the Ricardo-Sraffa trade theory, and so forth. Most, however, simply do not account for the driving impetus … greed. On that basic principle civilization was built.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_GAMES_RECREATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Recreation is an essential element in the human condition; indeed, leisure is considered a necessity under the Universal Declaration of Human Rights adopted by the United Nations General Assembly in December 1948 AD. Recreational “pursuits” may be communal or solitary, active or passive, structured or freeform, healthy or harmful, private or public. The leisure time devoted to recreation varies significantly from one culture to the next, although anthropologists have found that those in primitive societies have significantly more of it than do individuals in more “developed” civilizations. For instance, the people of the tribes of the Great Basin such as the Shoshone were viewed as extraordinarily lazy by European interlopers, who filled their time with building, praying and “making a profit.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_GAMES_RECREATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Each early civilization had its own forms of recreation. Recreation – in the form of games and sports – were often the vestiges of warfare, hunting, religious practices or other useless activities. Plato among others held that recreation was crucial for both the individual as well as the society, in that one could learn, explore and experience things in a “safe” environment. But in the Middle Ages, for many, recreation became a luxury; everyone worked hard … and the Church condemned most forms of leisure (not that folk didn’t engage in all these despite this). The Renaissance wasn’t much better, although the wealthy did find time to play games and read, and “artistic hobbies” were taken up by various feckless folk.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_GAMES_RECREATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>It was the Industrial Revolution that really brought leisure, games and recreation into the mainstream again. The annual hours committed to “work” declined in the Industrial West from 1840 to the present from the range of 3000 to 1800 hours. Workers and their unions demanded – and got – ever shorter work weeks, paid vacations, weekends off, and all sorts of other benefits … just so they could spend their extra earnings and spare time on recreation and games.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_GLOBALIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the 20th Century AD, the globalizing impulse can be viewed as ever-widening ripples of homogeneity … from local to national to regional to global … with the logical conclusion being a unified economy, unified culture, unified language, unified state, and perhaps a unified civilization. Rapid developments in information technology have spawned new, virtual relationships that lead to cultural entropy. International industrialization has brought the mass production of standardized goods that can be inserted into every market in every place. The reduction of tariffs and creation of free trade zones, elimination of national capital controls, and passage of new subsidies has given rise to sprawling and diversified global corporations. Supranational recognition of international property laws (copyright and patent restrictions) insures the global domination of accepted artforms, though sometimes at the expense of local diversity, traditions and individuality.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_GLOBALIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The 1840s form a watershed (of sorts) in globalization with expansion of international economies, as the British forced open the interior of China (in the Opium Wars) and the United States browbeat Japan into opening its ports to Western trade. The integration of separate, highly specialized agricultural production created the first “world economy”: French wines, Australian beef, Indian teas, Japanese rice, South American peppers, African spices. The industrial technologies of the factory, railroad, telegraph, Gatling gun and steamship facilitated similar rules and regulations spreading from nation to nation. Though interrupted briefly by two world wars and a great depression between, globalization resumed its triumphant march as the engines of mass media and advertising spread its tendrils beyond the iron and bamboo curtains … the export dynamics of culture reaching into every village. Sociologists argue the world has entered a frenetic fourth phase of globalization, in which developed and developing nations are becoming equal partners in investment, and as per capita income between the two rapidly converge.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_GLOBALIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>A brave – although perhaps bland – new world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_GUILDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>At their best from the 12th through the 15th centuries, the medieval merchant and craft guilds fostered a stable and productive economy, supported charities and social reforms, helped finance roads, schools and churches. And made possible the transition from feudalism to capitalism. Yet the guilds’ conservatism, exclusivity, monopolistic practices, and political meddling eventually eroded their benefit, dooming them to irrelevance and dissolution. By the time decrees abolishing craft associations were enacted in France (1791), Spain (1840), Germany (1859), and Italy (1864), the guilds’ authority had long been on the wane.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_GUILDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Predecessors of the trade guilds were found as early as the 3rd Century BC in Rome and Han China. But by the early Middle Ages, most Roman craft organizations (the collegia), often mutated into Christian confraternities, had disappeared – with the exception of stonecutters and glassmakers, who were employed in building all those churches. The collegia did survive in the Byzantine Empire and figured heavily in the social order of the capital; the famous Book of the Prefect c. 900 AD provides insight into an elaborate guild structure whose primary purpose was imposition of rigid controls on every craft and trade in Byzantium. This concept of control of quality and quantity and price likely spread to Italy in the 10th Century, and then throughout Europe in the 11th Century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_GUILDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Medieval guilds were generally established by charters or letters patent issued by the governing body of a city or town, providing a monopoly on production or trade of a good or service there. The ruler was paid a tithe and the guild got to set standards and prices … so everyone was satisfied (save maybe the consumers). Records from the late 12th Century show over 100 guilds chartered by each of the cities of London and Paris. In places, so powerful were some guilds that they became the governing body of cities, indicated by the guildhalls found in Germany, Switzerland, and Holland. But corruption, coupled with new technologies, proved their undoing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_HUMANISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to the British Humanist Association, secular humanism is: “1) putting human beings and other living things at the centre of your moral outlook; 2) seeing the world as a natural place and looking to science and reason to make sense of it; and 3) promoting and supporting human flourishing across all frontiers, and championing human rights for everyone.” </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_HUMANISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>These humanist concepts have been around since at least 1500 BC in various Indian and Asian philosophies. In the 6th Century BC, Gautama Buddha expressed a skeptical attitude towards the supernatural and the “soul”; Zarathustra held that humans were thinking beings dignified with choice and agency. Greek philosophers from Xenophanes to Plato sought to explain the world in terms of human reason, and Epicurus concisely summarized human-centered approaches to achieving happiness. In the Middle Ages, most Muslim scholars pursued rational and scientific interpretations of existence in their writings about individualism, secularism, skepticism and liberalism ... all humanist concepts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_HUMANISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>But in Europe, humanism came late to civilization. Catholicism had a strong presence until the Renaissance, and it wasn't until a rediscovery of the “classics” by Italian poets that brought humanism back. Francessco Petrarca (better known to most as Petrarch) in the 1300s is often called the “Father of Humanism”; his discovery and translation of Cicero’s lost letters into the common vernacular is also credited with initiating the Renaissance. The growing endorsement of classical studies by scholars in the new universities – the studia humanitatis programs that consisted of grammar, poetry, rhetoric, history and moral philosophy – spread the concept of a secular approach to understanding across borders. Aided by an outpouring of rediscovered or newly translated Greek and Roman manuscripts by the likes of Aristotle, Cicero and Livy; these works were full of fresh, radical, even avant-garde ideas.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_IDEOLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The course of modern civilization has been determined by, as much as anything, modern “isms”: capitalism, socialism, communism, fascism, conservatism, liberalism, pluralism, racism, feminism, terrorism, scientism, and an infinite host of other ideologies that dictate how society “should work.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_IDEOLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>At the time of the French Revolution the philosopher Destutt de Tracy used the word idéologie for what he termed his “science of ideas.” In this he had bought into the view of Francis Bacon that the destiny of science was to improve the life of mankind; ideology was science with a mission, aiming to serve men – even saving them from themselves – by ridding their minds of prejudice and preparing them for the supremacy of reason. But when Napoleon linked the word “ideology” with what he considered the more detestable elements of Revolutionary thought, he invested it with disapprobation and fanaticism rather than rationalism (yet more “isms”). Karl Marx, along with influential German sociologists Max Weber and Karl Mannheim, used the term in the pejorative sense of false consciousness engendered by belief systems. From this perspective, a political ideology is an intellectual construct not to be judged in terms of its truth, consistency or clarity, but rather as an expression of some group’s special interests.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_IDEOLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Until the advent of the mass media, the ideologies remained largely theoretical, merely the subject of obscure academic debates. But the ability to promote “causes” through print, radio, newsreels and then television made all the “isms” much more immediate, and crusaders of all ilk invested their identities in one or another. All the wars, movements and genocides of 20th Century civilization can be attributed to divisive ideologies. As Joycelyn Elders states, “we all have got to come to grips with our isms.” Otherwise, the future looks grim.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MASS_MEDIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The “mass media” (as a collective) is essentially an Industrial era phenomenon, although some historians stubbornly argue that it began when Gutenberg rolled his press. The growth of the commercial printing industry in 18th Century London – centered around the publishers on Grub Street – is a more reasonable start, for it was here that cheap copies of penny-dreadfuls, erotic novels and tabloid weeklies were reproduced by the thousands on steam-presses. These were sold to a growing audience of rudimentary readers, spawned by a new public education system and crammed into an urban environment with few leisure escapes; supported by these masses, publishing no longer depended on the refined tastes of the aristocracy, wealthy and clergy for profits.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MASS_MEDIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As the Industrial Age morphed into the Modern, a number of revolutionary technologies brought new ways of pandering to media consumers. Photography was developed in the 1820s, and methods for reproducing images in print improved throughout the century, making magazines and newspapers even more appealing to a barely-literate public. The telegraph, invented in the 1830s and in widespread use by the 1850s, revolutionized both personal communication as well as the newspaper trade, as news really was now “new.” The penny press could, through a continuous stream of telegraph cables, bring the doings (and advertising) of the region, the nation and – after the completion of the 1863 trans-Atlantic cable – the world to one’s door.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MASS_MEDIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Photography led to motion pictures, and the movie industry grew to supply escapist fare to anyone with a dime in their pocket and a couple of hours to kill. By 1927 sound had been added to the flickering images, and the world underwent an entertainment explosion. For personal communication, Bell’s little gizmo intended to replace the telegraph, his “telephone,” put everyone in touch, everywhere, all the time. Wireless telegraphy also eventually led to the radio, and “commercial” radio became the first broadcast mass medium, beaming music, news and advertising right into the home. Soon, television, which spread with incredible speed in the 1950s, evolved into the greatest time-devourer of all … until, that is, video games and the Internet joined the ranks of the mass media.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MEDIEVAL_FAIRES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As foreign trade expanded and craftsmen flourished, in the late Middle Ages a new kind of marketplace sprang up. A facet of European feudalism, a “market town” was one that had the legal right, granted to it by a lord, to have a permanent market; for other towns and villages, and even city neighborhoods, there arose the practice of hosting a market faire. During the faire, travelling merchants and craftsmen would assemble at a designated spot and offer their wares for sale. In time, all sorts joined in the event – entertainers, lawyers, doctors, tax-collectors, and other riff-raff. The faires, lasting just a day or three (and often associated with a saint’s feast day), were usually set up in the precincts of a church or abbey. Except in England where this sort of avarice – the whole “Christ driving the money-lenders from the temple” bit – was seen as a desecration and therefore forbidden by the Statute of Winton enacted during the reign of Edward I (c. 1300 AD).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MEDIEVAL_FAIRES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The local nobles encouraged the establishment of such faires as the merchants were required to pay to set up their tents and booths. Then they usually had to also pay a tax to the king. Everyone got what they wanted: the king and nobles got money (to buy luxuries); the merchants got a profit; the peasants and villagers got new goods, new ideas, and new news.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MEDIEVAL_FAIRES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Over the decades, a large number of these market faires were established by royal charter, the earliest extant being dated 1199. There are also many references in church and government records of faires which do not appear to have a charter; these are described as “prescriptive” … that is they were held by custom. Many of the oldest faires, especially those in urban centers, were prescriptive and had been operating for a century or more … such as the market faire held on the green at Maldon (Essex), first mentioned in writing in 1287 but which may have been in place as early as 916.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MERCANTILISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>By the 1600s, the Spanish, British, Portuguese, French, Russians and sundry other European powers had empires to run, and empires were costly baubles. The way to keep the home economy healthy was to establish a system known as mercantilism; in effect, the colonies were the “cash cow” for the mother country. It was, for obvious reasons, extremely popular with absolutist monarchs and their subjects – at least those in the homeland – and the dominant economic practice from the 16th through the 18th centuries. Simply put, the Crown put limits on what finished goods the colonies could produce, whose ships they could use, with whom they could trade … and then taxed everything.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MERCANTILISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>It was inevitable that the British perfected mercantilism. It was expensive to send troops and ships to defend and dominate their colonies spread around the globe. For decades the British government’s stance was “salutary neglect,” passing laws to regulate colonial trade but not enforcing them; the colonies benefited from goods that slipped in from France, Holland, Spain and their nearby colonies in North and South America. However, strapped for cash by the Seven-Years War and other misadventures, in 1763 AD Parliament moved to enforce the many restrictions and taxes and even passed new ones – the Navigation Acts and the Sugar Act. A bad idea as it turned out, for it sparked a revolution in the Americas.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MERCANTILISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Other European nations embraced mercantilism to varying degrees, with varying degrees of success. The Netherlands had little interest in limiting international trade and so adopted few mercantilist policies. During the Thirty Years War, however, Sweden and Denmark both passed restrictive trade laws and taxes to fund their involvement; and the Holy Roman Empire, while desirous of such an economic policy, was simply too decentralized and diverse to implement it efficiently. France adopted mercantilism as early as 1539 when a royal decree banned the import of woolen goods from Spain and Flanders and the export of bullion (another universal aspect of mercantilist economics).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MERCANTILISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>But mercantilism didn’t work very well when the Industrial Revolution came, and by 1860 England had ended the last vestiges of the mercantile era.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MERCENARIES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since the dawn of civilization, men have killed and died for money (more sensible than for honor, faith, love, or other nonsense). No one is quite sure the first time a tribal chieftain hired mercenaries to augment his ill-trained (and likely reluctant) militia or guard his person, but after the Qin conquest of the other warring states, the Qin and Han dynasties employed nomadic horse archers from the steppes to insure security. Xenophon recounts that Cyrus the younger hired “Ten Thousand” Greek mercenaries in 401 BC to seize the throne of Persia, and Macedonia, Carthage and Rome employed “barbarian” mercenaries in their wars.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MERCENARIES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But it was during the Medieval Age that mercenaries came to the fore in war. The Byzantine emperors followed the old Roman practice of contracting foreigners as a personal bodyguard, notably the fearsome Norsemen formed into the Varangian Guard. In England, William the Conqueror employed Flemish archers to first win and then rule the land. In Italy, condottieri companies were in service to any city-state willing to pay for their professionalism in the internecine wars that marked the 12th through 15th centuries … though they switched sides at the drop of a coin. And El Cid wasn’t the only Christian to fight for a Muslim ruler.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MERCENARIES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The so-called “free companies” evolved after the Peace of Brétigny in 1360 ended (for nine years) the Hundred Years War when hundreds of experienced soldiers chose to continue the life (and looting) they had known. Since most nations of the time couldn’t afford to maintain standing armies, there was no lack of work. Following colorful and ruthless commanders such as Sir John Hawkwood, Arnaud de Cervole, Rodrigo de Villandrando and Werner von Urslingen, these companies dominated warfare across Europe into the 1600s. In the British Isles and France, the bloody-minded Scottish gallóglaigh (literally “foreign young warriors”) made their mark by slaughtering all sorts of Englishmen. Then there were the famed Swiss mercenaries, some of whom formed the Papal Guard of the Vatican.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MERCENARIES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>The tradition continues …</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MILITARY_TRADITION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since humans have never been able to get along long, it was destined that war would evolve as those primitive hunter-gathers settled down and found they needed something more than a club to bash in their neighbors’ heads. Thus, in a number of places military traditions arose to make the head-bashing more efficient. Initially, this tradition simply meant training the militia, those “volunteers” who did the ruler’s bidding when conflicts arose. India had some of the earliest such militias; after the Aryan invasions c. 2000 BC the Indus Valley city-states began maintaining trained cadres of warriors. Around the same time, the Old Kingdom of Egypt established a trained militia to combat the Libyans, Nubians, Canaanites and other annoyances. In China, the Warring States Period firmly established a military tradition in that civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MILITARY_TRADITION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>It was in Greece – specifically Sparta – however that the earliest “professional” army was given birth; in Sparta, at the age of seven boys were sent to a barracks to be indoctrinated into the military traditions of their homeland. (At the age of 33 they were released from barrack life and allowed to marry and have a family, although they remained “on call” until the age of 60.) By the time Rome got done, military tradition had come to encompass a host of practices: everything from tactics and uniforms to formations and even salutes. Rome’s successors in Europe formalized the practice of mass violence even further, and in the Far East Japan’s code of bushido became ingrained in that culture. By the time gunpowder and gasoline made war a butcher’s business rather than a glorious adventure, every nation had its own military traditions, stretching back generations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MILITARY_TRAINING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Military training isn’t just about getting teenagers to keep step so they don’t trip over each other, or to all point their spears in the same direction so they don’t stab each other; military training includes getting them to follow orders (even senseless ones), to get and stay fit, and to kill (preferably without being killed, but that’s of secondary importance).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MILITARY_TRAINING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In militant civilizations, such as the Spartan and the Zulu, compulsory state-sponsored military training started in early childhood. In Sparta, the education system – the Agoge – emphasized obedience, endurance, courage, and self-control … and that loyalty to the state came ahead of all other concerns. By contrast, the goal of the Athenian education system was to produce thinkers trained in the arts and sciences, although prepared for war; young boys learned calisthenics and ball games, while older boys practiced ever more militaristic activities such as running, boxing, and wrestling.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MILITARY_TRAINING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Vegetius states that the Romans trained first for marching and fitness before even being allowed to train with weapons. Initially the new soldiers used wicker shields and wooden weapons, then graduated to the gladius, and finally were taught to use the pilum. So important was training for the imperial army that roofed halls were built for drill and sparring so these could continue even in winter. Far to the east in China, the military was – with the exception of a few professionals – made up of conscripts levied from the masses; although specifics varied from dynasty to dynasty, in general those in the Xianzu (reserves) were forcefully enrolled for a short stint of military training at the age of 20.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MILITARY_TRAINING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>In feudal Japan those of the samurai class were born into austere lives of brutal training and conditioning. Although training regimes differed as much as the samurai themselves, some tenets remained constant throughout Japanese history: mental preparation, physical training, personal fortitude, along with unarmed and armed combat techniques. It is an ideal of military training still emulated around the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MOBILIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since the first chieftain called upon all his able-bodied subjects to pick up their clubs and follow him, mobilization has been the prerogative of governments. But “mobilization” has been around only since the mass levy of forces by the Directory to defend the French Revolution. By the time of the American Civil War new technologies – notably the telegraph and the railroad – had moved nations towards a more efficient manner of conscripting and assembling troops. It is estimated that the Confederate States of America mobilized about 11% of its (free) population for the war, and that Prussia could mobilize 75% of its reservists quickly … which it did with great effect for the Second Schleswig War, Austro-Prussian War, and Franco-Prussian War.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MOBILIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Two rapidly-industrializing nations – Great Britain and the United States – led the world in planning for mobilization. The British needed a way to get lots of Redcoats to distant places to maintain their empire; and the United States needed a way to get lots of Bluecoats to distant places to build theirs. Great Britain, when faced with the Boers in Africa, was quickly able to mobilize its troops and pound them into submission; America, spurred by a Cuban independence movement, was equally successful at bringing their might to bear on the hapless Spanish in the Caribbean and Philippines. The rest of Europe took note, and when first Austria and then Russia began mobilizing in the wake of the assassination of Archduke Ferdinand in July 1914, all the great powers did so as well.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MOBILIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Two decades later they were all at it again, sparked when Poland instituted a partial mobilization on 24 August in the face of a German buildup along the borders. Within days the British and French had both mobilized … Germany, Italy and the Soviet Union were in a semi-permanent state of mobilization anyway. In the aftermath, most of the “Free World” powers followed America’s lead when it passed the National Security Act of 1947, an all-encompassing plan to implement rapid mobilization and deployment. Although as the Cold War progressed, such elaborate plans became moot under the shadow of the mushroom cloud.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MYSTICISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term “mysticism” is derived from the Greek term meaning “to conceal.” In the Hellenic civilization, it referred to “secret” rituals … not necessarily religious, for it lacked any connotations of the transcendental or divine. But then the Christians got hold of the word and it came to refer to the “hidden” allegorical interpretations of the Scriptures or to “hidden” presences, such as that of Christ at the Eucharist. Then the Christians bent it again, using it to denote three “theological” intertwined aspects of the divine: the biblical, the liturgical and the spiritual (or contemplative for non-Christians). Typically, mystics – theistic or not – view their mystical experiences as a stage in human transformation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MYSTICISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Thus, by the Renaissance – when mysticism abounded – it might be best thought of as a constellation of practices, discourses, texts, institutions, traditions and experiences all aimed at transcendence. Ironically, it also got condemned by the Church, and a lot of mystics – who became identified with the occult – got tortured and burned in their quest for transformation to another state of existence. Later, as human horizons expanded with the Enlightenment, so the threads of all sorts of mysticism got tangled: Christian, Jewish, Islamic, Buddhist, Taoist, Hindu, Tantric and so forth. The coming of modernity didn’t put these mystical fires out, only threw gasoline on them.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MYSTICISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Psychologists such as Carl Jung sought to combine the “authenticity” of science with the mysticism of the spiritual in a search for “undiscovered paths to the unconscious self” that could lead a man towards “realizing his real nature and attaining his real goal.” Of course, the mystics never did quite define what that goal is supposed to be. Whether apophatic (indescribable) or kataphatic (shareable), theurgic (such as the Jewish kabbalah) or theologic, whether the mystic seeks a “union” or an “identity” with a higher intelligence, mysticism persists into the 21st Century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_NATIONALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to political scientists, nationalism “arises and flourishes in modern societies described as being associated with having an industrial economy capable of self-sustainability of the society, a central supreme authority capable of maintaining authority and unity, and a centralized language or small group of centralized languages understood by the community of people.” Simply put, nationalism is overweening patriotism, an identification first with one’s country rather than town, region, or extended family. The roots of it can be traced back to the Hebrews, but they weren’t alone, for in the following centuries this nationalistic pride was found among the Greeks, Romans, Chinese, and Catholic Europe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_NATIONALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The growth of the middle classes, their growing desire for political power, and the subsequent development of democratic thinking helped fuel the rise of nationalism. But it was the French Revolution that gave birth to nationalistic expression. To those revolutionary thinkers that undertook the Terror, the “nation” was inseparable from the “people,” and for the first time a people would create a government in accordance with their collective will, glorifying the nation through the principles of liberty, equality and brotherhood. Thus began the political transformation of civilization. Meanwhile, German philosophers such as Hegel and Herder argued that a sense of nationality held modern societies together, through cultural self-expressions of nationhood. Then the Napoleonic wars spurred all sorts of folk to resist foreign domination (whether by emperors or revolutionaries) based on racial, ethnic, linguistic or religious identification.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_NATIONALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>As the Holy Roman Empire fell apart, and the Austro-Hungarian and Ottoman ones stumbled, all sorts of peoples found a nationalistic voice – the Poles, Greeks, Magyars, among others. On the periphery, campaigns for independence fueled by rampant nationalism in Ireland, Norway and Bulgaria made progress. The unruly small kingdoms in Germany and Italy coalesced into new nations, each with a common sense of identity and destiny. And in Serbia all this managed to ignite a world war … driven by nationalism.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_NATURAL_HISTORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A beautiful, old-fashioned term but puzzling … since everyone knows what “natural” means and what “history” is, isn’t “natural history” the study of non-human life on Earth in the past? No, it isn’t. Natural History is the study of animals, plants, fungi and such in their environment. Leaning on observational rather than experimental research, natural historians tend to wander about grubby places and occasionally publish.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_NATURAL_HISTORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Aristotle was the first to apply reason to what he observed of the diversity of nature, but it was Pedanius Dioscorides who first found practical applications for natural history in pharmacology. The medicinal uses of nature remained the primary emphasis of the field through the 18th Century AD. Throughout, the major principle of natural history was the scala naturae (or “Great Chain of Being”) decreed by God, an arrangement on a linear scale of all things – minerals, plants, primitive animals to more complex animals – in increasing perfection, culminating in humanity. It was a concept quite acceptable to the Catholic Church.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_NATURAL_HISTORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Until that is, the exploration of the wider world during the Renaissance brought all sorts of new organisms to light. The rapid increase in the number of known species prompted attempts at systematic classification of these into taxonomic groups, culminating in the revolutionary system of Swedish scientist Carl Linnaeus published in 1735. Study of natural history, once freed of the heavy hand of the Church, expanded phenomenally. Commencing in 1749 and continuing through 1804, the Histoire Naturelle, générale et particuliere was an encyclopedic collection of everything known of natural history compiled by the Comte de Buffon in 36 volumes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_NATURAL_HISTORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>By the Industrial era, natural history was all the rage. Amateur naturalists crawled out of every garden, and explorers kept bringing back odd creatures from distant places. Across Europe and the Americas natural history societies sprang into being, and gigantic public museums – such as those in London and Washington – were built to display bones, pelts and bugs on pins for the edification of school children for all time.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_NAVAL_TRADITION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mankind has been fighting battles on water for over three millennia; the first recorded sea battle occurred supposedly about 1210 BC when Suppiluliuma of the Hittites defeated a fleet from Cyprus and then burned their merchant fleet. It was the start of the long naval tradition of carrying conflict to sea, and plundering the neighbor’s seaborne trade.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_NAVAL_TRADITION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Obviously, those civilizations with extensive coastlines or lots of islands tend (but not always) to develop a tradition of staining the sea red quicker than their less fortunate neighbors. Thus, the rowed ships of ancient Greece and Carthage dominated the Mediterranean, in which opposing ships tried to ram or board one another (in essence, just bludgeoning away like armies did on land). In ancient China the war junk was developed, although the first standing Chinese navy didn’t come into existence until Song dynasty of the 12th Century AD; meanwhile the Chola dynasty of medieval India was the greatest naval power of the region at the time.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_NAVAL_TRADITION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>By the time the Middle Ages rolled around in Europe, a number of kingdoms had renowned naval traditions: the Vikings, the English, the Dutch, the Spanish, and Portuguese. These traditions would help them “discover” the faraway lands and slaughter the indigenous people so Europeans could settle there. The cogs, caravels, and carracks not only made the oared ships obsolete but could survive crossing the vast, open oceans. Not surprisingly, these ocean-going kingdoms also managed to cobble together great maritime trading empires as the Middle Ages morphed into the Renaissance.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_NAVAL_TRADITION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Then came gunpowder, and naval warfare changed forever. Gone were the days of maneuvering so a ship could slam its prow into the side of another as infantry stormed over the railings, replaced by maneuvering so a ship could unleash its broadside into the hapless enemy. A development that favored those nations that already had a strong naval tradition.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_NUCLEAR_PROGRAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When “Trinity” was detonated in New Mexico in July 1945 AD, it was the culmination of a centuries-long science project. Uranium had been discovered in 1789 by the German chemist Martin Klaproth. Wilhelm Rontgen received the Nobel Prize for his discovery of ionizing radiation in 1895; then in 1898 Pierre and Marie Curie isolated radium from pitchblende, the same year that Samuel Prescott showed that radiation destroyed bacteria (and other living things). Between 1898 and 1938, more discoveries followed … until Hahn and Strassmann finally proved that atomic fission had occurred in their experiments. Lise Meitner, Otto Frisch and Niels Bohr calculated that the energy released from nuclear fission as about 200 million volts, a figure Frisch confirmed experimentally in January 1939.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_NUCLEAR_PROGRAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The world war brought civilization the Manhattan Project, as the United States raced to be the first nation to build an “atomic” bomb. The horrendous result of all this science was a device known as “Little Boy” that was dropped on Hiroshima on 6 August 1945, destroying 12 square kilometers and killing around 75 thousand (exact estimates are difficult to determine since 90% of the doctors and 93% of the nurses in the city died in the explosion). By December 1945, another 75 thousand survivors had died of radiation poisoning. When Japan didn’t surrender unconditionally immediately, Truman ordered a second bomb dropped on the city of Nagasaki, with similar results. Japan surrendered.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_NUCLEAR_PROGRAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>But now everyone wanted “the bomb.” Throughout the 1950s and 1960s the U.S. and USSR competed for nuclear supremacy until a point of MAD (“mutually assured destruction”) was reached. During the same decades, Anglo-American cooperation brought the British the bomb, and China was made a nuclear power in 1964 by a subsequently regretful Russia. France developed nuclear weapons on its own. Since then these five powers have tried to put the apocalyptic genie back in the box – but all sorts have embarked on nuclear programs: India, Pakistan, Israel, Libya, Iran, and North Korea.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_OPERA_BALLET_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once European civilization had an educated, wealthy elite with too much time on their collective hands and looking for something to set themselves apart from tasteless commoners, the world was ready for opera and ballet. Jacopo Peri, around 1597 AD, composed what is considered the first opera for a group of Florentine humanists (The Florentine Camerata). Meanwhile, during that century ballet evolved as an outgrowth of courtly dances in Renaissance Italy, and developed its iconic forms in France. During the Baroque era, both became ever more refined (i.e., divorced from the music and dance of those crude commoners) in Naples, Vienna, Paris and other cultural centers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_OPERA_BALLET_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>At the beginning of the Baroque era, opera seria was the dominant style, with stories derived from classical mythology and the lead parts sung by famous castrati. But whereas these operas focused on the poetry of the words, by the end of the era this had given way to the primacy of the vocal virtuosity, the bel canto approach. During the so-called “golden age of opera,” composers such as Verdi and Wagner developed distinctive, national traditions. During the years following the French Revolution, a new, industrialist middle class had the money to frequent the theater, driven to be “cultured.” A wave of Romanticism swept across Europe, and opera became more accessible to those jumped-up commoners; in a couple decades even the lower classes could enjoy opera, for the phonograph and then radio brought the caterwauling right into their hovels.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_OPERA_BALLET_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In the 16th Century, Catherine de Medici – wife of Henry II of France and patron of the arts (among other things) – sponsored displays of refined dance, the ballet de cour, for the edification of noblemen and women at her lavish court events. A century later Louis XIV, a passionate fan of dance, sought to popularize and standardize ballet; in 1661 he helped establish the Académie Royale de Danse in Paris. By 1681 performances of ballet had moved from the court to the stage, and early ballets of the Romantic era such as Giselle and La Sylphide proved popular far beyond France … especially in Tsarist Russia. Russian composers and choreographers produced soaring works such as The Nutcracker, Swan Lake and The Sleeping Beauty, which even the layman could appreciate through wars and revolutions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_RAPID_DEPLOYMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Most First World nations now have military formations capable of quick deployment into the field at short notice; as opposed to “Quick Deployment Forces” (which are local in nature – such as the American National Guard), “Rapid Deployment Forces” (RDF) are meant for outside the borders of the home country. In general, these RDF consist of elite formations, such as the American 82nd Airborne Division, 75th U.S. Ranger Regiment, or British Royal Marines. All have the mission of having combat troops “wheels up” and battle-ready within 18 hours of notification, and all are trained in “forced entry” into enemy territory to seize and secure key places (such as airfields or beaches) for follow-up units.</Text>   
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_RAPID_DEPLOYMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The history of rapid deployment forces is rich and varied, as with most elite military units. Marines are perhaps the oldest such formations, and trace their antecedents back to the naval landing shore parties of Peter the Great and the U.S. Marine Corps was originally established by the Continental Congress in 1775. The latter earned its “rapid” reputation during such battles as the First Barbary War, the Mexican-American War, the Boxer Rebellion, and during dozens of missions to protect American interests around the globe. In Europe, meanwhile, light infantry units such as grenz, chasseur, and jager (depending on national preferences) formations were established that could be quickly mobilized and transported to the border. In time, airborne and air mobile units were added to the mix.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_RAPID_DEPLOYMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>With the onset of the Cold War, both sides developed RDF orders-of-battle that incorporated units from several services. In Great Britain, the Joint Rapid Reaction Force consisted of a pool of specialized units from all three armed forces, capable of mounting operations under the auspices of NATO, the European Union or the United Nations. The United States created its own Rapid Deployment Joint Task Force in March 1980 with the specific mission to “help maintain regional stability and the Gulf oil-flow westward.” In Russia, the Collective Rapid Reaction Force formed in 2009 has largely supplanted the Soviet VDV (airborne) units used for such purposes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_POLITICAL_PHILOSOPHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>At its most basic, political philosophy is focused on the concept of the creation of government; what form it should take; what is meant by the likes of liberty, justice, the law and other civilized fictions; and the rights (minimal) and duties (just about everything else) of the citizens. As might be imagined, political philosophers do not agree on much. In fact, the meaning of the term “political” is itself one of the most contentious topics.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_POLITICAL_PHILOSOPHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Political philosophy had its beginning in ethical debates on questions as to what constitutes a “good life.” Since people are by nature sociable – there being few proper hermits about – the question follows as to how a person should behave in the company of others. Chinese political philosophy dates from the Warring States Period, specifically to the writings of Confucius in the 6th Century BC. The first work of Western political philosophy is the Republic by Plato, who sought solutions for what he saw as injustice and inequity; to do so, he proposed the first of what would be many utopian (in that they are “moral”) political systems. Roman political philosophy was heavily influenced by the Stoics, and so tended to be a bit more pragmatic.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_POLITICAL_PHILOSOPHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>After some centuries taking a more theological approach, Renaissance political philosophy returned to the pragmatic – as embodied by the works of Niccolo Machiavelli. Then a bunch of intellectuals … Rousseau, Hobbes, Locke, Montesquieu and the like … began spouting off about the “social contract,” human rights, equality and such, leading to a number of revolutions, especially the French one that turned civilization on its head. To confuse things even further, with industrialism taking hold, Marxist political philosophers (Marx, Engels, Lenin, etc.) proposed yet another sort of political structure – radical socialism – as the only “correct” form of government … leading to yet another bloody revolution.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_POLITICAL_PHILOSOPHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>And political philosophers have yet to agree as to who is right …</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_PROFESSIONAL_SPORTS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Throughout most of human history, men have worked hard to have “fun” and enjoy their leisure time. Leisure was primarily a privilege for the affluent; everyone else faced an incessant struggle for food, shelter, clothing and safety. While folks had always enjoyed playing and watching sports, especially team sports, these had generally been amateur competitions – setting aside those bloody chariot races in Rome, ball games in Mesoamerica and polo matches in Persia. But with the leisure “industry” exploding during the Industrial Revolution and people willing to pay to watch paid athletes compete, and all those empty hours to fill for the working class, well … professional sports.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_PROFESSIONAL_SPORTS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Public school sports and club sports in England had been the rage since the 1660s, and in the mid-1700s the first “first class” (semi-professional) teams in cricket were formed. Meanwhile, the Industrial Revolution was raging. As the masses moved to the cities they brought their rural sports with them; and advances in transport and communication opened opportunities for university teams to compete against each other. This all sparked efforts to impose standard rules, and in 1848 AD the Cambridge Rules codified the play of association football (known as soccer in some backward places). This in turn led to the establishment of the Football Association in 1863 in London, the first governing body of a spectator sport; the year before, the Notts County Football Club was paying some of its players, making it the oldest professional club in the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_PROFESSIONAL_SPORTS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Meanwhile, across the pond, following the Civil War the sport of baseball captured the attention of the masses in northeastern America. Since money seemed a great incentive to play hard, several early baseball teams put their players on salary, the first being the Cincinnati Red Stockings beginning in 1869. In 1871 the first professional baseball league was created, and by the beginning of the 1900s most large cities in the eastern United States had one or more professional teams, divided in National and American divisions. And sports haven’t been “fun” since.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_RECORDED_HISTORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Understanding the past appears to be yet another basic human need, and the recording of history emerged independently in civilizations throughout ancient history. The earliest simple chronologies date back to ancient Mesopotamia and Egypt. But the first actual factual (more-or-less) history that wasn’t just carved into tombs and temples was the “Twenty-Four Histories” of China, the official accounts of the dynasties there from C. 3000 BC through the Ming dynasty of the 17th Century AD. Starting with the Tang, each dynasty established an official post to write the history of its predecessor using court records; eventually this amounted to 3213 volumes (of sometimes dubious worth).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_RECORDED_HISTORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In Western civilization, Herodotus of Halicarnassus (c. 450 BC) is generally acclaimed as the “Father of History” although it was his contemporary Thucydides who actually approached history as a methodical account of true events. Unlike Herodotus, Thucydides regarded history as the product of choices made by human beings, a matter of cause and effect rather than divine intervention as Herodotus (and later a whole bunch of Christian scholars) did. Through the Medieval and Renaissance periods, events were seen (and recorded) through the lens of religion. It was left to the German Georg Friedrich Hegel to return to a secular approach to history; Hegel himself was simply refining the approach of the Arab historian Ibn Khaldun, who argued that the past was a strange landscape and in need of interpretation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_RECORDED_HISTORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The apex of Enlightenment history was reached with Edward Gibbon’s monumental six-volume work on the decline and fall of the Roman Empire, published in 1776. With its stress on objectivity and the use of primary sources, it made Gibbons the first “modern historian.” A claim also made about Leopold von Ranke (1795-1886), who focused on archival research and the analysis of historical documents with an emphasis on narrative history. By the time the French Annales School and Marxist-Leninist approaches looked to interpret history in new ways, history was no longer just a factual account but offered insights into how … and why … civilization came to be like it is.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_REFORMED_CHURCH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>It is said that a little rebellion now and then is a good thing, but rarely does it spark as profound a change as the Protestant Reformation of the 16th Century. A German theologian named Martin Luther struck the match by protesting the Catholic Church’s plenary indulgence, the practice allowing the wealthy to literally buy their way out of Hell. These ideas took hold amongst a swiftly growing ranks of protesters throughout Europe, eventually leading to a religious schism from the Church. Soon Lutheranism spread throughout the Holy Roman Empire, Reformed churches sprang up in Switzerland and the Netherlands, and Presbyterian congregations formed in Scotland. (Meanwhile, Henry VIII of England founded the Anglican Church to divorce his wife and marry the younger Anne Boleyn.)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_REFORMED_CHURCH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>A weakening was already under way in Catholicism, as humanism and the Scientific Revolution challenged accepted “holy” writ. Moreover, free thinking was abroad in the thriving urban cities and among the emerging (and determined) middle class. As often happens, this Reformation came with a lot of blood; the Thirty Years War devastated Germany and killed an estimated 25% to 40% of its population as the Holy Roman Empire sought to reassert Catholicism. The Peace of Westphalia in 1648 AD finally ended the war by insuring that each sovereign had the right to determine the religion of his state, and that Christians living everywhere had the right to practice their faith in public (during specified hours, that is).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_REFORMED_CHURCH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Reform in religion is not, certainly, limited to Christianity. Reform movements within Islam and Judaism have led to new branches of the parent faith rather than schism. In these, the reformers have attempted to adapt the traditional “church” to liberal, human-rights oriented values. These movements grew out of differences in interpretation of core values, emphasizing the evolving nature of their obligations and practices. Similar movements have evolved Buddhism and Hinduism, as these ancient religions seek relevance in modern civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_SCORCHED_EARTH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>War is never simply about defeating enemy armies. To win, one must destroy an enemy’s means and morale to carry on the war. This kind of desolation was all too familiar to civilians from ancient times through the late Renaissance, but the Industrial Revolution’s many advancements turned rapid, wholesale destruction into a legitimate military strategy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_SCORCHED_EARTH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>A scorched earth policy removes or destroys an enemy’s capacity to wage war—food, supplies, infrastructure, or anything else that the enemy could find useful. Czar Alexander I of Russia stalled and starved Napoleon Boneparte’s 1812 invasion by ordering the Russian countryside burned. This defensive scorched earth strategy allowed Alexander to destroy his nation’s own farmland rather than allow the Grand Army to live off the land. In the American Civil War, General William T. Sherman brought scorched earth to his enemy’s territory. Sherman’s “March to the Sea” ravaged hundreds of miles of railroad, ransacked millions of pounds of food, and burned military targets and civilian property alike.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_SCORCHED_EARTH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>While many nations practiced some degree of scorched earth warfare, World War II saw it occur on a grand scale—tragically apparent during the German invasion of the Soviet Union. What Soviet forces didn’t destroy during the German advance, German forces did when they retreated three years later. The horrendous, large-scale effects on the civilian population, seen again during conflicts in Korea and Vietnam, led to the strategy being banned under the 1977 Geneva Convention.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_SOCIAL_MEDIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>ICYMI, social media contains all one needs to know about human civilization … or at least those bits of it that the connected people know. Except perhaps whether social media is the boon or the curse of the 21st Century. BTAIM, they’re not even sure exactly how it got started. LMAO.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_SOCIAL_MEDIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>B4 there was Six Degrees, weblogs or My Space, it started with the first dial-up BBS launched by Ward Christensen and Randy Suess in Chicago in February 1978 AD. These primitive online meeting places were independently-produced hunks of code that allowed users to communicate through a central server where they could download files and post public messages. These text-only services quickly became popular with BFFs through WOM, and through the 1980s and early 1990s various services – such as FidoNet – arose to link these BBSs together into world-wide messaging boards. Meanwhile, commercial services such as CompuServe expanded into the public domain, offering discussion forums on all manner of subjects … and a newfangled service termed “email.” FOMO brought thousands of Gen-Xers into the fold. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_SOCIAL_MEDIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In 1997 the first site that everyone can agree was a SMP was launched: SixDegrees.com. Lasting only until 2001 due to a proliferation of SPAM, it allowed subscribers to create an updateable profile of themselves, and then “friend” other users. FYI, by 2000 around 100 million people had access to the Internet; all manner of users were utilizing chat rooms for discussion, dating and sharing. The first social media surge followed shortly after with the launch of LinkedIn (2002) and MySpace (2003). But IMHO it was 2004 and the launch of Facebook by Mark Zuckerberg and 2006 and the launch of Twitter by Jack Dorsey that established the “connected” world of social media. Today, on these and dozens of other services (Flickr, Tumblr, Habbo, Sina Weibo, etc.) virtually any text, video, audio or image file can be shared on all sorts of devices, even mobile ones … although TBH, it is becoming ever harder to separate the wheat from the chaff.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_SOCIAL_MEDIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>DFTBA … IRL.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_SPACE_RACE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>After the war, the United States and the Soviet Union recruited, coerced or simply kidnapped hundreds of surviving German scientists … and none so numerous as those who had worked on the Nazi rocket programs. As the Cold War heated up, space became yet another field of competition for the two superpowers as each side sought to prove the superiority of its technology (and, by extension, its political-military-economic system). At first, the intent was to be able to launch bigger versions of the German V-2 rockets, ones capable of carrying a warhead to distant cities. But soon, some slightly-mad visionaries saw a “better” use for those ballistic missiles; in 1955 AD, just four days apart, both nations separately and publically announced they would place an artificial satellite in orbit by 1957 or ’58.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_SPACE_RACE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Soviets won the first leg of the space race, launching Sputnik I into orbit on October 1957; four months after, the German von Braun (who headed the American effort) and his team put Explorer I atop a four-stage Juno I in Cape Canaveral and fired it off. Over the next few years, several hapless dogs and monkeys were shot into orbit on one-way trips, all leading up to the Soviets launching Yuri Gagarin into orbit in April 1961 … who enjoyed a round-trip. Once again the Americans had lost the race by just months, with John Glenn orbiting the Earth in Friendship 7 in February 1962. When U.S. President Kennedy made his bold claim that America would land a man on the moon before the end of the decade, things heated up again.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_SPACE_RACE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The next years were marked with some spectacular failures (exploding rockets make for great images), for both the Soviets and the Americans, but culminating with the launch of Apollo 8 in 1968, the first manned mission to orbit the moon. On 20 July 1969, American astronaut Neil Armstrong proclaimed “one small step for man, one giant leap for mankind.” In July 1975, with relations between Russia and America thawing, the first joint mission – the Apollo-Soyuz docking – meant the space race was over.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_STATE_WORKFORCE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Work began with Homo sapiens; along with tool making, a complex brain structure, and a spoken language, the organization of labor was responsible for mankind’s conquest of nature and certainly differentiated human beings from other animals. In Oriental Despotism, the historian Karl Wittfogel makes a strong case that the large-scale irrigation projects in ancient Mesopotamia and Egypt built by laborers conscripted by the state brought civilization: work specialization, the emergence of social classes, organized government, and cultural hierarchy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_STATE_WORKFORCE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Save for the militia army (of course) the ability to “draft” a state workforce for monumental public works projects was the ancient ruler’s primary display of power and “concern” for his subjects. In time, these public projects took on all sorts of forms; the Great Pyramid at Giza used some 100 thousand workers over 20 years, and the Great Wall in China employed even more conscripts over generations. In these and other projects, the workers were mostly peasants (rather than slaves, who were much too valuable to waste by the thousands building such wonders), serving the state as a form of service tax. The Romans pioneered advanced organizational techniques for their skilled state workforce to build the infrastructure that made Rome a millennial empire: roads, aqueducts, public baths, harbors, docks, lighthouses and entertainment venues such as the Colosseum and Circus Maximus.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_STATE_WORKFORCE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Labor service to the state took various forms, but all entailed some sort of unpaid, unfree work. Popular in Western civilization was corvée, labor that was intermittent in nature and for limited periods; in ancient times for a single, massive project, evolving in the Far East to be a certain number of days each year at the lord’s behest. Serfdom was the standard under feudalism, with the peasants required to work for the “Lord of the Manor” in whatever capacity he (or she) might deem necessary … including helping with the monarch’s or Catholic Church’s latest construction folly. Then came the Industrial Revolution’s debt-bondage and wage-slavery … although collective bargaining, minimum wage, child labor laws, prisoners’ rights, and the 40-hour week have pretty much done away with a state workforce.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_SUFFRAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Suffrage – the odd notion that everyone in a democracy deserves to vote. Before the first of a series of reforms in 1832 AD in the United Kingdom, only 3% of the adult male population was “qualified” to vote. In general, both in the Americas and in Europe, the right to vote depended on how much one earned and the value of his property. Thus, the majority of people who could vote were both wealthy and male. Throughout the early 1800s idealists fought to extend the franchise to women, the un-wealthy, immigrants, and various minorities with some concessions won (such as the 1870 15th Amendment in the United States). But, largely, voting was still a white, middle-class, male privilege.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_SUFFRAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>While the history of universal suffrage is a hodge-podge of reform movements and civil protests and editorial diatribes, the most visible (and noisy) were women’s efforts in the United States and Great Britain to get to vote. Although full female enfranchisement was still decades away in most places, there had been some brief instances of women having the vote: in Sweden-Finland 1718 to 1772, Corsica 1755 through 1769, and even in New Jersey in 1776 (it was rescinded in 1807).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_SUFFRAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In the United States, the campaign for women’s suffrage began in earnest in 1848 when a group of abolitionists, mostly women, gathered in Seneca Falls to discuss women’s rights in a democracy. The outcome, a significant – and sometimes violent – effort to gain the vote. Meanwhile in the United Kingdom, following the flawed 1832 Reform Act, suffrage became a political topic, leading to the formation of the National Society for Women’s Suffrage in 1867 and the even more militant Women’s Social and Political Union in 1903. Although the process was delayed by the distraction of the First World War, in 1920 in the United States and in 1928 in the United Kingdom women were finally given full voting rights … well after New Zealand (1893) and Finland (1906).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_THEOLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once civilization created organized religion, it was inevitable that theologians would follow. Theology is a “philosophical discipline concerned with religious speculation and apologetics” focused on the divine and sacred, humanity and “god,” salvation, and eschatology. In its efforts to be as applicable and systematic as any science, theology has spawned a host of “isms”: agnosticism, atheism, deism, dualism, monotheism, pantheism, polytheism, animism, totemism and such. Although certainly applicable to all religions, theology has been a major thread primarily in the Abrahamic faiths – Judaism, Christianity, Islam, and their offshoots.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_THEOLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The philosopher Plato identified the term “theology” with the mythical, which might have a temporary pedagogical significance but that would eventually be cleansed from the rational state. This identification of theology with mythology remained common throughout the Mediterranean civilizations until the Christians took umbrage and declared that theology was a means of proclaiming the divine, of confessing to it, and of preaching this confession. Thus, by the early Medieval Era theology was the attempt by adherents to make a logical and reasonable statement of faith, to explicate that statement in terms of rationalism, and to place it in the context of the “real” world as well as the spiritual. By the Renaissance, theologians were striving mightily to distance themselves from mysticism and be taken seriously by other academic disciplines.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_THEOLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>During the late Middle Ages and early Renaissance, theology was the ultimate subject at most universities, being labelled the “Queen of the Sciences” and serving as the capstone for the Trivium and Quadrivium that learned young men were expected to master. Theology’s eminent place in the university curriculum finally began to be challenged during the Enlightenment, especially in Germany. Most of the unresolved debate since has centered on whether theology’s methods are appropriately theoretical and scientific.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_THE_ENLIGHTENMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Enlightenment was a sprawling intellectual, philosophical, cultural, social movement marked by empiricism, scientific rationalism and reductionism displayed in the questioning of religious and political orthodoxy. It sprang from the thinking of several influential thinkers writing in different places on different subjects – politics, science, religion, aesthetics – and spread across Europe, the several currents mixing and mutating. In short, it was a tidal wave of rationalism … and swept civilization into a new channel.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_THE_ENLIGHTENMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The power of reason was first explored by the philosophers of ancient Greece, towering thinkers such as Plato, Aristotle, Zeno, Socrates, and Thales of Miletus. The Romans adopted and adapted Greek thinking to include their thinking on a rational natural order and natural laws, but most of this was rejected by the Church in the following centuries, until Thomas Aquinas resurrected reason as a tool of understanding … although he subordinated it to spiritual revelation of the revealed truths of the Church. Soon a rediscovery of the ancient classics, humanism, experimental science, the Renaissance and the Protestant Reformation brought about a new way of thinking. Thinkers such as Bacon, Galileo and Copernicus challenged Church dogma about the ways the universe works; the likes of Voltaire, Diderot, Rousseau, Hume and Smith offered new thoughts on the human condition. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_THE_ENLIGHTENMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Some historians date the Enlightenment from 1715 (the year Louis XIV died) to 1789 AD (the beginning of the French Revolution), for it was during this period that great thinkers circulated their thinking through meetings at scientific academies and societies, literary salons, Masonic lodges, and especially through printed books and pamphlets. Especially virulent were the concepts of rational politics, as thinkers such as John Locke and Thomas Hobbes and Thomas Paine espoused individual rights, the social contract and representative government. This was appalling thinking to the monarchs and the church. And such thinking led to various revolutions, the Napoleonic wars, the Industrial Revolution, and everything since.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_TOTALITARIANISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term 'totalitarismo' was first used by the “philosopher of fascism” Giovanni Gentile in the midst of the world-wide depression to convey the comforting sense of an “all-embracing, total state” which could provide security and prosperity for its citizens if they would but surrender some of their liberties. It can be argued that totalitarianism is an ancient concept, around for millennia. Under Minister Li Si, Legalism was the prevailing philosophy of the Qin dynasty: political activities were restricted, liberal literature destroyed, and those who did not conform summarily put to death. The rigid caste-based society envisioned by Plato in the 'Republic' has many totalitarian traits, and Machiavelli’s 'The Prince' offered still more totalitarian ideals.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_TOTALITARIANISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>A number of political philosophers and historians have taken up the subject of totalitarianism. Although they don’t agree on much else (such as how effective it may be, under what circumstances and with what results), they do agree that there are five key features that together distinguish a totalitarian state: an official ideology to which general adherence is mandated; a single party, hierarchically organized, interwoven with the state bureaucracy; monopolistic control of the armed forces; monopolistic control of the mass media; a system of terroristic police control; central direction of the state’s capitalist economy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_TOTALITARIANISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Although it may be inconceivable that any rational person would willingly give up political pluralism and individual liberty, true liberalism contains a contradiction: unrestrained pursuit of personal liberty is a threat to others, and therefore to society. And pluralism can lead to paralysis. With their stress on the social rather than the individual, and battered by the political and economic chaos following the First World War, a number of political leaders promoted totalitarianism (indeed, there were totalitarian movements in most countries) and some came to power: Benito Mussolini in Italy (1922), António Salazar in Portugal (1932), Adolf Hitler in Germany (1933) and Francisco Franco in Spain (1936). And quite a few since … in Argentina, Paraguay, Haiti, Albania, Angola, Iraq, Uganda, etc., etc., etc.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_URBANIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>It is estimated that by 2050 AD some 70% of the world’s population will live in urban areas, sucking up scarce resources and creating waste on an unprecedented scale in human civilization. It is a trend that has been advancing since the first towns arose in ancient Egypt, Mesopotamia, India and China when mankind finally moved beyond subsistence farming and primitive societies could afford to feed “useless” mouths – priests, philosophers, bureaucrats and the like. But cities were limited to the population that the local agriculture could support, “local” expanding as transportation expanded. Too, agricultural production was labor intensive, and there were only so many jobs available in towns for craftsmen and other trades. But the onset of the agricultural and industrial revolutions in the 18th Century shattered that millennia-old balance.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_URBANIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Only three percent of mankind lived in cities in 1800; by 1900 that figure had risen to 14 percent, and 12 cities had populations over a million each. Just a half-century later that percentage had doubled and there were 83 cities in the world numbering over a million humans. Cities just kept getting more crowded; the number of “mega-cities” – those with populations of ten million or more – rose from three in 1975 to 16 in 2000, and is projected to be 27 in 2025. All thanks to technology.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_URBANIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Sociologists have proposed that the Industrial Revolution threw off the four natural limits on the growth of urban centers: the distance to food and water supplies, the geographic extent of walls and fortifications, the speed of traffic (all those slow-moving oxcarts and pedestrians), and the availability of power. Steam engines and motor cars, natural gas and electricity, iceboxes and indoor plumbing, artillery and aeroplanes. The telephone and automobile brought yet another stage of urbanization in the early 20th Century, the phenomenon of suburbs. No longer did folk need to live near the factories and offices they labored in in the cities; now they could live in the “countryside” again.</Text>
		</Row>
	</BaseGameText>
</GameData>