<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Anton Strenger (Firaxis Games) -->
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<BaseGameText>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_INTRO_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
      <Text>Resources are sources of [ICON_Food] Food, [ICON_Production] Production, [ICON_Science] Science, [ICON_Gold] Gold, or [ICON_Culture] Culture, and they can provide special bonuses to a civilization. Your civilization's wealth and power will be determined by the number and kinds of resources you control to a large degree. To utilize a resource, it first must be within your civilization's borders, and then you must construct the appropriate "improvement" in that hex. For example, you must construct the Plantation improvement to get the benefit from a Banana resource.</Text>
    </Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_ALUMINUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Greeks and Romans used aluminum salts as astringents and bath powders. For centuries, that’s all aluminum was good for, until in 1825 AD the Danish chemist Hans Orsted managed to create a lump of aluminum metal. In the 1850s, pure aluminum was so difficult to produce that bars of it were more valuable than gold and even exhibited as a curiosity at the Exposition Universelle in 1855. Scientists, of course, just had to find uses for it, and now aluminum is found in everything from spacecraft to skillets.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_ANTIQUITY_SITE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Francis Bacon wrote in 1605 that "antiquities are history defaced, or some remnants of history which have casually escaped the shipwreck of time." Treasure hunters, grave robbers, and academics have been seeking “antiquities” to carry back to civilization for a millennium. By definition, antiquities are objects from the past, ranging from simple arrowheads to artistic treasures. The sense that a lost civilization could be uncovered by a systematic study of its relics and artifacts has driven amateur collectors and eminent scholars (and thieves) to seek out and dig these up at antiquity sites around the globe … including some of the most inhospitable places known. This passion for collecting the leavings of the human past eventually gave rise to a new academic discipline - the field of archaeology. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_BANANAS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Tasty and nutritious, bananas and the less-sweet plantains are the product of large, herbaceous, flowering plants found in tropical climates. First cultivated in New Guinea and Southeast Asia, records (mostly folk tales) suggest that bananas were first purposefully grown in the Kuk Swamp around 5000 BC. In time, traders carried banana plants to Madagascar, and the cultivation of these spread across Africa – to be discovered by Europeans looking for a new treat.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_CATTLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Whether beef, dairy, or draft animals, cattle in all their forms have been serving mankind since before history began. In fact, it appears that wild aurochs were domesticated at some point around 10,500 years ago in what is today Turkey. Evidence shows that cattle were being used as a medium of barter around 7000 BC in the Indian subcontinent. Ever since, cattle and oxen have supplied meat and milk, leather and horn, and been beasts of burden and objects of religious devotion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_CINNAMON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to the Roman writer Pliny, a Roman pound (about 11.5 ounces) of cinnamon cost up to 300 denarii … ten months wages for a common laborer in the city. Cinnamon has been used since antiquity, as a medicine, aphrodisiac, and to flavor both sweet and savory foods. It was imported into Egypt as early as 2000 BC, and was so highly prized among the Greeks that small amounts were given as gifts to Apollo at his temple at Miletus. So valuable was the spice that traders kept the source (the bark of Cinnamomum trees found in Sri Lanka and on the Malabar coast of India) secret for centuries.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_CITRUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The genus Citrus includes a number of flowering plants that produce a variety of fruits – including oranges, tangerines, grapefruit, limes, lemons, and others that have been a staple in the human diet for millennia. First cultivated in Southeast Asia, the fruits from these trees and shrubs are a fine source of vitamin C, a shortage of which brings scurvy … a debilitating condition that can lead to a rather nasty form of death. Hence, on long voyages, commanders found it beneficial to keep a store of citrus on hand.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_CLOVES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Cloves are the dried flower bud from a tree native to the Maluku Islands in Indonesia; an aromatic spice, it is used in cuisines worldwide. Now harvested primarily in Indonesia, India, Zanzibar, and Madagascar, cloves have a numbing effect on mouth tissues and have been used in the past as a medicine as well as a spice. Until planted outside the islands, the Dutch East India Company had a virtual monopoly on the spice; in Europe in the 17th and 18th centuries, cloves were quite literally worth their weight in gold due to the demand.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_COAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>From the Old English term col, meaning “mineral of fossilized carbon,” coal has been civilization’s primary source of heat for millennia – of homes, forges, smelters, electrical plants and such. Decomposed plant matter that has been compressed over millennia, coal was first used for carved ornaments dating back to c. 4000 BC found in the Shenyang region of China. Men have been stripping it out of the ground ever since.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_COCOA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Chocolate comes from cocoa beans, and cocoa beans come from the cacao tree, an evergreen native to Central and South America. Cultivation of the beans was extensive in early Mesoamerican civilizations; residue of chocolate drinks have been found in Olmec ruins dating back to c. 1750 BC. Introduced by the Spanish to Europe, by the mid-1700s cocoa was immensely popular there as a hot beverage, cooking ingredient, and even as a medicine.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_COFFEE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Coffee beans are cultivated in over 70 countries, and the bitter drink produced from them consumed worldwide. Like cocoa and tobacco, coffee acts as a stimulant … in this case due to the presence of caffeine, an adenosine antagonist. According to legend, it all began when Kaldi, a 9th Century Ethiopian, noticed that his goats became energized after nibbling beans from a wild coffee plant. Probably an apocryphal tale, but it is known that by the 15th Century coffee beans were being roasted, ground, and used in drinks across Arabia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_COPPER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Ductile with a high heat and electrical conductivity, copper has been used by men for thousands of years, since at least 8000 BC (giving name to the so-called Copper Age). But mostly it was used in alloys, such as bronze, brass, and cupronickel, all of which are a lot more durable and stronger, and hence good for things like armor and swords. Copper itself has some useful properties, not the least the fact humans need trace amounts in their diet to avoid some unpleasant debilitating conditions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_COSMETICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The use of cosmetics spans 6000 years and almost every civilization. In one way or another – ritual, religion, courtship, art – cosmetics have been a staple of being human. Even when frowned upon, as in ancient Rome (the wanton Cleopatra, for instance, was condemned for it) and ancient Israel (where Jezebel was lambasted for her painted eyes in the Old Testament). Even as late as 1900 AD using cosmetics was somehow disreputable, but the “Flapper Era” brought it to prominence in America and Europe, and made it a big business. The cosmetics industry has grown steadily ever since, driven by the “youth culture” prevalent today.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_COTTON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Cultivated since the early Indus Valley civilization some seven millennia ago, the cotton plant produces a soft fiber that ripens in a boll and can be easily harvested. Spun into yarn, the fiber results in a soft, pliable, light fabric, perfect for hot climes. It remains useful, with around 27.5 million tons produced annually. And cotton helped spur the Industrial Revolution, once mechanized spinning machines and the cotton gin were invented in the late 1700s.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_CRABS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Living in both salt and fresh water, and even on land, the various species (over 800) of crab have a thick exoskeleton and twin claws. Crabs have been a source of food for humans for millennia; today, they make up over 20% of all the marine crustaceans caught, farmed, and consumed worldwide. Pheromones are used by fully aquatic crabs to attract a mate – given how tasty they are, a necessary survival skill – while terrestrial dwelling crabs often use visual signals, such as male fiddler crabs waving their large claws to attract a female.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_DEER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Found in just about every climate and terrain on the planet, herds of deer have been hunted by primitives with spears (or now guns) for necessity and sport forever. During the Upper Paleolithic period, reindeer were the primary meat of Cro-Magnon people; in China, Homo erectus fed upon the sika deer; ancient Celts hunted red deer. Since deer were so plentiful (and so tasty), they also figured in the artistic culture and heraldry of many civilizations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_DIAMONDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Formed in the lithospheric mantle under conditions of extreme heat and pressure, lumps of metastable allotropes of carbon – better known as diamonds – have fueled wonder and greed in civilization since the days of ancient India. Found in deposits near the surface, by the 4th Century BC several Indian settlements were trading in diamonds, which inevitably found their way to Europe. Although uncut and unpolished – the technology for this wouldn’t be developed until the late 1300s – diamonds became a marker of power and privilege. They still are, although now faux diamonds can be made in labs.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_DYES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Humans have always liked bright colors. And civilizations seemingly forever have used color to signify role and rank, status and membership. Ancient peoples discovered that a wide variety of substances – plants, minerals, and animal bits – could be used to produce dyes to provide those bright colors. So, for some 37 thousand years folk have been dying fabric, paint, and their skin and hair.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_FISH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Rich in protein and oils and minerals, fish have been a staple in the diet of humans since the Paleolithic Age, some 40 thousand years ago. Shell middens, piles of fish bones, cave paintings, and analysis of the Tianyuan Man show that freshwater fish were regularly consumed by prehistoric primitives. As technology developed, especially in the realm of sea-going boats, fish and all things that came from them, became ever more available to civilizations. To the point now that overfishing the Earth’s oceans threatens to depopulate whole species.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_FURS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Homo sapiens have been wearing the pelts of fellow mammals since they wandered into the cold climes, about 125 thousand years ago. Once wool and flannel fabrics were developed, which were far more durable, warmer, and easier to keep clean, wearing furs was just an affectation. Nonetheless, several species were hunted to near extinction during the 1700s and 1800s – beaver, fox, mink, seal, the list goes on. Others were bred in captivity – ermine, sable, chinchilla, etc. – to be harvested for their coats. And the “fur trade” (think Hudson’s Bay Company) made some men very rich.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_GYPSUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Hard, but relatively easy to carve, gypsum is a sulfate, evaporate mineral found in deposits in sedimentary rock. A fine-grained, white or lightly tinted variety – alabaster – was used for sculptures and monuments by the ancient Egyptians, Mesopotamians, Romans, the Byzantines, and English during the Middle Ages. Fairly common, gypsum can be ground into a powder and used as fertilizer, to make plaster, and even in the preparation of various foods (bread, beer, and mead for instance), shampoos, and creams. There are few things in civilization as useful as gypsum.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_HORSES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The horse is one of the two remaining extant subspecies of Equus ferus, and one of the first animals humans domesticated sometime around 3500 BC in central Asia.  It seems horses were very useful for all that moving about and hunting that primitives needed to do. As beast of burden, military mount, companion, and occasional food source, the horse is likely the most important tamed animal in history.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_INCENSE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Incense, believed to have both medicinal and mystic qualities, is any material – usually some part of a plant – that gives off an aromatic smoke when burned. Incense is known to have been used extensively in both ancient Egypt and ancient India by 3300 BC. Besides its use in religious ceremonies, incense has been used in homes to cover the rich scent of crowded humanity, while the cloying fragrance helped mute the odor of decomposition in mummies for Egyptians.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_IRON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>By mass the most common element on Earth, with an atomic number of 26, iron is fairly malleable under heat … and fairly useful. Iron beads dating to about 3500 BC have been found in the excavations at Gerzah, Egypt. Iron proved useful for all kinds of things needed by early civilizations: cooking pots, hinges, tools, and pointy weapons to stab other people with.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_IVORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Harvested from the teeth and tusks of various animal species – elephant, whale, hippo, walrus, and the like – ivory’s luster and durability made it (before plastic proved better suited) one of the most valuable commodities in civilization. The Greeks, Romans, and Chinese prized it for its ability to be carved into long-lasting decorations, statuettes, cups, utensils, and false teeth. This was unfortunate for the animals, who were hunted to near extinction. The demand for ivory in 1831 AD in Great Britain alone accounted for the deaths of over 4000 elephants in that single year.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_JADE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Mongolia’s Hongshan culture and China’s Liangzhu culture, c. 3500 BC, jade was used for both utilitarian and ceremonial purposes. Surface deposits of the silicate mineral were easily mined in both regions. Jade was put to use in both India and Korea as well, although somewhat later. Even later, the elite in pre-Columbian Mesoamerica treasured it for its symbolic use in religious rituals. Jade has lost none of its allure, and is still prized by craftsmen and artists for its luster and ability to be carved into virtually any shape.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_JEANS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Invented by Jacob Davis and Levi Strauss in 1873, jeans were born of the need for a sturdier pair of pants during the western gold rush.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_MARBLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The ancients found marble as a building material durable and beautiful, more lasting than sandstone and easier to quarry than granite. Categorized by color and location, marble became a cultural standard of tradition and taste. Highly prized by the Greeks and Romans, marble was used by sculptors and engineers for those things meant to stand the test of time. Now they use concrete … less enduring but a lot cheaper.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_MERCURY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mercury – or quicksilver – is one of only two elements that is a liquid under normal conditions of temperature and pressure. Although known for centuries, it was more a curiosity than useful; in China and Tibet it was thought to prolong life and maintain vigor, while the Greeks put it in ointments, and the Romans in cosmetics (they’d all be shocked to learn it has serious adverse health effects). It wasn’t until the Scientific Revolution that it proved useful in things like thermometers, barometers, manometers, blood pressure gauges, mercury switches, and all kinds of other devices.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_NITER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Better known as saltpeter, niter is the mineral form of potassium nitrate. Although known for millennium, it didn’t become important until the Chinese figured out it could be combined with sulfur to make gunpowder in the mid-1st Century AD. And gunpowder is really good for making fireworks and blowing things up. Niter is also useful as a fertilizer and food preservative, but few people remember that.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_OIL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Oil greases the wheels of modern civilization, so to speak. For centuries before the coming of the internal combustion engine, oil was used for fire, lubrication, and to make asphalt. In 347 AD, oil was being produced from bamboo-drilled wells in China. But it wasn’t until 1847 when James Young discovered a method for distilling kerosene from oil that oil drilling became a booming industry. A boom only fueled by the discovery of the methods to refine gasoline from crude oil.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_PEARLS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Composed of calcium carbonate in concentric layers, a pearl is secreted by an oyster around something that is irritating its soft, inner tissues. Some people find these little coated irritations quite attractive, and so pearls have been highly prized for centuries. Since at least the 6th Century BC, divers in the Indian and Pacific oceans have brought pearls up from the depths to serve as jewelry, to be sewn onto clothing, and to grace crowns and thrones.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_PERFUME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Fragrant oils mixed with solvents and fixatives have been used by civilized man for millennia, because people sometimes smell. Ancient records and the findings of modern archeologists confirm the use of perfumes of various sorts – made from plants, animal parts, and even some minerals – since the first human settlements. The modern perfume industry, tracing its roots to the 14th Century Arabia and France, expanded aroma compounds with ever new concoctions. Maybe if they had known that perfumes can cause asthmatic attacks, allergic skin reactions, headaches or nausea, they wouldn’t have.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_RICE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Rice is a dietary staple of more than half of the world's human population, mostly in Asia. Chinese legend attributes the first cultivation of rice to Shennong, who “invented” agriculture. Whatever the truth of that, it is known that the ancient Egyptians were exporting rice, and large deposits of preserved rice have been found in Roman camps dating to the 1st Century AD. Rice remains vital to stave off famine; world production of rice has risen steadily from about 200 million tons in 1960 to 600 million tons in 2000.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_SALT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Used for preserving food and to season it when cooking, salt also just happens to be essential to animal life. The earliest evidence of the processing of salt dates back six millennia, to the ruins of salt works found in Romania and China. Salt can be mined, or extracted by evaporation of sea water, both processes simple enough even for illiterate barbarians to manage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_SHEEP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Domestic sheep are likely descendants of wild mouflon breeds found scattered across Europe and Asia. Sheepherding is the oldest documented occupation, commencing some 5000 years ago in Asia Minor. Men and their dogs kept the sheep safe from predators so the village could enjoy the wool and the mutton, both essential to the rise of the ancient Mesopotamian civilizations. The practice spread across Europe, North Africa, and the Middle East. There are today over 200 breeds of sheep in existence, each bred for a specific quality: hardiness, size, quantity and quality of fleece, milk production … and tastiness.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_SHIPWRECK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Ships sink … a fact known well to sailors. And to treasure hunters, salvage divers and underwater archaeologists, all seeking to make a name for themselves by bringing up artifacts (especially gold ones) from the shipwreck. A shipwreck is a treasure trove: underwater archaeologists seek to understand the past through it; salvage divers seek to recover cargo or parts from it; treasure hunters – despite any romantic notions – seek to get rich from it. The lure of lost treasure found on the seabed has been fostered by some fabulous discoveries, such as that of the wreck of the Nuestra Senora de Atocha (worth around $450 million) or the pirate ship Whydah Gally ($400 million). Still out there somewhere, among lesser shipwrecks, the Portuguese Flor de la Mar (estimated treasure of $2.6 billion).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_SILK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A natural protein fiber, silk is produced by insect larvae to create cocoons. The best quality of silk comes from the cocoons of the mulberry silkworm, as the Chinese discovered around 3630 BC (archeologists uncovered the body of a child of that period in silk wrappings). Legend presents the Empress Leizu as developing silk weaving, which spread throughout the Far East during her reign. Soon enough it was carried along the Silk Road, becoming China’s notable export to the West.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_SILVER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Malleable and shiny, silver has lured prospectors and thieves alike for at least 6000 years, since it was first mined in Asia Minor and several Aegean islands. Roman currency was based on silver, and Roman mining (mostly done by slaves) produced silver on an as-yet unprecedented scale. Chinese dynasties too used silver as their medium of exchange, minting it into coins to pay off their debts to the colonial powers. In the New World, the Spanish Cerro de Potosi was history’s largest silver mine, and the Comstock Lode brought thousands west to Nevada. All of which made Judas Iscariot’s 30 pieces of silver seem a pittance.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_SPICES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Spices enhance (or mask) the flavor of prepared food, and might be made from seed, bark, root, leaf, blossom, or just about any other part of a plant. The “spice trade” developed across Southern Asia and the Middle East around 2000 BC when people discovered properly prepared cinnamon and pepper helped make spoiled food palatable. Within a few centuries, spice merchants ranged across the known world and linked East and West. Spices really were the “spice of life,” and demand for them has been insatiable ever since.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_STONE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to geologists, stone is “a naturally occurring solid aggregate of one or more minerals or mineraloids.” Granite, for instance, is a mix of feldspar, biotite and quartz. The entire outer layer of the Earth’s crust is composed of rock. So, it isn’t surprising that “civilized” man has been using stone for constructions, tools, weapons, decorations, and paperweights since the – well – Stone Age.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_SUGAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Sugar is an incredibly sweet short-chain carbohydrate derived from sugar cane (or beets). It is believed that sugar was first used by Polynesians to spice their foods and drinks, and the practice spread to India and China, and from there across Asia and into Europe. Eventually sugar cane was transplanted to the Caribbean and to North and South America, where it was found to grow incredibly well … so long as someone was available to tend it.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_TEA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Dried leaves steeped in hot or boiling water, tea is the second most human-consumed beverage (after water) in the world. Tea plants are native to Eastern and Southern Asia, and tea drinking began during the Shang dynasty in China, likely as a medicinal cure that evolved into an acquired taste. Many teas – such as Darjeeling or the green teas – have a bitter, astringent taste, but have a mildly stimulating effect. Over the centuries many flavors of teas have been developed, ranging from sweet to floral, and from nutty to grassy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_TOBACCO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Tobacco is the cured leaves of the tobacco plant, a member of the Solanaceae (nightshade) family. Serving as a stimulant, smoking or chewing tobacco also releases dopamine in the human body, which gives a sense of pleasure and reward; dopamine is normally released by eating, drinking, and other pleasurable activities. Used since 1400 BC by the natives of the Americas, both for social and religious purposes, like so many vices tobacco was introduced to the world by Spanish explorers around 1559 AD, who brought seeds and leaves back to Europe on the orders of King Philip II.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_TOYS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As any parent knows, children will play with anything at hand – rocks, sticks, cardboard boxes, paper bags, dead insects, etc. But civilized children play with civilized toys – dolls, blocks, small soldiers, wooden weapons, carved animals, etc – all, according to psychologists, to prepare them for adult life. Setting aside the notion of adult toys, playthings have been found in tombs dating back to the Indus Valley civilization (c. 3010 BC) and Mesopotamian city-states. With the Enlightenment, and the notion that children should “enjoy” childhood, “play” became a major industry … and more than one innovator has made a fortune catering to children’s whims.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_TRUFFLES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A rare and expensive delicacy, truffles are the fruit of a family of fungi that grow underground. With a pungent aroma and powerful taste, truffles are used primarily for seasoning dishes in a variety of cuisines. But finding truffles is a laborious process. “Truffle pigs” were domesticated specifically for the purpose of finding truffles; with their uncanny sense of smell, these pigs are said to have been in use since the Roman Empire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_URANIUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>With 92 protons and electrons, six of the latter valence electrons, uranium is a silver-white metal that is slightly radioactive. The use of uranium dates back to at least 79 AD, when it was used to add a yellowish color to ceramic glazes. But Enrico Fermi found a more malevolent use for the metal; his research in 1934 led to the discovery of “nuclear fission.” And in December 1942, another team led by Fermi as part of the Manhattan Project initiated the world’s first self-sustained nuclear reaction. A few years later, thanks to uranium, the skies above Hiroshima lit up.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_WHALES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Whales have been hunted nearly to extinction for their meat, blubber, ambergris, oil, and bones (best not to be too useful to the dominant species). Whales have been hunted commercially since the 17th Century, but commercial whaling is now banned by several international commissions … although Norway, Iceland, Japan, and others have continued to license whaling vessels. The beasts also loom large in the folklore of several civilizations, and who can forget the 1851 novel 'Moby Dick.'</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_WHEAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>First cultivated in the Fertile Crescent of the Middle East about 8000 BC, wheat is a remarkably versatile grain; it can be ground into flour, fed to livestock, and made into beer. By 5000 BC, wheat farming had spread far; archeologists have found evidence of cultivation in China, India and even England. Relatively easy to grow and with relatively large yields, it was perfect for a growing, gluttonous civilization. Though wheat has found itself at the center of dietary controversy again and again, it remains a staple food across the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_WINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>'In vino, veritas.' In wine, truth. Wine is an alcoholic beverage made from fruit, honey, rice, and just about anything else that can be fermented. Archaeological evidence shows that wine was being produced from grapes as long ago as the Neolithic Age in the Zagros Mountains. Wine was so highly thought of that it became the staple in many religious ceremonies, national celebrations, and the dinner parties of effete snobs throughout history.</Text>
		</Row>
	</BaseGameText>
</GameData>
