<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlSpy.com) by Anton Strenger (Firaxis Games) -->
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<BaseGameText>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_INTRO_CHAPTER_INTRO_TITLE">
			<Text>Introduction</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_INTRO_CHAPTER_INTRO_PARA_1">
			<Text>Welcome to the Civilopedia for Sid Meier's Civilization VI! Here you will find detailed descriptions of all aspects of the game. Clicking on the tabs on the top edge of the screen will take you to the various major sections of the Civilopedia. The Navigation Bar on the left side of the screen will display the various entries within a section. Click on an entry to go directly there.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_CITIES_NAME">
			<Text>Cities</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Introduction</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Cities are vital to your civilization's success. They allow you to build units, buildings, and wonders. They allow you to research new technologies and gather wealth. You cannot win without powerful, well-situated cities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>How to Build Cities</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Cities are constructed by Settler units. If the Settler is in a location where a city can be constructed, the "Found City" action button will appear. Click on the button and the Settler will disappear, to be replaced by the new city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Where to Construct Cities</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Cities should be constructed in locations with plenty of [ICON_Food] Food and [ICON_Production] Production and with access to Strategic, Luxury, and Bonus resources. It is often a good idea to build a city on a River or coastal hex, as sources of water are very important to a growing [ICON_Citizen] Population. Cities constructed on Hills gain a defensive bonus, making it harder for enemies to capture them.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>With a Settler selected, ideal city locations will be shown on the map with an icon. Additionally, every Settler after your first will show the Settler Lens, giving you an idea of where on the map will provide the best source of water for your city, and indicating unavailable tiles.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_12_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Growth</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_12_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Your city will grow, or add more [ICON_Citizen] Citizens, with surplus [ICON_Food] Food. Any amount of [ICON_Food] Food over the total consumption of a city's [ICON_Citizen] Citizens, 2 per, is considered surplus, and is added as progress towards a new [ICON_Citizen] Citizen.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_12_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>A city will add all surplus [ICON_Food] Food towards growth if its current [ICON_Citizen] Population is 2 or more below the city's [ICON_Housing] Housing limit. If the city is 1 [ICON_Citizen] Population below its [ICON_Housing] Housing limit, its growth will slow to 50%. When the [ICON_Citizen] Population is at the [ICON_Housing] Housing limit, it will grow only at 75% the normal rate. A city can grow to 5 [ICON_Citizen] Citizens over its [ICON_Housing] Housing limit at this rate, and then it will stop growing entirely.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_12_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>A city will stagnate and not grow if it does not have surplus [ICON_Food] Food. If it makes less [ICON_Food] Food than its [ICON_Citizen] Citizens consume, the city will starve and slowly lose [ICON_Citizen] Population until it is able to support itself again.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_13_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Food</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_13_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>A city requires 2 [ICON_Food] Food per [ICON_Citizen] Citizen (another term for "[ICON_Citizen] Population") per turn to avoid starvation. A city acquires [ICON_Food] Food (as well as other yields) by assigning its [ICON_Citizen] Citizens to "work" the land around the city. The city can work any tile within 3 spaces of the city that is also within the civilization's borders, provided as well that it is not being worked by another city. Cities cannot work tiles occupied by wonders.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_13_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Left to its own devices, the city will assign as many [ICON_Citizen] Citizens as needed to acquire its [ICON_Food] Food.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_14_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Housing</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_14_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>[ICON_Housing] Housing is a representation of the maximum amount of [ICON_Citizen] Citizens or [ICON_Citizen] Population you can have in each city. The base source of [ICON_Housing] Housing is a water source.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_14_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Many buildings grant [ICON_Housing] Housing. After researching Pottery, every city is able to build a Granary, which adds 2 [ICON_Housing] Housing, and later they can build Sewers, which also adds 2 [ICON_Housing] Housing. Buildings in other districts sometimes add [ICON_Housing] Housing, such as the Barracks in the Encampment district, the University in the Campus, and the Lighthouse in the Harbor. The Palace building in your capital city also adds 1 [ICON_Housing] Housing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_14_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Each Farm, Pasture, Plantation, or Camp supports a small amount of [ICON_Citizen] Population — 1 [ICON_Housing] Housing for every 2 such improvements. Supporting rural [ICON_Citizen] Population in this fashion will allow for slightly larger [ICON_Citizen] Populations prior to the Industrial Era, when the Neighborhood district becomes available.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_15_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Water</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_15_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Placing your city near a water source should be one of your first decisions in any game. The presence of a good water source will immediately set the initial [ICON_Housing] Housing level of a city. A city not adjacent to any water will have a max [ICON_Citizen] Population of 2 at the start. A city on the coast will have a max [ICON_Citizen] Population of 3. And a city adjacent to a River, Lake, or Oasis will have a max [ICON_Citizen] Population of 5.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_15_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>The fresh water status of a city may be upgraded by adding an Aqueduct tile next to the City Center. Aqueducts may only be placed in tiles that are adjacent to a River, Lake, or Mountain that is also adjacent to the City Center.  Completion of the Aqueduct district raises the city’s [ICON_Housing] Housing from water by 2 or up to 6, whichever is larger—so 7 if adjacent to River, Lake or Oasis, or 6 otherwise.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_10_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Districts</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_10_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Civilization VI, buildings are no longer trapped in your City Center, but may sprawl across your territory as part of districts. The map is more important than ever as you are faced with important strategic placement decisions. The Campus and Holy Site each receive special boosts from placement near Mountain tiles, but the Campus also benefits from a nearby Rainforest tile.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_10_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>A city must expand its [ICON_Citizen] Population before it can construct multiple districts:[NEWLINE]• 1 [ICON_Citizen] Population for 1 District[NEWLINE]• 4 [ICON_Citizen] Population for 2 Districts[NEWLINE]• 7 [ICON_Citizen] Population for 3 Districts[NEWLINE]• Each additional District requires +3 [ICON_Citizen] Population[NEWLINE]The Aqueduct, Neighborhoods, and any district unique to your civilization ignore this [ICON_Citizen] Population requirement.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_10_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>When a city is ready to construct something, the Choose Production button will appear. If a district can be constructed, it will appear on this menu. Click on the district to order the city to begin construction, opening the district placement lens. Here, you will be given an overview of the different yield outcomes available on the tiles surrounding your City Center, and you can better make a decision about where to place your district. This lens will also show you which tiles are unavailable, as some districts have very specific placement requirements (for example, the Encampment cannot be built adjacent to a City Center). Furthermore, all districts must be built within 3 tiles of a City Center.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_10_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Districts may be placed on top of features such as Woods or Rainforest if you have the technology to remove those features, but for a longer construction time. No District can be built on a floodplain.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Neighborhoods and Appeal</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Neighborhoods are a special district that allows a city to house more [ICON_Citizen] Population and is affected by Appeal. The term “Appeal” is used to describe a special form of adjacency bonus that just applies to Neighborhoods, and also will affect Culture Victory’s [ICON_Tourism] Tourism system through National Parks and Seaside Resorts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Breathtaking Neighborhoods provide 6 [ICON_Housing] Housing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Charming Neighborhoods provide 5 [ICON_Housing] Housing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Average Neighborhoods provide 4 [ICON_Housing] Housing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>Uninviting Neighborhoods provide 3 [ICON_Housing] Housing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_6">
			<Text>Disgusting Neighborhoods provide 2 [ICON_Housing] Housing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_7">
			<Text>Finally, Appeal also affects the ability to place National Parks and Seaside Resorts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_8">
			<Text>A tile's Appeal can be viewed in its tooltip and is affected by the following:</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_9">
			<Text>+2: Each adjacent Natural Wonder</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_10">
			<Text>+1: Each adjacent Holy Site, Theater Square, Entertainment Complex, or wonder</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_11">
			<Text>+1: Each adjacent Mountain, Coast, Woods or Oasis</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_12">
			<Text>+1: If the tile is on a River or Lake</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_13">
			<Text>-1: Each adjacent Industrial Zone, Encampment, Airport or Spaceport</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_14">
			<Text>-1: Each adjacent Rainforest, Marsh or Floodplain</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_15">
			<Text>-1: Each adjacent pillaged tile</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>After your district has been built, you may now begin populating it with buildings. Buildings can be built through the Production Menu similarly to how you build your district. Some buildings have prerequisites, such as other buildings or technology requirements; these buildings will not be visible in your Production Menu. You may notice that you have some buildings available to build before you place any districts, such as the Monument. These buildings reside in the City Center.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Wonders</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Wonders are a special type of building that fills an entire hex and has a significant impact on gameplay. When you select one to build from the Production Menu, you will enter the placement lens, just like you would for building a district. Most wonders have specific placement requirements, and the lens will highlight which tiles are available. All wonders must be built within 3 tiles of a City Center.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Each wonder is unique. Though multiple civilizations may attempt to build the same wonder, only the civilization that first completes the wonder can reap its benefits. Civilizations failing to complete a wonder in time are refunded a portion of [ICON_Production] Production and some [ICON_Gold] Gold.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>For more information on each wonder, see the Wonders and Projects section of the Civilopedia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>The Palace</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Palace is a special building. Part building, part wonder, the Palace automatically appears in the first city you build, which makes that city the [ICON_Capital] Capital of your empire. The Palace provides a small amount of [ICON_Production] Production, [ICON_Science] Science, [ICON_Gold] Gold, and [ICON_Culture] Culture to your civilization. If your [ICON_Capital] Capital is captured by another civilization and you still have other cities under your control, the Palace will automatically transfer to another city, which will become your new [ICON_Capital] Capital.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Citizens</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Cities thrive based upon the land around them. Their [ICON_Citizen] Citizens "work" the land, harvesting [ICON_Food] Food, [ICON_Gold] Gold, [ICON_Production] Production, [ICON_Science] Science, and many other yields from the tiles. [ICON_Citizen] Citizens can work tiles that are within three tiles' distance from the city and that are within your civilization's borders. As your city grows, it automatically assigns its [ICON_Citizen] Citizens to work the lands around it. It seeks to provide a balanced amount of [ICON_Food] Food, [ICON_Production] Production, and [ICON_Gold] Gold. You may order a city's [ICON_Citizen] Citizens to work other tiles – for example, if you want a certain city to concentrate on generating [ICON_Gold] Gold, or [ICON_Production] Production, select the Manage Citizens icon in the City Selection Panel to choose specific tiles for your [ICON_Citizen] Citizens to work.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_16_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Happiness</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_16_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Happiness measures the contentment of your people in a single city, and is measured by seeing if the [ICON_Citizen] Population of that city has as many [ICON_Amenities] Amenities as expected. 1 [ICON_Amenities] Amenity is required for each 2 [ICON_Citizen] Population, start at a [ICON_Citizen] Population of 3. A content city will not have any modifier applied to it, but a happy city will have a 10% growth increase and a 5% yield increase. Furthermore, an Ecstatic city will have a 20% growth increase and 10% yield increase. Likewise, having too few [ICON_Amenities] Amenities will create displeasure among your [ICON_Citizen] Citizens, and the growth and yields will receive negative modifiers. At the level of unrest, your growth will stop and you may find rebel partisans in your city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_17_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Amenity Sources</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_17_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>[ICON_Amenities] Amenities can come from a wide variety of sources. Each Luxury resource can contribute up to 4 [ICON_Amenities] Amenities to your empire (1 per city) to the 4 cities that need them most. Distribution happens automatically, as long as the Luxury resource is improved (a Plantation improvement built on Spices, for example). The Arena, built in the Entertainment Complex, provides [ICON_Amenities] Amenities to its local city. The Zoo and Stadium also provide [ICON_Amenities] Amenities, but regionally. Some wonders also provide [ICON_Amenities] Amenities. Furthermore, there are a few Religious Beliefs and policies that provide [ICON_Amenities] Amenities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_17_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>War weariness and bankruptcy will lower the [ICON_Amenities] Amenities in a city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Specialists</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITIES_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Specialists are alternative assignments for [ICON_Citizen] Citizens, which involve working a district tile instead of a normal tile. As a general rule, specialists are a good way to get yields otherwise hard to find on normal tiles, but the city needs a solid support base of [ICON_Food] Food to support them in the long term. Specialists are also particularly useful when a city grows large later in the game, and has more [ICON_Citizen] Population than there are normal tiles to work. There are different types of specialists, each with different effects. All specialist types except the generic [ICON_Citizen] Citizen have a limit on how many assignments there can be in a city. This limit is determined by the number of buildings in the district associated with that specialist type.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_WORLD_NAME">
			<Text>The World</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Terrain and Features</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Civilization VI, the world is made up of hexagonally-shaped "tiles" (also occasionally known as hexes and spaces). These tiles come in a variety of "terrain-types" -  Desert, Plains, Grassland, Hills, and so forth  - and many also include "features" like Woods and Rainforest. These elements help to determine the tile's usefulness to a nearby city as well as how easy or difficult it is to move through the tile. A tile's terrain and features may have important effects upon any combat occurring there.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Every tile in the game belongs to a continent. Continents are geographical boundaries, and are not necessarily tied to a landmass—the Pangaea map, for example, is made up of several continents. You can determine a tile's continent by that tile's tooltip or by viewing the continent lens.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Resources</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Resources are sources of a variety of different yields ([ICON_Food] Food, [ICON_Production] Production, etc.), and some provide other special bonuses to a civilization. They appear in certain hexes. Some are visible at the start of the game, while others require the acquisition of specific technologies before you can see them. To utilize a resource, it must be within your civilization's borders and you must construct the appropriate "improvement" in that hex. There are three types of resources: Bonus, Luxury, and Strategic. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Bonus resources can increase the [ICON_Food] Food, [ICON_Gold] Gold, or [ICON_Production] Production output of a hex. Bonus resources cannot be traded to other civilizations. These resources can be "harvested" by Builders to remove the resource and provide an immediate, one-time sum of [ICON_Food] Food or [ICON_Production] Production to the city that owns the hex.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Luxury resources increase your civilization's happiness by providing [ICON_Amenities] Amenities and provide a small bonus to the hex's yield output. Only one source of a specific Luxury resource provides [ICON_Amenities] Amenities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Strategic resources are not always visible at the start of the game—they may require knowledge of a particular technology before they appear on a map. Strategic resources allow you to build certain units. When you construct an improvement on a Strategic resource hex, it allows you to build units that require that resource (i.e. Musketmen require Niter) in any of your cities that has an appropriate district—Encampment for land units, Harbor for naval units, or Aerodrome for air units. If you build an improvement on 2 copies of that resource, you can build or purchase those units in any city, whether it has the appropriate district or not.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Natural Wonders</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Natural wonders are the great and glorious creations of nature that awe and inspire us all. These include Crater Lake and the Great Barrier Reef – all places that truly display the grand beauty of the natural world. All natural wonders provide unique benefits to your civilization, and some even have additional special effects (for instance, healing adjacent to the Dead Sea will make a unit’s health refill completely.)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Rivers</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Traditionally, cities have been built along Rivers, and for good reason. Rivers provide fresh water for people to drink and irrigation, improving the farmland around the city. They also protect a city, as it is quite difficult to mount an assault against a city across a River.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Tribal Villages</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Tribal Villages are less civilized than other civilizations, but are friendly nonetheless. Visiting tribal villages provide a random benefit to the civilization of the unit that first enters their tile. The village disappears after its gifts have been claimed. Gifts include survivors, such as Builders or Traders, technology or technology boosts, military units, [ICON_Faith] Faith, [ICON_Gold] Gold, [ICON_GreatWork_Relic] Relics, or civic boosts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Barbarians</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Barbarians come from "outposts", which may appear randomly in any tile that cannot be seen by a unit. Each Barbarian unit belongs to its own home outpost. There are three types of Barbarian outposts: Naval, Cavalry, and Melee. A civilization will earn a [ICON_Gold] Gold reward for dispersing a Barbarian outpost − in addition to the benefit of stopping it from spawning more Barbarian units.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Naval Barbarian outposts on the coastline can create naval units (equal to those that can be created by the civilization with the most advanced tech). These units will menace your coastline, destroy naval improvements and attack hapless land units which stray too near the coastline. It's important to maintain a navy to keep them off your back, but the best way to stop these attacks is to destroy the coastal outposts nearby.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Cavalry outposts, appearing inland and near a Horse resource, will spawn mounted units.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Every outpost will first generate a Scout, searching for targets. If you’re spotted by a Barbarian Scout, it will return to its outpost and begin building units for an invasion or raid. Watch out, because you’re going to be the next target. If you don’t move fast, you’ll soon see a party of Barbarians at your borders, ready to destroy your improvements or conquer your city. This is why it's important to periodically sweep the countryside around your civilization, destroying outposts before they become a threat.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Lenses</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Lenses are a tool you can use to change your view of the world. Each lens will overlay important information that will help you make strategic decisions in the game. Some lenses are activated automatically, like when you choose to place a district from a city's Production Menu. Others can be activated manually from the Lenses button on the mini-map. These are the lenses you can use in game and what they do:</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WORLD_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Appeal. Shows the appeal level of each tile.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Continent. Shows the geographic extent of each continent.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]District Placement. Shows valid placement locations for wonders and districts, as well as any adjacency bonuses available for districts. This will only appear when attempting to build a district or wonder.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Government. Shows the distribution of governments across the map.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Political. Shows the owner of each tile.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Religion. Shows the majority religion and religious follower distribution across the map. This appears whenever a Religious unit is selected.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Settler. Shows recommended city sites and water availability at each tile.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_COMBAT_NAME">
			<Text>Combat</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Introduction</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Combat occurs between two political entities that are at war with each other. A civilization may be at war with another civilization or with a city-state. Barbarians are always at war with all civilizations and city-states.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Declaring War</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>There are two ways to declare war. The first requires you move a military unit you control into another civilization's unit. This will prompt a pop-up message to appear asking if you want to start a war. Alternately, war can be declared in the Diplomacy Window. Within that window, you will always have the option to make a surprise declaration of war, except against your declared allies. Your civilization will suffer a costly warmongering penalty if you make a surprise declaration of war. To avoid some of this penalty (but not all), denounce the offending civilization and soon the option to formally declare war will appear in the Diplomacy Window.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>War Weariness</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Having a nation that is constantly at war will diminish the productivity and happiness of your people. War weariness grows for every battle you fight. This accumulation is worse when those battles occur in foreign territory or when your units are killed. It is worse still if those units are killed by a nuclear weapon, but launching a nuclear weapon yourself is the greatest source of war weariness. All war weariness you accumulate is increased if you declared war without using a Casus Belli.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>War weariness is applied to every city you own as a negative [ICON_Amenities] Amenity, lowering your city growth and productivity. Having low [ICON_Amenities] Amenities for too long can cause rebel partisans to spawn in your cities. These hostile units will attack your units and pillage your tiles and districts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>While war weariness will slowly reduce while you are still at war, it reduces at a greatly increased rate when you are not at war with any player.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Warmongering</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Warmongering is more than just a diplomatic consequence; it can be a state of mind, considered a most honorable thing from a certain point of view. It is believed that a soldier in Napoleon's early days of conquest saw his General and Emperor’s constant warmongering to be of righteous cause! There are, however, some stiff penalties for launching a non-justified, or lack of Casus Belli, war.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>A player who launches into a non-Casus Belli war (see the section on Casus Belli under Diplomacy) will start to accumulate diplomatic warmongering penalties from other civilizations that player has come in contact with, on top of any war weariness already suffered. Launching a surprise war, capturing opposing civilizations cities, razing captured cities, and using nuclear devices increases the diplomatic penalty based on what era the player is in. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>The other approach is to denounce the opposing civilization first and then declare war formally. With this avenue to war, the warmonger penalties are NOT increased and there is the opportunity to use a Casus Belli to reduce those penalties.  However, because you must first denounce your opponent, such a plan is "telegraphed" for the target and you will not have the advantage of surprise.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Ending a War</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Wars can end violently or peacefully. A war ends violently when one side is destroyed. This occurs when that side has lost its last city. The peaceful resolution of a war involves diplomatic negotiations. You or your opponent may initiate a Peace Deal. See the section on Diplomacy for further details.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Barbarians will never negotiate. War with Barbarians will continue until the Barbarians are destroyed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Unit Combat Statistics</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Civilization VI, military units have five combat oriented stats: Hit Points, [ICON_Strength] Combat Strength, [ICON_Ranged] Ranged Strength, [ICON_Bombard] Bombard Strength, and [ICON_Range] Range.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>All units have 100 Hit Points. As a unit takes damage, it loses Hit Points. A unit is destroyed once it loses all of its Hit Points.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>All military units have [ICON_Strength] Combat Strength. Melee units use their [ICON_Strength] Combat Strength when attacking or defending. Ranged units use their [ICON_Strength] Combat Strength when defending.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Any unit that can engage in ranged combat has a [ICON_Ranged] Ranged Strength statistic. This number is compared with the target's [ICON_Strength] Combat Strength to determine the results of the attack. Units with a [ICON_Ranged] Ranged Strength can also attack district defenses but at a reduced effectiveness.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>[ICON_Bombard] Bombard Strength is the anti-district strength of a unit. Units with [ICON_Bombard] Bombard Strength can also attack units, but at a reduced effectiveness. Units cannot have both a [ICON_Bombard] Bombard and [ICON_Ranged] Ranged Strength.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_6">
			<Text>The unit's [ICON_Range] Range stat determines the distance at which a unit can launch a ranged attack. A [ICON_Range] Range of "2" means that the target can be in an adjacent tile or one tile distant. A [ICON_Range] Range of "1" would mean that the target had to be adjacent to the attacker.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Line of Sight</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Generally, there must be no obstructions, such as a Mountain, between a ranged unit and its target. Units on Hills or flying can often see over obstructing terrain.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Combat Bonuses</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Warfare is not practiced by just the experienced and well equipped. Military history has shown time and time again that the combatant, using superior tactics, leadership, and the terrain to their advantage can defeat a numerically superior and better equipped force. In Civilization VI, it is no different.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>In combining your military might with the right force organization of combined arms, leadership, and intuitive use of terrain you can have the power to destroy your enemies armies, no matter how big or small, advanced or not. Using terrain to your advantage, you can position your forces on Hills, in Rainforests or Woods, and across Rivers from your enemy to ensure a distinct defensive advantage. Looking at the enemies movements across terrain as they approach you can also help you better understand what their battle plan is or where they look to strike.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Terrain can also be detrimental to your fight; be sure to avoid fighting on Flood Plains and Marshes as these have a negative effect on your defensibility. If you find yourself on indefensible terrain, and do not feel you can defeat your enemy on the attack, perhaps building a few Forts will help you push back the enemy. Remember to attack the enemies flanks, it is their weakest point and will also grant you advantage! Using a well-rounded military force with the proper terrain dispositions while having the use of a Great General will ensure victory!</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Experience and Promotions</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>A unit that survives combat will gain "Experience Points" (XP). Once a unit reaches a certain amount of XP it will 'level up', at which point it can receive a promotion. Promotions enhance the unit in some way. When selecting a promotion, the unit is healed an amount of Hit Points. The unit will not continue to gain any further XP until the promotion is selected.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>City Combat</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Cities may be attacked and captured by military units. Each city has a "City Combat Strength" stat that determines its strength when attacked by other units. The higher the city's City Combat Strength, the more difficult it is to capture the city. Unless the city is extremely weak or the attacking unit is extremely strong, it will take multiple turns to capture a city. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Walls add extra protection to a city or Encampment, making it even more difficult to conquer. This protection is like armor, shielding the city from attacks. Melee units deal only 15% of their normal damage to walls, and ranged units deal only 50% of their normal damage. Only Bombard units deal 100% of their normal damage to walls, making them necessary to capture a fortified city. If the walls are damaged, they stop being as effective and the district's health will start taking a little bit of damage with every attack. Walls can only recover health with a Project found in the city's Production Queue, like repairing district buildings, that becomes available if the district has not taken any damage for 3 consecutive turns. Once a city has walls, it can make ranged attacks against enemy units using a "City Ranged Strength" stat.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The City Combat Strength is based on the [ICON_Strength] Combat Strength of the strongest melee unit built by your civilization, minus 10, or by the Combat Strength of a garrisoned military unit.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The City Ranged Strength is based on the [ICON_Ranged] Ranged Strength of the strongest ranged unit built by your civilization.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The city gets additional bonuses to its City Combat Strength for each non-pillaged district it has, making big cities harder to capture, and from terrain and a few other modifiers sources.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Cities can also be under siege from attacking units. The City Center and other defensible districts like the Encampment are considered under siege if all 6 tiles around them are occupied by enemy units, under enemy Zone of Control, or are impassable due to mountains or Natural Wonders. In these circumstances, the district will not recover lost health, instead of healing automatically every turn as normal.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_10_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Conquering a City</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_10_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>When your unit enters an enemy city, you have two choices: you can destroy the city (if it was not a [ICON_Capital] Capital) or you can annex it and make it part of your empire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_12_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Formations</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_12_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Formations allow you to easily move units together. This can be useful for escorting civilian units in hostile lands, or even creating stronger units in Corps and Armies. A military unit can create a formation with a support or civilian unit at any time. Naval military units may also create a formation with embarked land units. Support units, such as siege units, are most effective in battle when linked with another military unit.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_12_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Starting in the Industrial era after completing the Nationalism civic, players will be able to unlock the ability to combine multiple military units of the same type into a single stronger unit. Two military units of the same type will be able to combine to create a Corps, giving them +10 to their base [ICON_Strength] Combat Strength. After researching Mobilization, three units of the same type may be combined into an Army, giving +7 to their base [ICON_Strength] Combat Strength. Keep in mind that their HP is NOT increased when units are combined in this way.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_12_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Once a Corps or Army has been formed, the units may not be broken apart into individual units again. The experience and promotions of the highest experience unit is preserved when creating this type of formation, so it is beneficial to combine rookies with more experienced units. Naval units may also be combined into Fleets and Armadas.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_13_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Pillaging</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_13_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Both improvements and buildings in districts without garrisons can be pillaged. This action renders them inoperable and awards the pillaging unit with some form of "plunder."  </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_13_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Pillaging a district takes 3 Movement Points, or all of your movement. Each building in a district must be pillaged separately, and awards some sort of plunder based on the district (see below). Once pillaged, a building cannot be pillaged again until it is brought back online by its owner (done through the Production Menu and takes 25% of the [ICON_Production] Production cost of initial construction of that building.)[NEWLINE]Pillaging a Campus awards [ICON_Science] Science.[NEWLINE]Pillaging a Holy Site awards [ICON_Faith] Faith.[NEWLINE]Pillaging a Commercial Hub awards [ICON_Gold] Gold.[NEWLINE]Pillaging a Theater Square awards [ICON_Culture] Culture.[NEWLINE]Pillaging a Harbor district awards [ICON_Gold] Gold.[NEWLINE]Pillaging an Industrial Zone awards [ICON_Science] Science.[NEWLINE]Pillaging an Aerodrome awards [ICON_Gold] Gold.[NEWLINE]Pillaging an Aqueduct awards [ICON_Gold] Gold.[NEWLINE]Pillaging a Spaceport awards [ICON_Science] Science.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_13_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Pillaging an improvement will take 3 Movement Points, or all your movement (if you have [ICON_Movement] Movement Points of less than 3).  It will mark the improvement in the tile as "pillaged".  Once pillaged, an improvement cannot be pillaged again until it is brought back online by its owner (a Builder operation that always takes one turn but does not require a Builder charge).[NEWLINE]Pillaging a Farm awards healing.[NEWLINE]Pillaging a Mine awards [ICON_Science] Science.[NEWLINE]Pillaging a Quarry awards [ICON_Culture] Culture.[NEWLINE]Pillaging Fishing Boats awards healing.[NEWLINE]Pillaging a Pasture awards [ICON_Gold] Gold.[NEWLINE]Pillaging a Plantation awards [ICON_Faith] Faith.[NEWLINE]Pillaging a Camp awards [ICON_Gold] Gold.[NEWLINE]Pillaging a Lumber Mill awards [ICON_Science] Science.[NEWLINE]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_MOVEMENT_NAME">
			<Text>Unit Movement</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MOVEMENT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Movement Points</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MOVEMENT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>All mobile units have a certain number of [ICON_Movement] Movement points that they can expend on [ICON_Movement] Movement every turn. Once they've expended those [ICON_Movement] Movement points, they can't move any more until the next turn. Units expend [ICON_Movement] Movement points to enter tiles, to attack other units, or to pillage improvements or districts. The terrain of the tile a unit is entering determines the [ICON_Movement] Movement point cost of the move.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MOVEMENT_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Roads</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MOVEMENT_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Roads are an important part of moving around the world. Placed by Trader units beginning in the Ancient Era, roads begin by reducing the [ICON_Movement] Movement cost of a tile to 1 when moving from one road tile to another. As technology progresses, you will unlock the ability to build better and better roads, and even bridges. Modern roads, for example, reduce [ICON_Movement] Movement to a half [ICON_Movement] Movement point per tile, when moving from one road tile to another. All roads allow units to ignore terrain-based movement penalties.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MOVEMENT_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Roads are placed by Traders, but may also be placed manually by Military Engineers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MOVEMENT_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Zone of Control</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MOVEMENT_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Many combat units exert a "Zone of Control" (ZOC) over the tiles around them. When a unit moves into an enemy's ZOC with [ICON_Movement] Movement leftover, its [ICON_Movement] Movement is stopped or it may attack.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MOVEMENT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Naval Movement</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MOVEMENT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Generally, naval units follow the same rules as land units, except that they move in the water rather than on land. Early naval units are often limited to coastal waters (those adjacent to land tiles) and coastal cities. Eventually, you'll produce naval units that can enter deep ocean tiles, and thus explore the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MOVEMENT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Embarking Units</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MOVEMENT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>At the start of the game, your land units cannot enter any water tiles. However, once you've learned the Sailing technology, Builders will be able to move into coastal water tiles. After Celestial Navigation, Traders will be able to embark. And after Shipbuilding, all units will be able to embark. To embark a unit, move the unit to a coastal tile and then click on the "Embark" Action. Once embarked, the unit must move into water.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_SCIENCE_NAME">
			<Text>Science and Technology</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_SCIENCE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Introduction</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_SCIENCE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Each technology you acquire gives your civilization access to some advanced unit, building, resource, or wonder, or gives you some other tangible benefit such as the ability to chop Woods and harvest Cattle. Each new technology makes your civilization that much more powerful. Every turn, your civilization receives [ICON_Science] Science added to its pool, and when you have accumulated enough [ICON_Science] Science, you acquire a new technology.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_SCIENCE_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Earning Science</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_SCIENCE_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>[ICON_Science] Science comes from a variety of sources, including your [ICON_Citizen] Citizens, your Palace, some Policies, some Religious Beliefs, some resources, wonders, trading, and of course the Campus district and its buildings. Look through the Civilopedia to find sources of [ICON_Science] Science.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_SCIENCE_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Eureka Moments</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_SCIENCE_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Eureka moments, also known as "technology boosts", provide an immediate and significant boost towards your research of a technology. These boosts will be earned as you play the game naturally, and your actions will determine what sort of Eureka moments you encounter. For example, settling a city on the coast will boost your progress towards Sailing and creating a Pasture will boost your progress towards Horseback Riding. To see all possible Eureka moments, take a look at the Technology Tree.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_SCIENCE_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>The Technology Tree</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_SCIENCE_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>To see how all of this works in the game, check out the amazing Technology Tree. It displays all of the technologies and shows how they are intertwined. You can click on a technology to order your civilization to research it – if your civilization doesn't know the prerequisite technologies it will research them as well. The technology tree will plot the quickest route to the requested tech, and you will research the necessary precursors in the order it displays. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_CULTURE_NAME">
			<Text>Culture and Civics</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CULTURE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Introduction</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CULTURE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>[ICON_Culture] Culture is the way that you advance through the Civics Tree, unlocking new policies and Governments. It’s also how you increase the size of your cities’ territories. Most importantly, [ICON_Culture] Culture can be another path to victory. Each civic you acquire gives your civilization access to policies or governments, as well as some buildings, districts, and diplomatic advancements. You acquire civics by accumulating [ICON_Culture] Culture. Every turn your civilization gets some amount of [ICON_Culture] Culture added to its pool. Each civic costs a certain amount of [ICON_Culture] Culture to learn; when you've accumulated enough [ICON_Culture] Culture, you acquire the civic. When you get the new civic, your pool is depleted and you start accumulating all over again, saving up for the next civic.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CULTURE_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Earning Culture</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CULTURE_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>[ICON_Culture] Culture can be earned from wonders, policies, leader abilities, natural wonders, city-states, Beliefs, [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Routes, and of course the Theater Square district. Look through the Civilopedia to find sources of [ICON_Culture] Culture.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CULTURE_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Inspiration Moments</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CULTURE_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Inspiration moments, also known as "civic boosts", provide an immediate and significant boost towards your study of a civic. These boosts will be earned as you play the game naturally, and your actions will determine what sort of Inspiration moments you encounter. For example, building a wonder boosts your progress towards Drama and Poetry, and building any district will boost your progress towards State Workforce. To see all possible Inspiration moments, take a look at the Civics Tree.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CULTURE_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>The Civics Tree</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CULTURE_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>To see how all of this works in the game, check out the amazing Civics Tree. It displays all of the civics and shows how they are intertwined. You can click on a civic to order your civilization to study it – if your civilization doesn't know the prerequisite civic it will research them as well. The Civics Tree will plot the quickest route to the requested civic, and you will study the necessary precursors in the order it displays. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_GOLD_NAME">
			<Text>Gold and the Economy</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOLD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Introduction</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOLD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>[ICON_Gold] Gold is the lifeblood of a civilization. It may be true that "money can't buy you love," but it can purchase a submarine armed with nuclear missiles, and that's not bad.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOLD_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Obtaining Gold</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOLD_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>[ICON_Gold] Gold comes from a variety of sources. You'll obtain [ICON_Gold] Gold by working the tiles around your cities, but other sources are available as well: terrains and improvements, trading posts, districts and buildings, [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Routes, Barbarian outposts, Tribal Villages, city-states, pillaging enemy improvements, capturing cities, and diplomacy with other civilizations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOLD_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Spending Gold</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOLD_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>There are many times that you can and will spend [ICON_Gold] Gold. Units and buildings both have "maintenance costs" that must be paid every turn. You can also extend your civilization's territory by purchasing individual tiles, or you can use the [ICON_Gold] Gold to purchase units and buildings. Upgrading obsolete units will also cost [ICON_Gold] Gold. [ICON_Gold] Gold may be exchanged with other civilizations during diplomacy, and if you ever lose a city, you will lose some [ICON_Gold] Gold as well.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOLD_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Bankruptcy</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOLD_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>If your treasury is at zero and you're running a negative budget, you will begin to receive a -1 penalty to your [ICON_Amenities] Amenities per every 10 [ICON_Gold] Gold you drop below 0. Additionally, at -10 [ICON_Gold] Gold you will automatically disband a unit, at -20 [ICON_Gold] Gold, two units will be disbanded, and so forth.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_FAITH_NAME">
			<Text>Faith and Religion</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Introduction</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Your Religion choices are incredibly important and can be game-changing. With the Religious Victory and Theological Combat, you have new and exciting tools at your disposal to spread your beliefs to other cities and civilizations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Earning Faith</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>[ICON_Faith] Faith is the currency of Religion and can be earned from wonders, policies, leader abilities, natural wonders, city-states, Beliefs, [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Routes, and of course the Holy Site district and its buildings. Look through the Civilopedia to find sources of [ICON_Faith] Faith.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Pantheons</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once you accumulate enough [ICON_Faith] Faith, you’ll be prompted to found a Pantheon, a precursor to the full-blown Religions to be founded later. Choosing which Pantheon to found depends on your short- and long-term goals for your civilization. After earning a Pantheon, you are well on your way to establishing your Religion. Unlike a full Religion, a Pantheon you choose will be unique to your civilization, and cannot spread outside your borders, or be displaced. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Great Prophets</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>You may found your Religion once you have earned (or purchased) a [ICON_GreatProphet] Great Prophet. Religious buildings will accumulate the [ICON_GreatProphet] Great Prophet points necessary to bring this special unit to your civilization. After the [ICON_GreatProphet] Great Prophet has been earned, send the unit to your Holy Site, and then found your Religion. [ICON_GreatProphet] Great Prophets may also be earned from Stonehenge.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Founding Your Religion</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>After founding your Religion, you will be prompted to choose a name and icon to represent your beliefs. You may choose a historical Religion, or create one of your own! A newly established Religion will consist of two beliefs: a Follower belief, and one of three additional types of beliefs that can be tailored to your play style. Once your Religion is founded, all of your cities with Holy Sites will automatically convert to the Religion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>You can then use the Evangelize Belief action on Apostles to add additional beliefs to your Religion. You can have a total of 4 beliefs in a Religion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Follower beliefs provide some kind of yield or other inherent bonus. This applies to all cities and civilizations that follow that Religion.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Founder beliefs provide a bonus that relies on the number of followers it has. Followers are citizens that follow that religion in all cities, regardless of whether or not that Religion is predominant in a city. This bonus is applied only to the civilization that founded that Religion.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Worship beliefs grant a unique type of building that can be built in Holy Sites, or purchased there with [ICON_Faith] Faith. Every Worship building has different benefits.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Enhancer beliefs help spread the religion by making its natural religious pressure stronger or by making Missionaries and Apostles cheaper.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Religious Units and Pressure</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>There are three types of Religious units: Missionaries, Apostles, and Inquisitors. Religious units may be purchased through your city with [ICON_Faith] Faith and will adopt the majority Religion of the city in which they are built. Religious units' primary purpose is to spread their Religion to other cities. To do so, move the unit adjacent to a City Center—or inside it, if the city is yours—and use the Spread Religion action. This will convert some of the citizens of that city to Followers of your Religion.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]If more than half the citizens in the city are Followers of a particular Religion and that Religion has the majority of Followers in that city, that Religion will become predominant in that city. Cities with a dominant Religion will apply religious pressure on other cities within 10 tiles, slowly converting the citizens of those cities to that Religion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Missionaries may be purchased with [ICON_Faith] Faith in any city with a Shrine and a dominant Religion, and have the ability to spread your Religion to any City Center in an adjacent hex.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Apostles may be purchased with [ICON_Faith] Faith in any city with a Temple and a dominant Religion, and are stronger than Missionaries. Apostles get to select a unique promotion when they are created which makes them more unique, such as having more charges or removing other religions from a city.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Apostles have several unique actions available in addition to spreading their Religion. They can Evangelize Belief, adding additional beliefs to your Religion, or Launch Inquisition, granting the ability to purchase Inquisitors. Furthermore, Apostles may initiate theological combat against other Religious units.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Inquisitors are special units that must be unlocked with the Launch Inquisition action on an Apostle. You only need to use this action once; once you have started an Inquisition, it never ends! You can then purchase Inquisitors in cities that follow the religion of the Apostle that launched the Inquisition with [ICON_Faith] Faith. Inquisitors are not good at spreading a Religion, but instead remove all other Religions from a city. They may also engage in theological combat against other Religious units.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Theological Combat</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Theological combat is the best way to defend against other Religions trying to spread across the map. Only Apostles and Inquisitors may initiate theological combat, and then only against other Religious units.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Theological combat works just like combat with military units, just attack one Religious unit with another. They will deal damage to each other based on their strength. Religious units can get bonuses to their theological combat strength from promotions, policies, the Theocracy government, if they are in or adjacent to a Holy Site following their Religion, if they are in the territory of a city following their Religion, or a huge bonus if they are in the territory of their Religion's Holy City.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>A damaged Religious unit suffers a penalty to the strength of its Spread Religion action, meaning it will convert fewer Followers. If a Religious unit is reduced to 0 Hit Points from theological combat, it will die. When a Religious unit is defeated this way, all cities within 10 tiles have a religious pressure drop of the defeated unit's Religion equal to the strength of an Apostle at full health and then a boost in the victorious unit's Religion of the same amount. If a Religious unit is killed by a hostile military unit, then the religious pressure drop occurs just like in theological combat.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FAITH_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Religious units can heal any damage they have by staying adjacent to or in a Holy Site that follows their Religion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_DIPLO_NAME">
			<Text>Diplomacy</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Introduction</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>You can accomplish a lot through diplomacy. You can gain allies and isolate your enemies. You can create defensive and offensive pacts. You can increase your technology through cooperative research ventures. You can end wars that are going badly for you. You can bluff the credulous and bully the timid. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Diplomacy with Civilizations</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>To initiate diplomacy, click on the leader you wish to contact in the upper right portion of the screen. The Diplomacy Panel will appear, displaying all known civilizations. Click on any leader to speak with them. Alternatively, you can click on a civilization's city banner to open communications with them. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>When you engage in diplomacy with civilizations, you will have a number of options available, depending on your current relationship. This screen will also provide important information about your relationship, as well as the latest gossip about what that leader has been doing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>You may choose to declare war, or denounce the leader. You may also negotiate a trade deal, or demand stuff from another civilization. You can also propose friendship, defensive pacts, and send delegations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_12_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Diplomatic Relationships</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_12_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Every other leader in the game has an opinion of you. Their opinion might be positive or it might be negative; it is in constant flux from events in the game. You can tell what your relationship with another leader is by the icon on their leader portrait, or by selecting Our Relationship with that leader on the Diplomacy Panel. The following relationship states exist in the game:</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_12_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Allies. When in an Alliance with a leader, you may not declare war on each other, you automatically share Open Borders, you may make Research Agreements and Defensive Pacts, and deals you make with each other are likely to be very favorable.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Declared Friend. When you choose to declare your friendship with a leader, you may not declare war on each other, you may make Research Agreements, and deals you make with each other will be more favorable. This relationship state is required to make an Alliance.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Friendly. This means the leader thinks positively of you and you have a better chance of getting favorable deals with them.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Neutral. You have done nothing to upset or impress the leader, and your interactions with them will be standard.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Unfriendly. For some reason, you have done something to upset this leader, and deals with them will likely be unfavorable for you, or you can choose to make demands of them. [NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Denounced. This leader has let the other leaders in the world know that you have done something to offend them. Your deals with them will be unfavorable if they will make them at all, but you can declare a Formal War against them and make demands.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]At War. Open hostilities have broken out between you, and you can attack or invade this leader but you will accrue warmongering and war weariness penalties.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Trade, Demand, and Discuss</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>You can make trade deals with other players by selecting Make Deal from the Diplomacy Panel with a leader selected. You will enter a negotiation table with that leader.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]On the left of the table are items you are able to trade, and on the right of the table are items the other player has available to trade. You can trade anything from [ICON_Gold] Gold to resources to cities! Select items from the other leader's side of the table to request they trade them to you, and select items from your side of the table to offer in exchange.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]When the other leader finds the deal acceptable, an "Accept Deal" button will appear, which will confirm the trade that is on the table. You will lose any items you proposed and gain any items from the other leader.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]If the leader does not like the deal, you can select the "Make this deal more equitable" button to cause the leader to propose a deal they believe is fair. You may then adjust their offer to suit your needs, and see if they accept. You can also ask the leader for something and select "What would it take?" to see what they want from you in trade.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]If you propose an item but do not ask anything in return, you can select "Give Gift" to give the item to the leader for free. Who doesn't like gifts? Or you can select "What would you give me?" to ask the leader what they would be willing to pay.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>If you are Unfriendly with a leader or either of you has Denounced each other, you will see the Make Demand option on the Diplomacy Panel with that leader selected. This option will take you to a negotiation table, but your side of the table will be blank. Instead, you select items from their side of the table to demand as tribute! Select "Demand Deal" to see if they will pay you what you ask. The leader may not take kindly to your demands.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Whether making a Deal or a Demand, some items are given permanently and some are only loaned to the leader. Sums of [ICON_Gold] Gold, Great Works, [ICON_GreatWork_Relic] Relics, [ICON_GreatWork_Artifact] Artifacts, and captured Spies are all permanent trades—once you give those items away, you have to trade again to get them back. Resources and gold per turn, however, are temporary, and once the deal has run its course you will get them back.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Depending on your interactions with a leader, you might also have the Discuss option on the Diplomacy Panel. Selecting it will show you a list of actions you can ask the leader to promise to stop doing towards you, but only if the leader has already done that action at least once. You can ask them to stop settling new cities near you, to stop spreading their religion to you, to stop spying on you, or to stop attacking a City State you are Suzerain of.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>All Deals, Demands, and Promises last for 30 turns, at which point they need to be renewed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Delegations and Embassies</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Delegations and Resident Embassies can be established between players to improve relations and gain Diplomatic Visibility. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>A Delegation, or Embassy, needs to be sent to every leader individually. Delegations cost 10 [ICON_Gold] Gold and Embassies cost 25 [ICON_Gold] Gold, which is paid to the other leader. This will give you a small positive bonus in your relationship with that leader. It also gives you 1 level of Diplomatic Visibility.  See the Diplomatic Visibility and Gossip section of the Civilopedia for more information on Diplomatic Visibility.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Resident Embassies are unlocked with the Diplomatic Service Civic, at which point they replace Delegations. The effects of Resident Embassies and Delegations do not stack.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Open Borders</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Open Borders is an agreement with another leader to allow them to move their units, military or civilian, through your territory. Without this agreement, entering another leader's territory is an act of war, except with Religious Units, who can ignore borders entirely. If you have Open Borders with a leader, their border will appear as a dotted line instead of a solid one. Open Borders is unlocked with the Early Empire Civic. Prior to that, your borders are open to everyone.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Open Borders can be offered as part of a Deal trade agreement, but it is offered individually by each leader—you can be granted Open Borders with a leader without granting them Open Borders in return. The deal lasts for 30 turns, and then it needs to be renewed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>If you are in an Alliance with another leader, you both grant each other Open Borders automatically.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_10_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Research Agreements</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_10_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>After researching Scientific Theory, two allied or declared friendly players can enter into a Research Agreement to get a tech boost for a chosen tech. As a part of forming this deal, a specific technology must be agreed upon. The number of turns it will take to complete the research will depend on the current research rates of both users. If either player earns the boost or tech by any other means, the agreement ends and the other player will get the boost immediately.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Defensive Pact</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>A Defensive Pact is an agreement between two leaders to come to each other's aid when targeted by a Declaration of War. If either member of the Defensive Pact is targeted, the other member will also declare war against the aggressor. Defensive Pacts are available through the Make Deal negotiation table. The two leaders must be in an Alliance to make the deal.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_14_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Joint War</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_14_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>After researching the civic Foreign Trade, a Joint War may be proposed between players. If you accept or propose a Joint War, you and another player will immediately be at war with the target player as set in the deal parameters.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Casus Belli</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Casus Belli represent reasons to go to war where the normal Warmonger penalty for a declaration of war or capturing cities are reduced or eliminated.  Once you reach the Renaissance era civic Diplomatic Service, you may accumulate Casus Belli against other powers.  See the table below for the conditions for each Casus Belli, the civic that unlocks them, and the percentage of the usual warmonger penalty that is applied.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Holy War: If one of your cities is converted to the enemy's religion[NEWLINE](Diplomatic Service, 50% warmongering)[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]War of Liberation: If a friend or ally had cities conquered[NEWLINE](Diplomatic Service, no warmongering penalty when liberating cities that have been conquered)[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]War of Reconquest: If you had cities conquered in a previous war[NEWLINE](Diplomatic Service, no warmongering penalty when retaking your previous cities)[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Protectorate War: if a city-state you are Suzerain of is attacked[NEWLINE](Diplomatic Service, no warmongering penalty when liberating a city-state target)[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Colonial War: if target civilization is two eras behind you in technology[NEWLINE](Nationalism, 50% warmongering)[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]War of Territorial Expansion: if target civilization borders your nation[NEWLINE](Mobilization, 75% warmongering)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_13_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Agendas</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_13_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Diplomatic Agendas are a major driving force in your relationship with other leaders. They drive the desires and behavior of those leaders. You can use Agendas to know how to get on a leader's good side, or what to do to avoid making them angry.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_13_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Leaders have a Historic Agenda and a Secret Agenda. The Historic Agenda is based on that leader's real-world historical personality and achievements. The Secret Agenda is assigned at beginning of every game, and could be a wide variety of things—maybe they like other civilizations with lots of culture or gold, or maybe they dislike warmongers. Revealing the Secret Agenda is important to knowing what pleases and displeases a leader. Increase your Diplomatic Visibility with each civilization to find out what their leaders' Secret Agendas are.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Diplomatic Visibility and Gossip</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Diplomatic Visibility allows you to receive Gossip, information about another player's actions. You gain more detailed Gossip based on your level of visibility, of which there are 5 levels: None, Limited, Open, Secret, and Top Secret. For example, when you have just met a civilization, you will receive information about their declarations of war, denouncements, friendships, alliances, and when they do something like found a Pantheon or complete a wonder. If you gain Limited Diplomatic Visibility, you will find out some information about their opinion of you and what government they have. At the Open level, you will have access to that civilization's diplomatic agendas, their relationships with other civilizations, and know when they have launched an inquisition.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>You must accumulate Diplomatic Visibility levels individually for each civilization. Levels may be gained by accumulating various sources of Gossip, including:</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Traders. Establish a [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Route to a civilization to increase visibility by one level.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Send a Delegation. Send a Delegation to a civilization to increase visibility by one level. Once Embassies are available, establishing an Embassy will replace this.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Spying or forming an Alliance. Establish a spy in another civilization's city to increase visibility by one level, or you can form an alliance with a friendly civilization. These two actions do not add separate Diplomatic Visibility levels - it does no good to spy on your allies![NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Send a spy on a Listening Post Mission. Performing the Listening Post mission in another civilization's city increases visibility by one level.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Research the Printing Press technology. This will increase your visibility with ALL civilizations by one level.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Play as Catherine de Medici. She gives France one level of access above normal at all times with civilizations she has met.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Spies and Espionage</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Starting in the Industrial era, Spies will become available. You may earn Spies from certain technologies and civics, and they can be built in any city. Spies begin at the Recruit level, and may gain levels from successful offensive operations, or capturing an enemy Spy. Upon reaching level 2, Spies may also earn promotions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Spies are not moved like other units. They jump from city to city using air, sea, road, or foot travel, each with their own travel time. Once established in a city, a Spy can be sent to a specific district and begin their mission. Missions include stealing technology boosts, creating rebel units, or simply increasing diplomatic visibility. Each mission takes a certain amount of time, and will have a different outcome. Your Spy may be killed or captured, or maybe he failed his mission but was not detected, or perhaps it was not detected and the mission was a success.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_CITYSTATES_NAME">
			<Text>City-States</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Introduction</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>City-states are the smaller political entities. They cannot win a game – they're not competing against you – but they can greatly assist or impede your progress towards victory. You can befriend city-states and gain a number of important benefits, you can ignore them and concentrate on bigger and more important foes, or you can conquer them and take their stuff. It's up to you. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>City-State Types</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>There are six different "flavors" of city-states. Each can provide you with different benefits if you befriend or ally with them.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>A trade city-state can provide [ICON_Gold] Gold to your civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>A Religious city-state can provide [ICON_Faith] Faith to your civilization </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>A militaristic city-state can provide [ICON_Production] Production toward producing units.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>A scientific city-state can provide [ICON_Science] Science to your civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_6">
			<Text>A cultural city-state can help you improve your [ICON_Culture] Culture. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_7">
			<Text>An industrial city-state can provide [ICON_Production] Production towards wonders, buildings, and districts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Communicating with City-States</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In order to communicate with a city-state, you must find it first. When one of your units encounters a city-state, the city-state will tell you what type it is, and if you're the first to discover it, you will automatically earn an [ICON_Envoy] Envoy with that city-state. Once you have met, you will be able to undertake "quests" from that city-state. If you want to get in touch with the city-state, you can click on the city itself, or you can go through the City-State Panel. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Envoys</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The bonuses you earn from a city-state depend on how many [ICON_Envoy] Envoys you have sent to the city-state. After earning [ICON_Envoy] Envoys, you will receive a prompt to choose which city-states to send them to. If you have multiple [ICON_Envoy] Envoys, you may divide them between city-states as you desire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Declaring war directly on a city-state removes all [ICON_Envoy] Envoys you had there. Otherwise, [ICON_Envoy] Envoys stay on the city-state permanently. [ICON_Envoy] Envoys at a city-state are visible to all players, and placing them may have diplomatic consequences. The bonuses earned are based on how many [ICON_Envoy] Envoys you have present, regardless of who else has [ICON_Envoy] Envoys there. City-states of a type all share the same Type Bonuses. They are cumulative, so that as a player places more and more [ICON_Envoy] Envoys on a city-state, they stack with the bonuses from before.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>{LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Suzerain</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The civilization with the most [ICON_Envoy] Envoys on a city-state, and at least 3 [ICON_Envoy] Envoys, is considered that city-state's Suzerain. There can be at most one Suzerain; ties are not allowed. If nobody has [ICON_Envoy] Envoys on a city-state, there is no Suzerain. The Suzerain gets several significant benefits:</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Unique city-state bonus: This is a powerful bonus which no other city-state will provide (ex. Jerusalem acts as a second Holy City for your Religion.)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Diplomatic allegiance: The city-state will automatically follow its Suzerain into war and peace, matching the diplomatic state of the Suzerain.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYSTATES_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Resource Sharing: All of the city-state's resources are automatically exported to the Suzerain, and the Suzerain may build improvements in their city-state's territory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_TRADE_NAME">
			<Text>Trade</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TRADE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Introduction</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TRADE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Trader unit is unlocked by researching Foreign Trade, and built in cities. Trader units are on a separate map layer, and do not interact with most normal things on a map. They can freely stack with any other units, and they ignore cultural borders.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TRADE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>When a Trader is in a city the player owns, it can begin a [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Route between that city and another city that is in range, as long as that [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Route is not already active (for example, if I already have a [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Route from Rome to Athens, I cannot start a second one), and the player has not reached their maximum number of [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Routes. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TRADE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Once made, the [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Route will last for at least 20 turns on Standard game speed. The Trader unit will move automatically along its path for the duration of the route, but will not finish the route until it has returned to the origin city's tile. When on an active route, the Trader unit will disregard terrain restrictions and move 1 tile every turn, placing a Road as it moves. Don't forget to protect your Trader from Barbarians or hostile civilizations, as it is vulnerable to pillaging.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TRADE_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Increasing Trade Routes</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TRADE_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>A player can only maintain a limited number of active [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Routes. This capacity is determined primarily by the number of Commercial Hub and Harbor districts they have, but can be increased by other means as well.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TRADE_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Trade Range</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TRADE_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>On land, a [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Route can reach destinations within a range of 15 tiles. Once the player researches the technology that allows embarkation, Traders can also move over water. On water, the range is 30 tiles. Changing between land and water can only be done at a City Center or Harbor district, and the allowance does not carry over. If the city has a Trading Post, the Trader "refuels" its allowance for the new travel domain, and can move further. Otherwise, it must stop at that city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TRADE_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Trading Posts</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TRADE_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Trading Posts extend your trade network and make it more lucrative. Not only do they let you reach further destinations, they also provide bonus yields to any of your [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Routes that pass through them (even if they are not the destination). When a player owns a Trading Post in a city, regardless of who owns the city, that player’s [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Routes can “refuel” their [ICON_Movement] Movement range and reach further destinations. Trading Posts are placed at a city once a [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Route to or from that city successfully completes, and the Trading Post belongs to the player that owned the [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Route.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TRADE_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Yields</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TRADE_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>A [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Route provides yields based on where it goes and what path it takes. The districts within a destination city will determine the types of yields provided to the origin city. For example, trading with a city with a Holy Site will provide [ICON_Faith] Faith, and trading with a city with a Theater Square district will provide [ICON_Culture] Culture.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_GOVT_NAME">
			<Text>Governments and Policies</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Governments</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Governments allow you to customize your civilization to match your play style by offering different combinations of slots to elect different types of policies, as well as offering distinct bonuses.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Unlocked through the Civics Tree, the available governments will change as you progress through time. In the beginning, you will have a simple government with only a handful of slots. But as you reach later eras, more slots in different combinations will be unlocked. On top of this, governments have their own special bonuses; the Theocracy government, for instance, will allow you to purchase land units with [ICON_Faith] Faith and offers a discount on [ICON_Faith] Faith purchases when active.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Finally, all governments have Legacy bonuses based on how long that government was active within your empire. For example, though you may have moved past the Theocracy government, you will receive a Legacy bonus of [ICON_Faith] Faith discounts based on how long that government was active in your empire’s history. You may switch your government at any time. If you switch to a previously adopted government, you will enter a state of Anarchy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Policies</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Policies have concrete effects for gameplay. Some increase your cities’ [ICON_Production] Production, while others generate more wealth, and still others help create a more effective military. There are no right or wrong policy choices in the game, and one policy may be better for a given circumstance than other, or better suit your personal playing style. Try them out and see.  </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>There are 4 types of policies, each of which may be slotted into a corresponding slot in a given government. Slotting these individual policies will give you the benefits described and enhance your game.  </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Gaining Policies</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>You can choose to adopt policies once you have gained [ICON_Culture] Culture to unlock your first government. Policies will be unlocked as you progress through the Civics Tree, and changing your government will allow you to slot different combinations of policies to better suit your play style. Any time a new government or policy is unlocked from the Civics Tree, you will have the opportunity to reselect policies or change your government for free. Otherwise, there will be a cost to make these changes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Policy Types</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>There are 4 different policy types to explore, each attributing to a different style of government. All types must be applied to an empty slot of the same type in the government, but a Wildcard slot can house any type of policy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Military: These policies are best for players who want a strong military on land and sea.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Economic: These policies can be useful in increasing all sorts of yields, whether through increasing district adjacency bonuses or reducing costs.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Diplomatic: These policies are best for players with a strong interest in building relationships, and can help strengthen the bonds with city-states or improve espionage operations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>Wildcard: These policies accelerate the rate of [ICON_GreatPerson] Great Person production.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Anarchy</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Switching to a previously adopted government briefly places your civilization into a state of Anarchy, which has the following negative effects:</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>1. You receive no [ICON_Gold] Gold, [ICON_Science] Science, [ICON_Culture] Culture, or [ICON_Faith] Faith from any source.[NEWLINE]2. Anarchy has no government special bonus or Legacy.[NEWLINE]3. Your policies provide no benefit and cannot be slotted.[NEWLINE]4. You won't be able to change governments until the state of Anarchy ends.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Anarchy lasts a minimum of three turns. The more you previously adopted this form of government, the longer Anarchy will last.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_GREATPEOPLE_NAME">
			<Text>Great People</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GREATPEOPLE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Introduction</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GREATPEOPLE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>[ICON_GreatPerson] Great People are the artists, merchants, engineers, scientists, generals, and admirals who can, singlehandedly, change the course of a civilization. There are nine types of [ICON_GreatPerson] Great People: [ICON_GreatArtist] Great Artists, [ICON_GreatWriter] Great Writers, [ICON_GreatMusician] Great Musicians, [ICON_GreatEngineer] Great Engineers, [ICON_GreatMerchant] Great Merchants, [ICON_GreatScientist] Great Scientists, [ICON_GreatProphet] Great Prophets, [ICON_GreatAdmiral] Great Admirals, and [ICON_GreatGeneral] Great Generals.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GREATPEOPLE_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Earning Great People</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GREATPEOPLE_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>[ICON_GreatPerson] Great People can be earned by generating enough of the right type of points. They are visible to all players, and they are visibly competed for between all players. Only major civilizations can earn [ICON_GreatPerson] Great People, not Barbarians or city-states. Each type of [ICON_GreatPerson] Great Person has its own points which are tracked separately. [ICON_GreatScientist] Great Scientist Points cannot count as [ICON_GreatArtist] Great Artist Points, and so on. The number of points needed to earn a particular [ICON_GreatPerson] Great Person depends that [ICON_GreatPerson] Great Person’s era. A Renaissance-era [ICON_GreatScientist] Great Scientist will cost much less [ICON_GreatScientist] Great Scientist Points than a Modern-era one. The points come from a variety of sources.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GREATPEOPLE_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Each district, and the buildings within it, provides points towards its associated [ICON_GreatPerson] Great Person type. This is the slow but steady source of points. Districts also allow a city to use [ICON_Production] Production towards projects which, when completed, contribute [ICON_GreatPerson] Great Person points.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GREATPEOPLE_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Using Great People</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GREATPEOPLE_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Each [ICON_GreatPerson] Great Person individual has a different effect, inspired by history. Most effects are strongly linked to a particular era of play, and are not optimal for use outside of that time. The effects fall into two broad categories, "birth" effects and "action" effects.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GREATPEOPLE_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>A Birth Effect happens as soon as the [ICON_GreatPerson] Great Person is spawned on the map, and do not need to be activated. These are mostly used for Great Generals and Great Admirals.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GREATPEOPLE_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>An Action Effect must be activated by the [ICON_GreatPerson] Great Person by using a “charge” at a certain location. The number of charges, the type of location needed, and the effect activated will vary based on the individual. Most individuals only have 1 charge and can only activate at a district matching its type (ex. most [ICON_GreatScientist] Great Scientists have 1 charge and must use it at a Campus). Like other charge-based units, the individual will disappear when all charges are depleted.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GREATPEOPLE_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Moving Great People</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GREATPEOPLE_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>[ICON_GreatPerson] Great People can move about the board like any other units. They are non-combat units, which means that they cannot stack in a tile with other non-combat units (Workers, Settlers), but they can stack with one military unit. If an enemy unit enters a [ICON_GreatPerson] Great Person's tile, that [ICON_GreatPerson] Great Person automatically retreats to a nearby city if able (the enemy doesn't capture it.)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_AIRCOMBAT_NAME">
			<Text>Air Combat</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AIRCOMBAT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Introduction</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AIRCOMBAT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>There are four main types of air units: support reconnaissance, support defense, fighters, and strategic bombers. These can be produced in any city that has built an Aerodrome and researched the prerequisite technologies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AIRCOMBAT_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Air Bases</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AIRCOMBAT_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Air units do not move around the map like ground and naval units. They must be "based" somewhere. The City Center can always hold one air unit, but building an Aerodrome, Airstrip, or Aircraft Carrier can increase your available slots. The Aerodrome can have up to 8 slots, the Airstrip 3, and the Aircraft Carrier begins with 2 but can gain more through promotions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AIRCOMBAT_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Patrols</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AIRCOMBAT_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Fighter aircraft can be deployed to a valid hex within their [ICON_Movement] Movement range from a friendly air base. After it is deployed, the aircraft will begin flying an orbiting pattern around its effective intercept range (currently 1 hex radius). This should make it more clear to both the attacker and defender the status of the Fighters in the Patrol state.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AIRCOMBAT_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Patrol state is continuing, somewhat like the 'Fortify' unit operation. Once an aircraft has been set to Patrol it will do so until it is ordered otherwise or it is destroyed. While Patrolling, the aircraft will continue to intercept and defend against multiple attackers. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AIRCOMBAT_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>At any time during the player's turn, Fighter aircraft can 'Return to Base' (station at a friendly air base) in order to heal. Aircraft stationed at an air base do not intercept attacking aircraft. Aircraft can heal at the end of the game turn when stationed on a City Center, Aerodrome, Airstrip, or Aircraft Carrier only if they have not been involved in combat. Healing is 'fastest' on an Aerodrome district, and less so on Airstrips and Carriers. These values can be increased through promotions and/or Policies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AIRCOMBAT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Air Strikes</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AIRCOMBAT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Heavy Bomber aircraft cannot deploy on Patrols, but they are instead considered 'stationed' at a friendly air base and can carry out attacks from that base. Unlike Fighter aircraft, Bombers do not engage in dogfighting, but they head straight for their target and attack. Bomber aircraft can 'pillage' district buildings and city improvements by attacking them directly. The effect is the same as a ground unit pillage action with one exception - the attacking air unit does not get the resulting benefit from the pillage action. In order for a pillage to occur, the attacking air unit must be at 50% health or higher.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AIRCOMBAT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Interceptions</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AIRCOMBAT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Fighters can be set to "Intercept" enemy air attacks.  (AA Gun and Mobile SAM automatically intercept; they don't need to be given a special mission.) If an air unit tries an air strike against a target within the range of an intercepting unit, the interceptor will fire on the attacker and do damage to it. Unless the attacker is killed by the interceptor, the air strike proceeds. Only one unit can intercept an air strike, and once it does so, it cannot intercept any more that turn.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_NUKES_NAME">
			<Text>Nukes</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_NUKES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Nuclear Device Types</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_NUKES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>There are 2 categories of atomic weapons: the Nuclear Device and the Thermonuclear Device.  They can be built as a city Project in any city and both require the Uranium resource to produce. There is no limit on the number that a player can build. [NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Once a Nuclear or Thermonuclear Device is created, it is added to the player's inventory and can then be used by any unit or improvement capable of deploying it on the map. This includes bomber aircraft, Nuclear Submarines, and the Missile Silo.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_NUKES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Nuclear Devices have a blast radius of 1. When deployed from a Missile Silo, they have a [ICON_Range] Range of 12. They cost 14 [ICON_Gold] Gold per turn to maintain.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_NUKES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Thermonuclear Devices have a blast radius of 2. When deployed from a Missile Silo, they have a [ICON_Range] Range of 15. They cost 16 [ICON_Gold] Gold per turn to maintain.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_NUKES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Nuclear Destruction</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_NUKES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>When an atomic weapon is detonated, several things happen to all the hexes within the blast radius. [ICON_Citizen] Citizens "working" the affected tiles are eliminated, units occupying the affected tiles are destroyed, and all tile improvements are pillaged. Any districts and buildings in the affected tiles are also pillaged and must be repaired to be used again. All tiles affected are contaminated with radioactive fallout.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_NUKES_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Nuclear Contamination</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_NUKES_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>After a nuclear attack, fallout will contaminate every tile affect  by the blast. Any units that end their turn in a contaminated tile take 50 damage each turn. [ICON_Production] Production cannot be applied to anything in tiles containing contamination, such as repairing buildings and districts. Tiles that are contaminated cannot be worked by the city until the contamination timer expires or until the tile is "cleaned." </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_NUKES_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Nuclear contamination can be "cleaned" from affected tiles by Builder and Military Engineer units. Cleaning a contaminated tile takes 1 build charge. Builder and Military Engineer units that are able to clean contaminated hexes will take less damage if they end their turn in such a hex. Any city tiles not directly affected by the nuclear blast will still function normally and contribute to the city’s yield.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_TOURISM_NAME">
			<Text>Tourism</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOURISM_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Introduction</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOURISM_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>[ICON_Tourism] Tourism is needed in order to win a Culture Victory. You can generate [ICON_Tourism] Tourism through Great Works, wonders, Holy Sites, [ICON_GreatWork_Relic] Relics, [ICON_GreatWork_Artifact] Artifacts, Seaside Resorts and National Parks. You can boost your [ICON_Tourism] Tourism through [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Routes, Open Borders, Great People, policies, and shared (or conflicting) late game governments. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOURISM_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Great Works, Relics, and Artifacts</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOURISM_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Great Works come in five different types. Writing, Art, and Music which can be generated through [ICON_GreatPerson] Great People, [ICON_GreatWork_Artifact] Artifacts, which are retrieved from Antiquity Sites by Archaeologists, and [ICON_GreatWork_Relic] Relics, which are created by Apostles with the Martyr ability when they die in Theological Combat, or obtained through Tribal Villages or the city-state Kandy. Once earned, a Great Work can be housed in a Great Work slot in the appropriate building or Wonder. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOURISM_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Seaside Resorts</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOURISM_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Seaside Resorts are a special improvement that can be built after researching the Radio technology. These generate [ICON_Tourism] Tourism based on the tile's Appeal.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOURISM_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>National Parks</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOURISM_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Designating National Parks can greatly enhance [ICON_Tourism] Tourism and [ICON_Amenities] Amenities. National Parks are designated by Naturalist units, which may be purchased in your city with [ICON_Faith] Faith after researching the Conservation civic.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOURISM_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>National Parks can be built on a cluster of any four tiles that meet the following requirements:</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOURISM_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>1. The tiles must be natural wonders, mountains, or a tile with an Appeal of Charming or better.[NEWLINE]2. All four of the tiles must be owned by the same city.[NEWLINE]3. The tiles must be contiguous and form a diamond shape.[NEWLINE]4. No tile can have an improvement or district.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOURISM_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>You can select a Naturalist to reveal any valid locations on the map. Sending the Naturalist to any highlighted tile will reveal the Designate National Park action button. Clicking on this button designates the National Park and consumes the Naturalist.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOURISM_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>A National Park's [ICON_Tourism] Tourism output is equal to the total Appeal of all the tiles included in the park. Additionally, the city that owns the park receives 2 [ICON_Amenities] Amenities, and the four closest cities in your civilization receive 1 [ICON_Amenities] Amenity.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_VICTORY_NAME">
			<Text>Victory and Defeat</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Introduction</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>There are multiple ways to win and lose a game in Civilization VI. It's important to keep an eye on your opponents' progress toward victory as you advance your own civilization. There's nothing quite as annoying as to be on the verge of capturing your last surviving enemy's final city, only to watch helplessly as he or she completes her Mars colony and wins an upset Science Victory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Domination Victory</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>If you are the last player in possession of your own original [ICON_Capital] Capital, you win. So if you capture all other civilizations' [ICON_Capital] Capitals and hang onto your own, you've achieved victory. However, this can be tricky. Suppose you're in a five-player game and you capture three of your opponents' original [ICON_Capital] Capitals, but the fifth player sneaks in and captures your [ICON_Capital] Capital while you're not paying attention – then he would win immediately. In other words, it doesn't matter who captures what: it's the last player holding onto his original [ICON_Capital] Capital who gets the victory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>If you've lost your original [ICON_Capital] Capital, but still possess other cities, you can still win another type of victory: Culture, Science, Score, or Religious. However, you cannot win a Domination Victory until and unless you recapture your own original [ICON_Capital] Capital. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Science Victory</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Science Victory is achieved by the first player to establish a colony on the planet Mars. Once the Space Race is underway, and someone has launched their first satellite, all players will know who is attempting this victory. Players receive bonuses for reaching each milestone along the way to victory. The following steps must be completed in order:</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Launch a Satellite into Space:</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Reminiscent of Sputnik in 1957, you may build a satellite to launch into space after researching Rocketry and building a Spaceport. After completing the Earth Satellite project, your satellite will be launched and you will be awarded visibility of the entire map. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Land a Human on the Moon:</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>Just like the Apollo 11 mission in 1969, you will send a human to the moon. This is unlocked after researching the technology Satellites, and can be built in any city with a Spaceport. Choose to produce the Moon Landing project to begin this mission. After the rocket has been launched, you will immediately be rewarded a lump sum of [ICON_Culture] Culture.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_6">
			<Text>Establish a Colony on Mars:</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_7">
			<Text>Science fiction for now, perhaps – but now you can be the first to send your people to Mars. After researching Robotics, Nuclear Fission, and Nanotechnology, you may build the Reactor, Habitation, and Hydroponics module projects in any city with a Spaceport. Note that more than one Spaceport means parallel production! </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_8">
			<Text>Once every piece is launched, you have won the game.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Culture Victory</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>If you aim to be the cultural epicenter of the world, this is the victory for you. The first civilization to possess a total number of [ICON_Tourism] Visiting Tourists that exceeds the [ICON_Tourism] Domestic Tourists of each other civilization in the game wins the Culture Victory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>[ICON_Tourism] Tourism is generated by [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Routes, shared (or conflicting) late game Governments, open borders, Great Works housed in your civilization, [ICON_GreatWork_Relic] Relics housed in your civilization, Holy Sites, National Parks, [ICON_GreatWork_Artifact] Artifacts, and wonders.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Religious Victory</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In order to obtain a Religious Victory, you must make your Religion the predominant Religion for every other major civilization in the game. This means not every one of a civilization's cities must follow your Religion, just the majority.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>While your Religion will spread passively simply by settling near other players, it is your Missionaries and Apostles who offer the best chance at victory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Score Victory</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_VICTORY_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In many games, one of the players will win the game by achieving one of the possible victories. However, if no one achieves one of these victories by the year 2050 (or a player-set turn), the winner is determined by the surviving civilization's "score." Points for your score are earned from number of civics, number of population, number of cities, number of technologies, number of "future technologies", number of wonders, military accomplishments, number of [ICON_GreatPerson] Great People, and number of Beliefs.</Text>
		</Row>
	</BaseGameText>
</GameData>
