<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<BaseGameText>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_INTRO_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Your Religious choices will have a major impact on your civilization. With the introduction of the brand new Religious Victory and Theological Combat, you have new and exciting tools at your disposal to spread your Beliefs to other cities and civilizations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_BUDDHISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>And the wheel turns … that is, the wheel of dharma, the Buddha’s teachings about the path to Nirvana, turns. Followed by more than 350 million people throughout the world today, Buddhism is based on the teachings of revered spiritual leader Siddhartha Gautama, known as the “Supreme Buddha, the Enlightened One.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_BUDDHISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As the central figure of Buddhism, Buddha was not recognized as a god, nor did he presume to claim a connection to God. Rather, Buddha taught his followers a path to enlightenment based on his own life experience, a distinction that differentiates Buddhism from many of the world’s other major religions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_BUDDHISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>A one-time prince in a small Indian kingdom until the age of 29, Siddhartha turned to the ascetic’s life after venturing outside the confines of the palace (there's a moral in there somewhere). He meandered around India for a few years, eventually sitting under a fig tree to meditate; there after several days he found “enlightenment,” and so released himself from the cycle of worldly suffering and arose the Buddha.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_BUDDHISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Buddhism’s primary tenets, the Four Noble Truths and the Eightfold Path, lay out the means by which one can achieve Nirvana, or peace from unending suffering. In their simplest form, the Four Noble Truths tell us that life is suffering, that suffering arises from our attachment to desires, that suffering ceases when that attachment ceases, and that freedom from suffering is only possible by practicing the Eightfold Path. So, to achieve enlightenment, one must give up everything one enjoys.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_CATHOLICISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Roman Catholicism refers to the theology and doctrine of the Christian church under the auspices of the Holy See, the papacy based in Rome. According to ecclesiastical scholars, Catholicism is distinguished from other branches of Christianity by its commitment to the church’s traditions, to the sacraments, and its priesthood as interpreters of the Bible.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_CATHOLICISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The earliest known use of the term “Catholic Church” is by Ignatius of Antioch around 107 AD. The early church was organized based on the rule of three patriarchs, those of Rome, Alexandria and Antioch – to which were later added the patriarchs of Constantinople and Jerusalem. But too many patriarchs tend to muddy the holy waters.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_CATHOLICISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Soon, the patriarch of Rome claimed special authority based on the connection between St. Peter and that city. For 1000 years, Roman Catholicism dominated Europe, until the Great Schism of 1054 AD that gave rise to Eastern Orthodoxy. Some 500 years later another major division in Christianity occurred with the Protestant Reformation, which saw many in Europe reject the teachings and practices of Catholicism in favor of more personal expressions of belief.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_CATHOLICISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Presently, the Roman Catholic Church considers those not in communion with the Vatican to be “non-Catholics” but tolerates differing interpretations of the Bible. A bit of a shift from the days when it burned heretics and most everyone else who differed from the Catholic dogma.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_CONFUCIANISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Confucianism is a faith based on the teachings of the Chinese philosopher Confucius (551-479 BC). Originally introduced as an ethical and social philosophy for the privileged elite, Confucianism has grown to a following of several million in the present day, mainly concentrated in the regions of East Asia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_CONFUCIANISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>During his life, Confucius sought to instill a strong belief in personal morality, social responsibility, and family loyalty, as each person served their “proper” role in society. He set his musings down in the so-called Five Classics. As a humanist philosophy, Confucianism focuses on the ability of every human being to learn, grow, and improve through “ethical” behavior and consideration for others.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_CONFUCIANISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Following Confucius’ death, his teachings spread for nearly 200 years until attempts at suppressing the philosophy were undertaken in earnest by the Qin Dynasty. The Qin rulers believed that Confucianism was a direct threat to their authority, and, as a result, they had most Confucian books burned, including many of Confucius' original writings. Temples were destroyed across the country, and a few stubborn followers of Confucianism buried alive.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_CONFUCIANISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Despite these attempts to wipe out the Confucian belief system, a hidden store of Confucian manuscripts was later discovered in the walls of a scholar’s home, and the religion found new life after the fall of the Qin. In the present-day, the works of Confucianism are studied by folk throughout the world. Although they approach Confucianism as more a philosophy than a religion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_HINDUISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Widely considered the oldest religion still in practice today, Hinduism – or the Sanatana Dharma (the “eternal law”) – is based upon a series of ancient manuscripts known as the Vedas. This collection of Sanskrit texts, encompassing four main scriptural works, is thought to have been written over 3500 years ago. With one billion (and ever growing) followers throughout the world today (most being concentrated in India and Southeast Asia), Hinduism is a fusion of various cultures and traditions, with no single founder nor creed, and as much a way of life as a religion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_HINDUISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Vedas focus on a single, unifying force that governs all aspects of our existence. Although there are a number of recognizable deities within Hinduism, notably Shiva, Vishnu, and Brahma, these deities are all but a small part of the greater God. Dharma, or the “Ultimate Reality,” is the universal power or law by which all things that exist are bound. The only means of breaking free from unending reincarnation is through meditation and the realization that the one God is in all things. Hindus also firmly believe in Karma, by which our deeds, both good and bad, have a cause-and-effect relationship on how our lives progress.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_HINDUISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Although there are a number of competing sects within Hinduism and the Vedic schools may differ in their interpretation of the ancient manuscripts, they do not view each other as rivals, and in fact share ideas and opinions openly amongst one another.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_ISLAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The second largest religion in the world, Islam is based on the belief that there is only one true God, Allah, and he has made his will manifest through a number of prophets on Earth. The most important of these prophets, Muhammad (570-632 AD), recorded God’s words in the Muslim holy book, the Qur’an, after suffering a round of visions. From this point forward, Muhammad preached that the only path to salvation was to devote oneself entirely to God through daily prayer, and strict adherence to the laws set forth by Him.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_ISLAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Five Pillars of Islam, the framework through which salvation can be attained, state in their most basic form that there is no god but God, and Muhammad is his prophet; one must pray daily to God at the five established times; one must give to the needy to support them; one must fast from dawn until dusk during the month of Ramadan; and one must make a pilgrimage to Mecca, at least once in a lifetime, during the holy month of Dhu al-Hijjah.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_ISLAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>As was the case with the founding of most religions, Muhammad and his followers were met by staunch resistance from other faiths. Despite this, the message spread across the Middle East following his death. Since that time, Islam has splintered into a number of competing branches, the largest being the Sunni and Shia denominations. Although bound by their overarching beliefs, these two sects quibble over interpretation of who should lead Islam’s faithful.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_JUDAISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to Rabbinic Judaism, a patriarchal God revealed his laws and commandments to Moses on Mount Sinai while the “Chosen People” were wandering about the desert after escaping from bondage. And it all got written down in the Torah (with some parts morphing into the Christian Old Testament), which forms the foundation of the Tanakh. In point of prosaic fact, it is generally believed by scholars that Judaism first appeared some 3500 years ago, one of the earliest monotheistic religions, as an evolution of several Babylonian religions around the 6th Century BC.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_JUDAISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Although Judaism’s core doctrines have been debated by rabbis for centuries, the Jews believe they are the Chosen People, selected by God to be in covenant with him, and that God will send a messiah to bring all of the chosen back to Israel. He just hasn’t arrived yet. Although the Jews have been persecuted throughout history and scattered across the world, Judaism as a religion has survived and even prospered. The Jewish ethno-religion numbers around 14 million, or roughly 0.2% of the world’s population.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_JUDAISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Despite their inherent differences, many aspects of Judaism are closely tied with both Christianity and Islam, as they are all considered “Abrahamic” religions, all descended from Abraham, the father of both Isaac (ancestor of the Israelites) and Ishmael (ancestor of Muhammed).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_ORTHODOXY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The goal of the estimated 300 million Orthodox Christians is to draw nearer to God throughout their lives through theosis, a spiritual pilgrimage to become more “Christ-like” (although it’s a little vague as to exactly what that entails). The earliest recorded use of the term “orthodox” in relation to Christianity was in the Codex Justinianus (c. 530 AD) where it meant “conforming to the creeds of the early Church.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_ORTHODOXY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Orthodox Church traces its roots to the Great Schism. During the 9th and 10th centuries AD the Christian church under the Patriarch of Constantinople made significant conversions among the peoples of Eastern Europe, including Kievan Russia and the Balkans. Doctrinal issues such as the filioque split and the authority of the Pope over the Patriarch in matters religious, exacerbated by the political and economic rivalry of Rome and Constantinople, led to a falling out. The Orthodox Church holds that only it practiced the original and true faith as established by Christ and passed down by the Apostles.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_ORTHODOXY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Moreover, after the fall of Constantinople to the Ottomans in 1453, the Eastern Church became ever more isolated from Rome under the relatively tolerant rule of the Turks. Meanwhile the Orthodox Church flourished under the Russian tsars, with lots of converts among the Slavs. Although somewhat diminished by Communist rule and all that rampant secularism, Eastern Orthodoxy holds fast to the old Christian belief in sin, salvation, and the incarnation of the spirit.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_PROTESTANTISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Protestant Reformation, as a movement that would eventually divide Christian Europe, began as a protest in Germany against Catholic doctrine and practices, especially in regard to salvation, justification and interpretation of the Bible. Although with some differences, all the Protestant movements maintained two tenets: that the “Good Book,” rather than papal interpretation, was the sole source of authority for Christians; and that salvation comes only through a personal connection with Jesus as the Christ rather than through good works or indulgences.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_PROTESTANTISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Based upon his readings of humanist scholars, in 1517 AD Martin Luther, a German priest in the university town of Wittenberg, published his 95 theses criticizing certain practices of the Catholic Church. His example saw other liberal religious thinkers advance their own critiques of the church; soon “evangelical” Lutheran denominations sprang up across Germany and Scandinavia along with “reformed” creeds in Switzerland under John Calvin. Meanwhile religion became mixed with politics in England and elsewhere, bringing yet more Protestant churches into existence (although Henry’s lust for Anne Boleyn had more to with it than belief).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_PROTESTANTISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The split in the Catholic faith would ignite a series of religious wars, Christians slaughtering Christians (instead of Muslims, Jews and other non-Christians) … echoes of which resonate still. Despite numerous movements and divisions within Protestantism since, its many, many (too numerous to keep track of) denominations together number about 670 million members.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_SHINTO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>With no founding figure and no central doctrine, Shinto is the rather amorphous spiritual belief of the Japanese people based on an individual’s connection to the physical world … and to Japan itself. The recorded history of Shinto dates back to the two great works written by O no Yasumaro at the behest of the Empress Gemmei: the Kojiki (c. 712 AD) and the Nihon Shoki (c. 720 AD). Based on oral traditions, the first establishes the imperial family as the soul of Japanese culture, while the second focuses on the “correctness” of the social hierarchy and orderly living.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_SHINTO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>One of the central aspects of Shintoism is the worship of spirits, known as Kami, who are acknowledged through the visiting of shrines. Although the Kami are not considered gods, they are spirits or entities with close ties to humans, and they can have a beneficial effect on the course of one’s existence. However, Shinto is not focused on the belief in Kami, but on the ritual of devotion itself. By paying respects to the Kami at shrines, one is showing interest and as such the Kami may bring positive benefits.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_SHINTO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Although Shinto has been central to Japanese life for centuries, with over 100 million adherents found in Japan today, Shinto is not a religion in the traditional sense, but an ingrained faith unique to the Japanese people.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_SIKHISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Founded in the 15th Century AD by the Guru Nanak Dev, Sikhism has grown through the efforts of successive Sikh gurus who espoused the virtues of peace, equality, and selfless service. Sikhism currently has over 20 million followers, based primarily in the Punjab region of India. The Sikhs believe in only one god, who has no physical form, but every Sikh has the ability to speak to God, and all are equal in God’s eyes – a very egalitarian faith.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_SIKHISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Sikhs are known for their generosity towards others, as one of the primary tenets of their religion is the idea that all people are created equal, regardless of religion, race, or sex. In differing from other major religions, Sikhism supports that belief that acts of good in service to others are more important than any form of ritual.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_SIKHISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Sikhs are also bound to defend against injustices, supporting all who are oppressed, as truth and peace should prevail above all else. The Sikhs believe that to attain salvation, every Sikh must practice disciplined meditation, as only through personal observance and focus on God can salvation be reached. Thus, there are a number of restrictions placed on the followers of the Sikh faith, including the requirement that they not cut their hair, not consume any intoxicating substances, and notably, not perform any ritual, superstition or pilgrimage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_TAOISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Taoism is a unique religion, founded on the basis of the ancient beliefs and philosophies of the Chinese kingdoms of the 2nd Century AD. Although not attributed directly to a single founding figure like most faiths, Taoism grew based on the writings of the philosopher Lao-Tsu, who wrote the Tao Te Ching in the 4th Century BC. Zhang Daoling, the first “Celestial Master,” founded the first school of Tao based on the works of Lao-Tsu. Others followed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_TAOISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Unlike most modern religions, Taoism is not dependent on the existence of some mythical, all-powerful, anthropomorphic “god.” Rather, it is a philosophical approach to life. One of the religion’s best known precepts, Yin and Yang, represent the world filled with complimentary forces in harmony and balance, a common example being light and dark. Followers of Taoism are encouraged to exercise humility, kindness, and compassion in their daily lives in order to maintain this balance in the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_TAOISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Throughout its history, Taoism has had many sects and branches split from the original school, as other elements of Chinese tradition crept into the philosophy. Magic, alchemy, and other mystical forces have all been included in some forms of Taoist thought since its early days. Although estimates of the total number of followers vary widely, it is believed that there are still several million “true” believers in China and the surrounding regions today.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_ZOROASTRIANISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Zoroastrianism, an ancient faith based on the teachings of the prophet Zoroaster, is believed to have been founded some 3500 years ago in the region around Persia. Once one of the largest religions in the world, Zoroastrian is only followed today by an estimated 200 thousand adherents, living primarily in India, Pakistan, and Iran. In general, it has been marginalized and overshadowed by Islam since the decline of the Sassanid Empire after the 7th Century AD.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_ZOROASTRIANISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Zoroastrianism is considered by some to be the oldest monotheistic religion in the world, although this is a point of contention among scholars. Zoroastrian beliefs are centered on the creator god Ahura Mazda, who is the focal point of all Zoroastrian tradition and worship. It is said that Ahura Mazda revealed his wisdom to Zoroaster, who then wandered about to spread the teachings across the region. The sacred texts of Zoroastrianism, known collectively as the Avesta, contain hymns said to have been written by Zoroaster himself.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RELIGIONS_PAGE_RELIGION_ZOROASTRIANISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>As with most religions, Zoroastrianism outlines the ways in which humans can supposedly live in harmony, in this case through “good thoughts and good actions.” Zoroastrians are often mischaracterized as fire worshippers, in part because of the prevalence of fire as a symbol in Zoroastrian rituals. In Zoroastrianism, fire represents the light of Ahura Mazda and believers will pray in the direction of the light, rather than to the fire itself.</Text>
		</Row>
	</BaseGameText>
</GameData>