<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Anton Strenger (Firaxis Games) -->
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<EnglishText>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AUCKLAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When the Maori settled upon an isthmus in what is now northern New Zealand, they found the surrounding landscape full of fertile land, lush jungle, and dormant volcanos. Protected natural harbors on either side of the isthmus offered plentiful fishing and a base for war canoes ('waka taua'). The settlers named it 'Tamaki Makaurau'—roughly translating to "the maiden sought by a hundred lovers."</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AUCKLAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In 1840—nearly 500 years after the Maori arrival—the new British Governor William Hobson decided Tamaki Makaurau would make the perfect colonial capital of the very new New Zealand. He renamed it Auckland—roughly translating to "my patron is the Earl of Auckland, and I want him to think of me favorably when I ask for more money."</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AUCKLAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Though the capital later moved to Wellington, Auckland's loss of political prestige was more than compensated by its vibrant economy. Even its limited military skirmishes had financial resolutions: when a Maori tribe sought to attack the city in  protest of their chief's arrest, Aucklanders settled the matter by handing over a substantial amount of tobacco. The opening of the Panama Canal in the early 20th Century further expanded Auckland's role as a vital stop in South Pacific shipping routes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ANTANANARIVO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The capital of Madagascar began as a sleepy highland town of the Vazimba people, until Imerinan King Andrianjaka took it for himself in the early 17th Century. From his royal compound he could look down upon the ever-expanding rice paddies that would keep his people fed. After a period of expansion and order, a decades-long Imerinan civil war turned Antananarivo into one of four capitals—but once the dust settled, it regained its status as the political center of the kingdom.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ANTANANARIVO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In the early 19th Century, King Radama I decreed the city open to European settlement. The city's booming economy drew artisans, manufacturers, and settlers. Factories flourished, infrastructure kept pace with the city's expansion, and distinctive architectural styles transformed the city's appearance. Radama's successors continued to cultivate cultural and technological advances, eventually decreeing a mandatory education for the city's citizens.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ANTANANARIVO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Then, in 1894, France invaded. Madagascar regained its independence from colonial authority in 1960, and with it, a modernized Antananarivo.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ARMAGH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Irish town of Armagh has long known religion. Thought to have been a worship site for ancient pagans, it gained prominence in the 5th Century when Saint Patrick, a Christian missionary, constructed and consecrated a stone church on the summit of a hill. Around that sprang a monastery, and then a town devoted to spreading  Christianity throughout Ireland—a beachhead of theology.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ARMAGH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>This is not to imply that Armagh is a coastal city. Its location in Northern Ireland is a short 25 miles to the ocean. Nevertheless, its reputation as the seat of the Church of Ireland made it a tempting target for those looking to score riches. Vikings raided Armagh's monastery twice in the 9th Century, each time making the overland trek to abscond with armloads of religious relics. John de Courcy, an invading Norman knight, thought to repeat the tradition when he plundered the town in the late 12th Century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_GRANADA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the 8th Century the Umayyad Caliphate spread through the Iberian Peninsula, rapidly conquering Visigothic Hispania. Granada, a fortified settlement in what is now southern Spain, was swept up in the invasion. In time to come (the late 15th Century, to be exact) its surrender to the Catholic Monarchs ('Los Reyes Católicos') would end the Reconquista of Andalusia—but for three quarters of a millennium, Granada belonged to the Moors.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_GRANADA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Located at the base of the Sierra Nevada range, Granada had the misfortune of being nearly indefensible due to its location on a low-lying plain. Its Moorish rulers quickly realized this and transferred their seat of power to the more defensible foothills overlooking the town. Part of their plans involved the building of alcazars, one of which would in later years be renovated into the beautiful Alhambra.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_GRANADA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Granada's Moorish masters shifted through the centuries. The Almohad replaced the Almoravids, who had themselves succeeded the remnants of the Umayyad. The city's fortunes changed again in the 13th Century with the Nasrid dynasty, whose alliance with the Catholic kingdom of Castile led to the Emirate of Granada. Direct access to trade centers in sub-Saharan Africa bought Granada freedom from the Reconquista—for a time.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MUSCAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The trade flowing through Muscat has been its lifeblood for at least two millennia. Nestled against the foothillls of the Al Hajar mountains, Ptolemy called it the Hidden Port ('Cryptus Portus') as early as the 1st Century. Unfortunately the city was not hidden well enough—its prime location at the mouth of the Persian Gulf has long since made it a tempting target for conquest.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MUSCAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Over the centuries Muscat's port has flown many banners: Sassanid, Arabian (under which it converted to Islam in the 7th Century), Abbasid, Seljuk, and Persian, to name a few. In the early 16th Century, a Portuguese admiral sought to open trade relations—with cannons, burning most of Muscat to the ground. It was rebuilt and remained under Portuguese rule until 1650, when the Omani forced them out and reclaimed the port city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MUSCAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Muscat has long come to conflict with the interior tribes of Oman, most commonly over self-governance. Amidst one such period of turmoil in the 18th Century rose the Al Bu Sa'id dynasty, which has remained unbroken through modern times. Today, an extensively modernized Muscat serves as Oman's capital and remains an important trading port.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PALENQUE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The "lost" Mayan city of Palenque was more accurately abandoned after a millennium of growth, sophistication, and eventually stagnation. Its earliest ruins date it to the 3rd Century BCE, where it was ruled by a series of kings and queens, many of whom are lost to history. Its darkest days were at the turn of the 7th Century, when a punishing war with the rival city of Calakmul left the Palenque sacked and most of its leadership captured or killed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PALENQUE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Queen regent Sak K'uk' ruled for three years before transferring leadership to her 12-year-old son, K'inich Janaab Pakal. The young king would come to be known as Pakal the Great, the architect of Palenque's prosperity. In his nearly 70 years of rule he pushed to rebuild and expand the city, erasing the scars left by Calakmul, and ordered the city's history carved into the walls and columns of its newly constructed temples and palaces. At the height of its power, Palenque forged alliances, captured enemy kings, and forced defeated rivals to pay tribute.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PALENQUE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>After Pakal's death, a grueling conflict with the rival realm of Toniná took its toll on Palenque. By the early 9th Century, the city was left to the jungle.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_EYJAFJALLAJOKULL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Eyjafjallajökull is the name for both an Icelandic volcano and the ice cap plugging its caldera. Though the volcano has remained active for over a millennia, it was little known outside of Iceland until a minor eruption in 2010. Its subsequent ash cloud halted air traffic in Europe for nearly a week and spawned thousands of hours of breathless news reports. Eyjafjallajökull's eruptions have traditionally predicted even larger eruptions of the nearby Katla, a far more active subglacial volcano—much to the chagrin of European air traffic controllers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_LYSEFJORDEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Glacial erosion from the Ice Age carved the majestic Lysefjord out of what is now southern Norway. A marathon's length of cold, black water wends between towering cliffs of pale granite. The brighter coloration of these rocks is what gives the "light fjord" its name, despite their tendency to throw the water below into shadow. The striking Pulpit Rock (or "Preikestolen") is the large, flat top of a nearly 2000 ft cliff near the mouth of Lysefjord, perfect for shouting stentorian exhortations at boats passing below.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_GIANTS_CAUSEWAY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Clusters of geometric columns known as the Giant's Causeway can be found along the coast of Northern Ireland. The columns vary in height, like a pipe organ that got away from itself. The columns closest to the coast disappear into the North Channel, while others jut out of the ground like basalt palisade walls. Legends claim the causeway was built by Irish giant Finn MacCool, who had been challenged to a fight by Scottish giant Benandonner. (Geologists disagree, connecting the pillar formation to volcanic activity 50 million years ago.)</Text>
		</Row>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_ALCAZAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
      <Text>The alcázars (a sort of final refuge) were castle-palaces built in many of the Moorish cities in al-Andalus, mostly between the 8th and 15th centuries AD. Many of these were built as the residence of the Moorish governors … and came in quite handy, not only against unruly rivals but also later against that perplexing Christian Reconquista. Many still stand, and are quite famous: for instance, those in Segovia. Toledo, Cordoba (the famed Alcázar de los Reyes Cristianos), Burgos, and Seville. The last, as an example, was built in 913 as a fort for the Cordoban governor; in the 11th Century, it was expanded into the palace known as al-Muwarak (“the Blessed”). The Christian king Fernando III made it his royal residence when he captured Seville in 1248. Now it is just another stop for tour buses in the city.</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_MONASTERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
      <Text>A monastery, in the Roman Catholic tradition, is a complex of buildings that serves as communal home and workplace for monks (and nuns, in modern usage termed “convents”). These also include someplace reserved for prayer, such as a chapel or church. And many housed hospitals, schools, distilleries, and more. According to legend, Christian monasticism began in Egypt, although the first monastery in Europe was founded c. 344 AD near Chirpan (Bulgaria) by St. Athanasius. A couple centuries later, in 529, Saint Benedict established the monastery at Monte Cassino, laying the pattern for Catholic monasticism. Monasteries soon began appearing all over Europe, and beyond.</Text>
    </Row>
	</EnglishText>
</GameData>
