<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<BaseGameText>
		<!-- Leaders -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_RADZIWILL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A Lithuanian noble and avowed Calvinist, Mikołaj the Black has always known ambition. He capitalizes upon his cousin Barbara's affair with Polish King Sigismund II to elevate his personal fortunes. An alliance with his cousin, Mikołaj the Red, has further propelled his family's influence amongst the Lithuanian nobility.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_RADZIWILL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Mikołaj's views on Poland and its relationship to Lithuania are complex. Though he strongly advocates for Lithuanian sovereignty and against a formalized Polish-Lithuanian union, he also urges his fellow Lithuanian nobles to adopt Polish culture. Perhaps a common language will allow them to more forcefully advocate against the union.</Text>
		</Row>	
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_RADZIWILL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Despite his feelings on Lithuanian independence, there is no question of his resolve against the many threats to the Polish and Lithuanian people. As Grand Chancellor of Lithuania he will rely upon all tools to thwart his nation's enemies—whether the stroke of the pen or the thrust of the pike.</Text>
		</Row>	
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_POTOCKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Proud Polish son Stanisław "Rewera" Potocki fought his first skirmish at the age of 18. He acquitted himself well enough against Polish rebels to gain an affection for fighting, and has spent the bulk of his life since on the battlefield.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_POTOCKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Though Stanisław has acquired a number of titles, the only one that truly matters to him is that of Great Crown Hetman, the commander-in-chief of Polish forces. Indeed, his career has been a series of prominent military engagements on behalf of the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth. Most notably, Stanisław defended against the Swedish Deluge, in which Swedish and Russian forces invaded the Commonwealth.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_POTOCKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>As becomes quickly in his company, Stanisław has a tendency toward the pompous. His earned his nickname from his rather insufferable use of the Latin words 're vera,' which mean 'in fact.' He would be the first to tell you he does, in fact, appreciate the nickname.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_OSTROGSKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>No word better reveals the character of Konstanty Ostrogski than devotion. To the Polish-Lithuanian Union, certainly—his capable command under Polish King John I earned him the title of Grand Hetman, the first to do so. To his homeland, definitely—of Volhynian stock, he has never forgotten his roots, despite his many accomplishments.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_OSTROGSKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But most of all, to his faith--that of the Orthodox Church. He pours his personal fortune into the building of Orthodox churches and schools, and is himself quite devout. A strange matter for a very Catholic Poland and Lithuania.</Text>
		</Row>		
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_OSTROGSKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Yet Konstanty's very devotion so defines him that few can reasonably question his loyalty. Tatar, Muscovy, or Ottoman alike—the Grand Hetman will break their advances, besiege their castles, and destroy their forces in detail. He is the anvil that breaks the hammer.</Text>
		</Row>	
		<!-- Civilizations-->	
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_RADZIWILL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Lithuanian nobility has long been an integral to the Grand Duchy's fortunes. We can count upon these proud descendants to have Lithuanian concerns at heart—sometimes at the expense of their Polish allies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_RADZIWILL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>This is not to say Lithuanian nobility pays lip service to the defense of Polish-Lithuanian welfare—far from it. They field a substantial number of soldiers from the Grand Duchy, and are quick to make them available for the Polish Crown. However, family pride can mingle with ambition, leading them to believe that their own interests and Lithuanian interests are one and the same.</Text>
		</Row>	
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_POTOCKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The long-lived Polish nobility often have humble beginnings, but the ascent of Poland's star has allowed them to expand their holdings and prove their commitment to the Crown, time and time again. As they gain prestige, so do the families acquire their wealth.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_POTOCKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>More than a few Polish families have been elevated to the rank of magnates. Nobility bestowed can ruffle feathers—but covetous whispers notwithstanding, many such families have proven to be stalwart defenders of the Crown. Their approach in court is much as it is in war—look right into your opponent's eyes, give them no room to maneuver, and never back down.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_OSTROGSKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Volhynian families are a curiosity in the Polish-Lithuanian Union. Certainly, they are loyal, but some have refused to abandon their faith in the Orthodox Church in favor of Catholicism.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_OSTROGSKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Such is the strength of the Union and its codified views of religious tolerance. They may do as they will, as long as they advance the Union's causes. And advance it they have, charging straight at all who would oppose us, making available their soldiers, fodder, and treasure when needed for campaign. Their best and brightest have commanded tens of thousands of Union soldiers to great success.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_OSTROGSKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Let them worship in the way they so choose. If doing so serves to bolster their worldly faith in our cause, more the benefit for the Union.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- City-States-->			
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_GDANSK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>For good reason, Gdańsk desires little more than its independence. After 150 years of unwanted rule by the Teutonic Knights (who insist upon naming the city "Danzig"), Polish King Casimir IV extended the Great Privilege to Gdańsk, thereby reaffirming its autonomy and providing favorable trade relations with the Polish-Lithuanian Union. Excellent news for a Hanseatic League city, which now had privileged access to Union markets as well as other League cities throughout the Baltic.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_GDANSK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>All good news for Gdańsk—unless the Teutonic Knights get their way and return the city to their control.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VIENNA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Habsburgs have made a mess of Vienna. Once the most important city in the Holy Roman Empire, a series of ineffectual emperors has reduced this once-thriving center of culture and trade to a coach with horses mounted at opposite ends. Most recently, murderous political reprisals have left the city without an effective government.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VIENNA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Ottoman Turks watch and wait. Already they have annexed Hungary and established a Transylvanian vassal state. Their opportunity to lay siege to Vienna's walls may come soon enough. If Vienna falls, could the Polish-Lithuanian Union be next?</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRAGUE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the short time since Rudolf II moved his court to the merchant city of Prague, the eccentric Holy Roman Emperor has already transformed the city into a capital of learning and culture. Rudolf II is pleased to fund the work of renowned personages such as alchemist John Dee, astronomers Johannes Kepler and Tycho Brahe, and painter Giuseppe Arcimboldo.</Text>
		</Row>	
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRAGUE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>And yet, Rudolf II has strange ideas about launching a Crusade against the Ottoman Empire. To insist so in Prague—the seat of the Bohemian Reformation, two centuries prior—could severely strain the patience of Rudolf II's adopted citizenry.</Text>
		</Row>	
		<!--Units-->			
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_OTTOMAN_JANISSARY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Ottomans take the children of their conquered lands and turn them into soldiers they call janissaries. They teach the children how to speak, to think, and to fight. Then they send them to conquer more lands—to take more children. A janissary's fearsome reputation comes in part from the muskets, which may as well be portable artillery. They will be the tip of the Ottoman spear thrust toward Austria's soft belly.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_OTTOMAN_JANISSARY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Vienna is the gateway to Poland. It must not fall. We cannot allow our children to suffer the same fate.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_TEUTONIC_KNIGHT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Bandits take many forms—some ambush unwary travelers on the roads, others raid undefended villages. The very worst clad themselves in steel and claim their depredations are in God's name.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_TEUTONIC_KNIGHT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Teutonic Knights are such men. When a Polish king hired their "knightly order" to liberate Gdańsk, they did so—and then liberated the loyal Polish populace from their lives. They crusade against Lithuania, a newly Christian nation. The only article of faith they hold is coin.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_TEUTONIC_KNIGHT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>They claim to act for God? Then let us send them to God, where they can justify their claims in person.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_HORSE_ARCHER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>We continue to lose our people to the Tatars. They take so many as slaves—tens of thousands—it's as though each year they pluck entire towns from the map. Their horse archers launch lightning raids on our outlying settlements and return with their living spoils. Practically raised in the saddle, these Tatars see themselves as the successors to Ghengis Khan himself.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_HORSE_ARCHER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The horse archers pour through our borders, harass our patrols, and fill our militias with arrows before retreating to their khanate. The only walls they fear are those made of pikes.</Text>
		</Row>		
		<!--Great People-->			
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_STANISLAW_SAMOSTRZELNIK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A Polish monk who paints in the Renaissance style, Stanisław Samostrzelnik is known for his rich illuminations and colorful frescoes. His 'Portrait of Bishop Piotr Tomicki' is a brilliant contrast of gold and green.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_STANISLAW_SAMOSTRZELNIK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Not bad for someone who is colorblind.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_MARTIN_KOBER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The innovative artist Martin Kober has served as court painter for Stephen Báthory and Sigismund III of the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth, as well as Holy Roman Emperor Rudolf II. He specializes in portraiture, capturing the likeness of royalty so that future generations may know the regal splendor of the Crown.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_BARTOLOMMEO_BERRECCI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Italian architect Bartolommeo Berrecci brings the forefront of culture to Poland. We have Jan Łaski to thank for inviting Berrecci to our lands. Among his extensive work at Wawel Castle, the Sigismund Chapel stands out as a gorgeous piece of the Italian Renaissance—right in the middle of Kraków.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_ADAM_KOCHANSKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>There is no greater love for Adam Adamandy Kochański than mathematics—beyond God, of course, but that need not be said of a Jesuit. He is no slouch when it comes to practical mathematics, either, displaying his mechanical mastery with his revolutionary clock designs.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_KAZIMIERZ_SIEMIENOWICZ_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>For the Polish-Lithuanian general of artillery Kazimierz Siemienowicz, there is no problem on the battlefield that can't be solved with explosives. His thoughts on rocketry and pyrotechnics are outlandish, but transformative—much to the chagrin of the various guilds, who have little good to say about Siemienowicz's 'Artis Magnae Artilleriae.'</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_KRZYSZTOF_GRODZICKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A Polish general of artillery who trained amongst the Dutch, Krzysztof Grodzicki has spent much of his career training his cannons upon Swedes and Cossacks. His successful defense of Lviv against the Swedish Deluge prevented the city's capture—one of the few in that costly war.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_SEBASTIANO_MONTELUPI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Although Sebestiano Montelupi is Italian-born, more than half of his life has been spent in Poland. An accomplished merchant and banker, Montelupi was made royal postmaster general by Polish King Stephen Báthory. In this role he oversees deliveries between the major cities of the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_KONSTANTY_KORNIAKT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Greek Konstanty Korniakt came to Poland early in life, and has proven an able and capable merchant. His trade is international in nature, and he has even managed to secure routes with the Ottoman Empire. Sigismund II trusts Konstanty's acumen enough to collect royal tolls on the king's behalf.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_NICOLAUS_COPERNICUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Astronomer Nicolaus Copernicus is no stranger to controversy. Why, he claims the sun is the center of the universe, rather than the earth! His "heliocentric" theories would seem completely absurd, if not for the interest amongst the Catholic clergy—Pope Clement VII himself numbers amongst the theory's supporters.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_SENDIVOGIUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The alchemist Sendivogius recently came from the court of Rudolf II in Prague with some peculiar but promising ideas. He suggests the air we breathe is like a bowl of bigos, wherein only one of the ingredients is necessary to sustain life. This would be preposterous … if King Sigismund III wasn't so intrigued.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_PIOTR_SKARGA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Never one to mince words, the Jesuit Piotr Skarga has as much to say about the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth's politics as he does the Counter-Reformation against the spread of Protestantism. Whether you consider him a jar of honey or the fly that floats within, none can question his gift with words.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_JAN_KOCHANOWSKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Though Renaissance poet Jan Kochanowski spent years in the court of Sigismund II, he truly came to prominence when he left the capital to settle in a country estate. A recent tragedy—the death of his young daughter, Urszula—inspired him to compose a haunting series of elegies in her honor.</Text>
		</Row>
	</BaseGameText>
</GameData>
