<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Anton Strenger (Firaxis Games) -->
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<BaseGameText>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_INTRO_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
      <Text>City-states are smaller political entities that cannot win the game, but can greatly assist or impede a civilization's progress towards victory. There are a few options to deal with these city-states. You can befriend them and gain a number of important benefits, you can ignore them, or you can conquer them.</Text>
    </Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_TITLE">
			<Text>Historical Context</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AMSTERDAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Amstelredamme, the original name of the Dutch capital Amsterdam, was a small fishing village founded at some point in the 12th Century AD near a dam on the River Amstel. The inhabitants soon figured out they could make more coin from tolls over nearby bridges, and by digging peat out of the surrounding muck – inadvertently beginning the reclamation of the polder around the town. Amsterdam was granted city rights c. 1300 by its liege lord, the Count of Holland and Zeeland. When the Dutch revolted against Catholic Spain’s rule, economic and religious refugees (those insidious Protestants) from Spanish-controlled areas flooded into Amsterdam. Soon it was the largest city in the free Netherlands, and a thriving port as well.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AMSTERDAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>During the 17th Century, Amsterdam became the world’s wealthiest city … at least until the English beat the Netherlands in the Anglo-Dutch Wars and Napoleon overran the country during the Napoleonic Wars. But the city still dreams of its “Golden Age,” when merchants from Holland traded across the globe, sailing to North America, Africa, the Far East, and all about Europe. It was the center of great art, since artists tend to be drawn to easy money. In 1602, the Amsterdam offices of the Dutch East Indies Company became the world’s first stock exchange by trading in its own shares.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AMSTERDAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The city did eventually recover its position as a great port after the troubles of the 1800s. The Industrial Revolution arrived early in Amsterdam, as the Amsterdam-Rhine Canal and the North Sea Canal dramatically improved commerce and an early train station brought goods from central Europe to its docks. Despite the effects of the Second World War (Holland managed to avoid the First), Amsterdam remains one of the world’s great commercial centers, home to some 1.5 million people (metropolitan area).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BRUSSELS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Brussels was founded along the banks of the Senne River in 979 AD when Charles of Lorraine constructed the first fortifications around a small Catholic chapel and town. The city lay low along the river and was often flooded, giving it its Dutch name Broeksel, or, “home in the marsh.” The citizens have been trying to live that down for centuries, focusing on making it an industrial center in the “new Europe.” Extensive city walls, constructed and expanded during the 11th to 14th centuries, allowed a period of growth, expansion, and relative security uncommon for the time.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BRUSSELS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>For some two hundred years, the city passed from one ruler to another … more or less peacefully. That ended abruptly in 1695 when Louis XIV of France sent troops to Brussels and bombarded the city with artillery, destroying the Grand Place and nearly a third of the city in the attack. This, forcefully, brought “Frenchification” to Belgium, at least in terms of culture.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BRUSSELS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>So, inevitably, in 1830 the southern French-speaking provinces of the then Kingdom of the Netherlands separated from the Dutch-speaking provinces in the “Belgian Revolution,” the conflict taking place for the most part in Brussels. Following Belgian independence, the new king Leopold I began destroying the old city walls to make way for new construction and more modern buildings for his capital. By now the Senne, once the life-blood of the city, was an open sewer and so between 1867 and 1871 was covered over.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BRUSSELS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Brussels escaped the two world wars relatively unscathed largely due to its lack of strategic significance, the inattention of its German occupiers, and the general passivity of its inhabitants. Perhaps it is this – or the fact it is a major transportation hub – which made the city a modern-day center for international commerce and the de facto capital of the European Union and the headquarters of NATO.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BUENOS_AIRES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A seductive city, which rambles north to south along the Río de la Plata, Buenos Aires has been the gateway to Argentina since inception. Porteños, as the multinational citizens of Buenos Aires term themselves, possess an elaborate and rich cultural identity, drawing on Spanish, Portuguese, Italian, German, Irish, Polish, Jewish as well as native influences; the city has often been referred to as the “Paris of South America.” Its lifestyle and architecture is more distinctly European than that of any other city in the southern hemisphere. Its physical layout is a mosaic as varied as its people, its cuisine, and its music. Buenos Aires is, not surprisingly, the most visited city in South America (ahead of even Rio de Janeiro).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BUENOS_AIRES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The city was founded as Ciudad de Nuestra Señora Santa María del Buen Ayre (“City of Our Lady Saint Mary of the Fair Winds”) in 1536 AD by a Spanish expedition. When Argentina became independent in 1816, the cosmopolitan city became its capital. In the decades between 1880 and 1940, Buenos Aires was a haven for those seeking refuge from political, religious, ideological, and artistic persecution in countries across Europe. From hungry Irish to devout Jews to Tsarist survivors, each wave of immigrants brought their traditions and talents to add to the stew, making the city the cultural rival of any world capital.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BUENOS_AIRES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Along with all the art and culture, Buenos Aires is a manufacturing center of the first order, with heavy industry composing 16% of the city’s economy. Factories, mostly concentrated in the southern part of the urban sprawl, produce textiles, chemicals, automobiles, beverages, and petroleum products. It also serves as the center for export of Argentina’s rich agricultural output: meat, dairy, tobacco, grain and wool. Buenos Aires isn’t just about the tango any longer.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_CARTHAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Until the Roman Publius Scipio Africanus plowed it under and salted the earth (so the legend goes) to conclude the Third Punic War, Carthage was one of the great cities of antiquity. Its birth beside the Gulf of Tunis is just as legendary, having been at the hands of its fabled first queen Dido. More prosaically, it actually grew from a Phoenician colony founded sometime during the first millennium BC.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_CARTHAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Ideally situated along the north coast of Africa, Carthage became an increasingly important center of trade in the Mediterranean through the next few centuries. However, this success was not without consequences, as Carthage eventually drew the ire of both Greece and Rome, and the ensuing conflicts with these intimidating rivals became ever more legendary.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_CARTHAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tension with Greece over control of the cities of Sicily, and the intertwining trade routes, led to a series of conflicts – the Sicilian Wars. Blessed with some of the greatest generals of the time, the likes of Hamilcar Mago and his grandson Hannibal Mago, by the 3rd Century BC Carthage established complete domination over the island. During these ongoing conflicts, Rome moved to assert its power over the whole of Italy. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_CARTHAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Not long after the conclusion of the Pyrrhic War, continued pressure from expanding Rome drew the ire of Carthage, as the two competitors fought for control of territory and trade. A series of escalating clashes now known as the Punic Wars erupted in 264 BC, when both powers became entangled in a local squabble over control of the Sicilian city Messina. Enduring thanks primarily to the brilliant leadership of Hannibal and able others until 146 BC, beleaguered Carthage was eventually forced to surrender. The city itself was burned to the ground and much of the remaining population slaughtered, the survivors sold into slavery.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_GENEVA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Originally settled on a hill overlooking a nice lake by a bunch of Paleolithic nomads, by around 500 BC Geneva became a Celtic fortified town, before it was taken by the Romans in 121 BC. Ownership of the city continued to slip between the warring neighboring states, until landing in the hands of the Germans in 1033 AD. By this time Geneva had become an important ecclesiastical seat, with the bishop of the city a direct vassal of the Holy Roman Emperor as a territorially vested prince.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_GENEVA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Since separation of church and state wasn’t too precise, power in Geneva was contested between the Savoy dukes and the Catholic popes for the next five centuries. When the last ruling bishop fled the city in 1533, the citizens of Geneva made a risky move in an attempt to rid themselves of both the Catholics and the Savoyards – the city allied itself with the Protestant state of Bern and declared Geneva a Protestant sovereignty in 1536. It remained a stronghold of Protestant faith for years to come, although some of the population had reverted to Catholicism by the early 17th Century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_GENEVA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Over time, Geneva became a center for scientific learning and research. In 1559 John Calvin founded the Geneva Academy (later University of Geneva) as a “humanist” seminary. In short order, various scientists arrived and discovered interesting things – the likes of pioneering geologist Jean-Andre Deluc, physicist Firmin Abauzit, and naturalist Francois Huber. In 1909, the university there awarded Albert Einstein the first of his honorary doctorates. More recently, Geneva has been home to Werner Arber (Nobel Prize in Medicine 1978) and Felix Bloch, the first director of CERN, which is based in a northwest suburb of the city. There’s even the Musée d’Histoire des Sciences in Geneva to commemorate all this scientific progress oozing from the city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_HATTUSA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once the capital of the mighty Hittite Empire, Hattusa is now just some sunbaked ruins – although it was added to the UNESCO list of World Heritage sites. Sometime before 2000 BC, the Hatti decided to build on the site of a prehistoric abandoned settlement on the ridge of Buyukkale, which didn’t have much to recommend it save its defensibility. In the 19th and 18th centuries BC merchants from Assyria established a trading post in the town, and introduced cuneiform writing. A century later, King Anitta destroyed the town and then cursed it for good measure, inscribing on a rock: “Whoever after me becomes king resettles Hattusas, let the Stormgod of the Sky smite him.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_HATTUSA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Only a generation later, his curse was ignored, as a Hittite king chose the spot for his new palace and capital. This marked the beginning of a line of Hittite “great kings,” 27 of whom are still known by name. Hattusa became the seat of learning, religion and politics for the empire; at its peak the city covered 1.8 square kilometers, surrounded by massive walls built during the reign of Suppiluliuma, c. 1333 BC. In the southern sector lay four great stone-built temples surrounded by mud-brick homes and shops. Some 40 to 50 thousand people dwelt in Hattusa at the time.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_HATTUSA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Although it is not known for certain, Hattusa was likely the site of most of the many technological advances made by the Hittites. They were the first known to have worked with iron, forging better weapons and tools. The Hittites were the first to develop two-horse chariots, and made use of iron-rimmed wheels (rather better for those rocky roads). The farmers improved irrigation, rotated crops and invented a number of agricultural tools. But in the end, all this didn’t help much; evidence indicates the city was destroyed, together with the whole Hittite Empire, sometime around 1200 BC.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_HONG_KONG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A city-state in its truest form for 99 years, Hong Kong (meaning “Fragrant Harbor”) is a great port on the Chinese coast. Now home to more than seven million residents, the island of Hong Kong and its mainland territory were once the site of numerous small settlements, including those constructed by foreign merchants. In fact, trade and commerce are the sole reason Hong Kong exists.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_HONG_KONG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>During the Jin dynasty, the village on the island evolved into a regional trading center thanks to its sheltered harbor and nearby salt production. During the 300-year Tang dynasty, Hong Kong flourished as an international port; the Tuen Mun district became a major naval base. In 1513 AD the Portuguese Jorge Álvares arrived, opening trade with Europe. But under the Ming dynasty Haijin edict (closed-door policy), the city began to fade. Until the British took a (heavy) hand.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_HONG_KONG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>During the reign of the Chinese Qing dynasty in the 19th Century, relations with England degenerated amidst growing concern over the importation of Indian opium into China. Britain had hoped to offset its increasingly expensive tea trade from China by exporting ever greater amounts of opium from India into China. However, the Qing rulers objected, and attempted to seize incoming opium shipments, thus inciting the Opium Wars in 1839.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_HONG_KONG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>After many years of conflict, the Treaty of Nanking provided the United Kingdom with various spoils, including a 99-year lease on Hong Kong. Prospering as a British colony for a century, Hong Kong was finally returned to China in 1997, after a peaceful transfer of power. Despite the avowed communism of the People's Republic, Hong Kong maintains a semi-autonomous system of government that supports free trade, and the city remains one of civilization’s financial hubs. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_JAKARTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Serving as the capital of Indonesia, Jakarta is both the largest and richest city in the Southeast Asian country. Since the first settlements in the area of Jakarta were laid by Hindu pilgrims in the 4th Century AD, the city has been known by many names, and controlled by an equally large number of would-be empires. For nearly 1000 years, Jakarta was part of the Kingdom of Sunda, which ruled a number of surrounding territories along the Indian Ocean. When meandering Portuguese explorers showed up in the islands in the 16th Century, the lucrative spice trade was quickly established with Jakarta being the primary port.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_JAKARTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Kingdom of Sunda eventually fell to the Muslim Sultanate of Fatahillah, who also expelled the Portuguese from the region. However, trade routes were reestablished soon after with the arrival of Dutch and English traders, including the influential English East India Company. After repeated conflicts between the two colonial powers vying for trade dominance, the Dutch and their own East India Company (shockingly) emerged victorious. The Dutch East India Company remained the dominant power in the Spice Islands until its eventual dissolution in 1800, when the Dutch formally declared the formation of the Dutch East Indies, their very own colony.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_JAKARTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In 1950, the efforts of Indonesian nationalists succeeded in gaining full independence for Indonesia, with Jakarta established as its capital. Although the city and its residents (some 9.58 million of them in 2010) have often been enveloped in political unrest and instability, the economy of Jakarta continues to grow. These days Jakarta’s wealth depends primarily on the money-service sectors: banking, financial investing, stock and commodities trading, real estate, and the like. Although export of spices and other luxuries continues to be important, the almighty rupiah has come to be the primary focus.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_JERUSALEM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>With portions of the old town having been constructed over 6000 years ago, Jerusalem is one of the most ancient still-standing cities in the world. Not without a lot of luck, for throughout its tumultuous history, Jerusalem has come under assault numerous times, as grasping empires and religious warriors alike have killed each other by the thousands to wrest control of the city from one another.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_JERUSALEM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The oldest neighborhoods in Jerusalem, the “City of David,” are said to have been built by the legendary king sometime during the first millennium BC. Over the centuries that followed, immigrants and refugees living under a number of kings, priests, and prophets worked to expand the city. By the time the Islamic caliphates rose to power in the 7th Century AD and seized it in the name of Allah in 638, Jerusalem had already been overrun by the Macedonian, Roman, and Byzantine empires.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_JERUSALEM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Not content with the city's current leadership, in 1095 Pope Urban II called upon Christian knights to liberate Jerusalem with the sword. What followed was two hundred years of bloodshed. In the end the Arabs ruled the city still (although they lost it for a time). They in turn were followed by the Ottomans, British and Jordanians.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_JERUSALEM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>The past century has arguably been the most controversial in Jerusalem’s sad history, after the establishment of the Jewish state of Israel and its subsequent annexation of the whole of the city following the Six-Day War in 1967.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KABUL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>To his fellow Afghans, Abed Rahmani wrote, “Be united like a rain; be powerful like an ocean.” The people of Kabul, largest city in Afghanistan, having weathered repeated imperial invasions to retain their distinctive culture and identity, can be said to have done that. Wedged in a valley in the Hindu Kush, Kabul occupies a strategic location on the route between south and central Asia, controlling the approaches to the Khyber Pass. And since it has centuries of experience resisting invaders, it has produced fierce warriors for all that time. When not fighting outsiders, the hill tribes happily fought each other.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KABUL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Kabul is over 3500 years old, but rarely free. The Hindu Rigveda praised it as the ideal city, a “vision of paradise set in the mountains.” Late in the Achaemenid Era, the city became a center for Zoroastrianism. Numerous kingdoms and empires held Kabul over the next dozen centuries. In 1504 AD the city was taken by Babur, who made it his headquarters as he carved out the Mughal Empire. Babur so loved the city he lived in for two decades that his tomb carried an inscription in Persian reading: “If there is a paradise on earth, this is it, this is it.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KABUL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The Afghans would spend most of the 1800s fighting the British off. Free at last when the 20th Century dawned, Kabul experienced a renaissance that spanned 60 years. During the rule of the liberal Mohammed Zahir Shah, European investments were made in modern communication and transportation … and weaponry. A ten-year Soviet occupation ended in civil war after the Russians withdrew in 1989, resulting in the repressive Taliban-controlled Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan. In 2001 an American-led coalition established a new democratic government.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KANDY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Records – more-or-less historical – indicate that the Sri Lankan town of Kandy was established by the monarch Vikramabahu III of Gampola and originally named Senkadagalapura near the Watapuluwa (a lot of letters for such a small place). Around 1400 AD, Kandy became an independent kingdom under the rule of Sena Sammatha Wickramabahu of the royal Kotte family. The Kandyan Kingdom remained independent, and fairly prosperous and secure, until the British invaded. In the Second Kandyan War, British forces met no resistance and captured the city in February 1815.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KANDY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Part of this may have been due to the inhabitants’ reluctance to see the city leveled, for it was home to several faiths – Theravada Buddhism, Hinduism, Islam, and even Christianity – and various holy shrines. For instance, the Buddhist Temple of the Sacred Tooth, built in 1595, lay within the royal palace. The Buddhist community observed – and still does – the Poya Days once a month religiously. The Hindus (roughly 13%) and Muslims (about 10%) kept their own celebrations and holy days just as fervently. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KANDY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Under the European leadership, Ceylon (as it was known) underwent rapid and drastic modernization. Save for a couple of rebellions – the Uva in 1818 and Matale in 1848 – Kandy was just a quiet corner of the British Empire. During the Second World War, it did serve as the home of the Allied South East Asia Command, but it was never threatened. The Donoughmore reforms in the 1930s, among them enforced religious tolerance, led eventually to Sri Lanka gaining independent Dominion status in 1948. Since then, the island has been troubled by political infighting, several assassinations, an intermittent insurgency, and a civil war (1983-2009). </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KUMASI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>There is archeological evidence that there has been a settlement (of some primitive sort) at Kumasi since the Neolithic period.  But the town wasn't commonly known until 1695 AD when it became the center of the Ashanti Confederation under Osei Tutu. With the 1701 victory over the Denkyira tribes, Kumasi became the cultural as well as the political center of the Ashanti ethnic group. Located astride two Saharan trade routes, it also became quite wealthy … and the discovery of gold in the kingdom didn’t hurt.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KUMASI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>No doubt the latter contributed to the legend that the priest and lawgiver Ohomfo Anokye received the Golden Stool from heaven, the embodiment of the spirit of the Ashanti peoples – past, present and future. Except, of course, the slaves; slavery was a historical tradition among the Ashanti, and were often taken in warfare or by raiding nearby tribes. Slaves were occasionally sacrificed, and were expected to follow their masters into the afterlife (usually with a little help). But on the positive side, Ashanti slaves could own other slaves and even request a transfer of ownership if they deemed themselves abused.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KUMASI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Kumasi was doing quite well, an “artistic” metropolis by all accounts, until the Anglo-Ashanti Wars … five of them between 1824 and 1901. The conflict was triggered by several coastal kingdoms in Ghana threatened by Ashanti expansion which called upon the British for protection; British greed for gold just may have been a factor also. Whatever the reasons, near the end of the Third Anglo-Ashanti War much of Kumasi, including the palace, was destroyed by British forces after their victories at the hard-fought battles of Amoaful and Ordashu. Although two more wars were left, Kumasi never regained its prominence and stature.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KUMASI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>It did, however remain the cultural center of the Ashanti; ceremonial control of Kumasi was restored to the Ashanti in 1926. In 1935 the Ashanti Autonomous Region was established in the British territory, with Kumasi as its capital.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_LA_VENTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When the Spanish explorers stumbled over the ruins of ancient Olmec (the “mother-culture” of Mesoamerica) cities, they gave them Spanish names, as they did at La Venta. The original Olmec city, “San Lorenzo,” was abandoned c. 900 BC and La Venta rose to prominence in the region. La Venta itself would be abandoned c. 400 BC, but in the intervening five centuries it was the heart of Olmec culture, art and religion. Unlike most Mesoamerican cities, there was little stone nearby, so the settlement was mostly built of clay and fill dirt.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_LA_VENTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Located on a two-square-mile island in the midst of a coastal swamp overlooking the outlet of the Rio Palma, La Venta was hardly a pleasant spot. But it was holy, with some spectacular displays of engineering and wealth. The Great Pyramid there was, at the time, the largest structure in the Americas; even after 2500 years of erosion, it rises 34 meters above the flat island.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_LA_VENTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Numerous monuments and sculptures adorn the complex, with burial tombs and altars having also been discovered. Of the iconic "Colossal Heads" carved by the Olmec, La Venta features four of the most famous. Weighing several tons each, archeologists can only theorize as to how the Olmec managed to acquire the stone for these massive carvings.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_LA_VENTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>And wealth … opulent “offerings” have been found through the site by archeologists mucking about: 1000 tons of polished serpentine blocks, extensive mosaics, and 48 deposits of jade, pottery, figurines and hematite mirrors. And the skeletal remains of slaves, lots of them, along with devices that appear to be for bloodletting (ceremonial spikes and such), leading to speculation concerning human sacrifice for religious purposes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_LA_VENTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>But it's unlikely history will ever know for certain, for much of La Venta has been leveled in the name of progress. For instance, the entire southern end of the island is covered with a petroleum refinery. And in 2009 a number of the heads were damaged by a group attempting to perform a supposed pre-Columbian religious ritual.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_LISBON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As one of the oldest cities in the world, Portugal's capital, Lisbon, has long been a prized trade hub on the Iberian Peninsula. Although Lisbon had existed in one form or another for a thousand years, the city became an integral part of the Roman trade network following their victory over Carthage during the Punic Wars. In August 711 AD, Moslem Berber forces took the city; the Moors were fairly liberal rulers, allowing all sorts of Moslems, Jews, and even Christians to continue to practice their faith … for a hefty tax. And it remained an active port, center of Moorish trade with north European nations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_LISBON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But the Reconquista saw crusader knights, led by Alfonso (later, the First as King of Portugal) took the city and promptly got rid of all the non-believers. Nonetheless, despite all the intolerance and autos-da-fé, Lisbon continually expanded as its port became the point of departure for Portuguese vessels sailing throughout the world. During the Age of Discovery in the 15th Century, many notable Portuguese explorers set out from Lisbon, including Vasco da Gama, the first to sail from Europe to India.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_LISBON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In 1755, one of the deadliest earthquakes in recorded history, the Great Lisbon Earthquake, rattled the Iberian Peninsula, nearly destroying all of Lisbon. Modern historians estimate that up to 100,000 people may have been killed as a result of the quake, and extensive reconstruction efforts were required to rebuild the crumbling city. Despite all the turmoil of various European wars (notably the Napoleonic one when the royal family fled to Brazil), Lisbon managed to remain more-or-less intact.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_LISBON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>In the present day, Lisbon is home to more than 500,000 residents and still serves as one of Europe's leading centers of commerce and trade. Lisbon is also a popular tourist destination, as the city features many examples of historic architecture, along with several fine museums and cultural festivals.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MOHENJO_DARO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Built sometime around 2500 BC, Mohenjo-daro was one of the largest of the Harappan civilization’s settlements, center of a thriving culture that spanned northern India and Pakistan. While the Egyptians were building pyramids for their pharaohs and the Minoans were leaping over bulls for sport, the 40,000 (or so) citizens of Mohenjo-daro were building striking structures of fired and mortared brick: public baths, a central market with a public well, spacious homes, a great granary (with air ducts to dry the grain), the “Pillared Hall” for assemblies, and the “College Hall” (78 rooms thought to have been a residence for priests).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MOHENJO_DARO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Archaeologists, as well as thieves, have found all sorts of marvellous art and artifacts in their excavating of Mohenjo-daro: sculptures of seated and standing figures, copper tools, official seals, gold and jasper jewelry, balance-scales, children’s toys, weights for commerce, carved furnishings. Among the most notable pieces are the bronze “Dancing Girl,” the Pashupati seal, and a seven-strand necklace estimated to be 4500 years old. The city must have been a comfortable place to live.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MOHENJO_DARO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>And relatively peaceful. The city had no outer walls, although there were guard towers to the east and some defensive works to the south. Although it appears that no human threats upset the tranquility, angry gods in the form of nature certainly did. Mohenjo-daro was destroyed at least seven times, and rebuilt – the new directly on top of the old. Seems flooding of the Indus river periodically drowned all that culture. But each time it arose to again become the most sophisticated city of the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MOHENJO_DARO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>But all good things come to an end eventually. When the Harappan civilization went into a sudden – and as yet unexplained, although historians have lots of theories – decline around 1900 BC, Mohenjo-daro was gradually abandoned. It was lost until 1920 AD, when a visiting Indian historian, Rakhaldas Banerji, found an old flint scrapper there.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRESLAV_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Until it was fortified in the early 9th Century AD, Preslav was just a sleepy little Slavic settlement. But by the time of the coronation of Boris I, with his capital in nearby Pliska, it was an important strategic center and the seat of the Bulgar 'Ichirgu-boil,' commander of the capital’s garrison and de facto head of the kingdom’s military. The town also became a religious center when the Bulgars converted to Christianity in 864 and built a number of churches there.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRESLAV_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But Preslav’s primary business was war. Once a pagan revolt was finally defeated in 892 and Boris appointed Simeon I as his successor, the decision was made to move the capital from Pliska to the much-more Christian Preslav. For the next 80 years, not only did the new capital become the political and military center of Bulgaria, but its cultural, artistic, and religious center as well. The walls were expanded and reinforced, and its barracks became the training ground for Bulgar delusions of grandeur.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRESLAV_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Until, that is, the Bulgars were defeated by the Kievan prince Sviatoslav Igorevich and Preslav occupied. The ensuing war between Byzantium and Kiev left the city ravaged and nigh razed by the liberating Byzantine armies. A lesson in being beware of one’s allies. The Byzantines carried off the Bulgarian treasury, the royal jewels and regalia, and most of the royal library.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRESLAV_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Preslav recovered some of its military importance in the first decades of the “Second Bulgarian Empire,” c. 1185. Indeed, it was – along with the fortress at Tarnovgrad – one of the joint seats of the kingdom under the co-rulers. But the strategic defensive position of Tarnovgrad proved better able to withstand outside threats. The Tartar raids of the 1270s drove off what citizens in Preslav survived; they built a new village of the same name a couple miles away, plundering the once-mighty walls for building materials.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NAN_MADOL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Most archaeologists and historians do not believe that the ruins of the abandoned city of Nan Madol, lying adjacent to the eastern shore of the island of Pohnpei in Micronesia, are a remnant of the lost continent of Mu. The city was instead constructed in a lagoon and consisted of about 100 small artificial islets built on stone and coral fill platforms separated by tidal canals. Instead of being left over from the prehistoric sinking of a continent, best guess is that construction of these islets started c. 8th Century AD, and that the construction of the megalithic structures upon these took place in the 12th and 13th centuries. All so the elite castes of the Sandeleur dynasty didn’t have to mix with the commoners.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NAN_MADOL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The original name for the lagoon-city was Soun Nan-leng (“Reef of Heaven”), and European explorers dubbed it the “Venice of the Pacific.” Most of the named islets were residential, homes for chieftains and priests … although some served special needs: food preparation, coconut oil production on Peinering, canoe construction on Dapahu. The mortuary “neighborhood” includes some 58 islets, covered with graves. Nan Madol was the political, religious and cultural seat of power for the Sandeleur, who had succeeded in uniting the clans (which totaled around 25 thousand people) on Pohnpei and Temwen islands. Shortly thereafter the ruler forced the tribal chieftains to move to the new city where he could keep an eye on them.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NAN_MADOL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>At its peak, the population of Nan Madol was perhaps about 1000. Since there are no sources of food or fresh water on the islets, everything had to be rowed over from Pohnpei. According to legend, the stones used for all the buildings and tombs were flown to the island by twin sorcerers Olisihpa and Olosohpa, who founded the Sandeleur. Whatever the facts of its creation, by the time the Europeans arrived in the early 1800s, Nan Madol had been abandoned, likely around 1450 when the Sandeleur collapsed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SEOUL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>While the area around Seoul has been settled since the Paleolithic Age, the city wasn’t officially founded until 18 BC when the kingdom of Baekje built its capital Wiryeseong on the site. In time, Baekje developed from a minor state into one of the Three Kingdoms of Korea, a group of countries which dominated the peninsula for most of the first millennium AD. Over time, Seoul grew into a formidable city with great political, cultural and commercial significance.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SEOUL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Eventually the Three Kingdoms were consolidated under one rule, and in 1394 AD the capital of this new entity was moved to Seoul. Large walls were built around the city, as much to keep out thieves as well as bears and other large, scary animals … such as those annoying barbarians. Eventually, Seoul opened its gates to the influx of westerners arriving in the Far East during the late 1800s, and the city quickly modernized. In fact, Seoul was the first Asian city to have electricity, running water, and the telephone.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SEOUL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>But this isn’t surprising, since Seoul has been the center of technological advances for centuries. The civil minister Choe Yun-ui invented moveable metal type there in 1234 AD to print 50 copies of the Sangjeong yemun … long before Gutenberg stumbled onto the same idea. The Joseon dynasty saw the invention of the water clock, the sight glass, the udometer and lots of other clever gadgets. In 1442, the apex of astronomical advances was reached with the Chiljeongsan, a compilation of computations on the courses of the seven heavenly objects. Then there’s the world’s first ballistic vest invented in the 1860s, a boon to the Korean army.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SEOUL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>With the likes of Samsung and LG Corporation and others headquartered in the city, scientific tinkering hasn’t slowed much since. In 2008 South Korea had the fifth highest R&amp;D expenditure in the world, much of that centered in Seoul. In electronics, computers, robotics, renewable energy and many other fields, Seoul is the cutting-edge for ever more discoveries.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_STOCKHOLM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The earliest written documentation of Stockholm dates back to 1252 AD and describes the city as an iron trading town, but in some Norse sagas it is claimed to be the lost city of Agnafit (where legendary King Ange was hanged by his captive bride Skjalf). Another tale states that the city was founded by the Swedesman Birger Jarl to protect the fledgling country from invading navies. Regardless of whichever (if either) is correct, the city quickly grew into a center for commerce, mining, and fishing … eventually joining the Hanseatic League.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_STOCKHOLM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In the 15th Century, a national independence movement began to form in Stockholm as the people of Sweden yearned to overthrow their Danish rulers. The Revolution did not go well, unfortunately, and in 1520 the Danish King Christian II entered the city and incited the Stockholm Bloodbath, a massacre of most of the Swedish opposition forces. Further uprisings across the country in the coming years were more successful and broke up the Kalmar Union (the pleasant name for Danish control of Scandinavia), and Sweden finally gained its independence. The first king of Sweden, Gustav Vasa, was crowned in 1523, and the population of Stockholm began to boom. Within a hundred years, the citizenry increased six-fold.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_STOCKHOLM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>During the latter half of the 20th century Stockholm became one of the great seats of learning in Europe. The Military Academy Karlberg, one of the world’s oldest, was founded in 1792; the Karolinska Institutet, one of Europe’s most prestigious medical schools, in 1811; the Royal Institute of Technology in 1827. But oldest of all is the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences, home of the Nobel Prizes, which was founded by famed naturalist Carl Linnaeus in 1739. The city has continued to move away from its roots of fishing, mining, and shipping and move towards high-tech research, modern manufacturing, and giving away millions to otherwise obscure scientists.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_TORONTO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The most populous city (2.6 million or so in 2011) in Canada, Toronto began as a minor French trading post in 1750 AD after the Iroquois had abandoned the region at the end of the Beaver Wars. But it must not have been a very good location, for the French abandoned it themselves in 1759. The Mississaugas inherited the area by default, but during that American colonial uprising an influx of British Loyalists arrived in the uncivilized frontier north of Lake Ontario. Thus, in 1787 the British negotiated the “Toronto Purchase” with the Mississaugas, securing over a quarter-million acres.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_TORONTO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The British built Fort York at the entrance of Toronto’s harbor, just in time for it to be captured and destroyed by American forces during the war of 1812. (Little known fact: the sacking of York was a primary motivation for the burning of Washington by British troops.) After that unpleasantness – and the unsuccessful Upper Canada Rebellion led by Toronto’s William Mackenzie in 1837 – Toronto entered an age of growth, improvement and industrialization. The Grand Trunk and Northern railways joined forces to build Union Station; meanwhile, steamers and schooners on Lake Ontario made Toronto a major gateway to the resources of the interior of the continent.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_TORONTO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>All this contributed to Toronto becoming an industrial hub. For instance, a number of distilleries began operations, making the city the largest producer of alcohol in North America; the Gooderham &amp; Worts distillery became the world’s largest whiskey factory in the world by the mid-1860s. The Great Fire of 1904 destroyed much of the downtown, but the area was rebuilt in a more genteel manner, and much of the industry was relocated to the suburbs. Factories and warehouses clustered around the rail yards and the port. Besides spirits, Toronto now produces automobiles, iron and steel, chemicals, paper, and packaged foods.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VALLETTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Valletta, located in the Republic of Malta, was founded in 1566 AD by Jean Parisot de la Valette, the 49th Grandmaster of the Sovereign Military Hospitaller Order of Saint John of Jerusalem of Rhodes and of Malta. This after the Knights Hospitaller had withstood a siege and invasion of the island by the Ottoman Empire a year earlier. (Malta had been given in perpetuity to the order by Charles V of Spain in 1530 to serve as a bulwark against the Ottoman tide.)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VALLETTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>To build and fortify the new city and the island, Valette requested help from the kings and princes of Christendom. And it was forthcoming … obviously their thinking was that it was better for a bunch of militant zealots to face the oncoming Moslems than their own troops and ships. Pope Pius V sent his own military architect to design the fortifications, and Philip II of Spain gave ships and weapons. Others donated large sums of money to sponsor churches and barracks and port facilities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VALLETTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The town, with its fine harbor and strategic location, was to weather centuries of warfare, even unto the Second World War. The Knights assumed the duties of policing the Mediterranean shipping lanes between Christian Europe and the Levant, fighting the Barbary corsairs and other pirates. They also set about freeing Christian slaves from the Moslems, mostly by raiding Ottoman shipping themselves. But the rise of Genoa, Venice and Pisa, and later the Protestant Reformation, eroded much of Valletta’s financial support.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VALLETTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Thus, in 1798 when Napoleon captured Malta while en route to invade Egypt, only Naples and the British seemed much concerned. A couple of years later the Maltese rose in rebellion against the French garrison; the victorious rebel leaders presented the island to the British, requesting that it be made a dominion of the empire. The 1814 Treaty of Paris confirmed British control, under whose thumb it remained until independence in 1964.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VILNIUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Lying at the junction of two navigable rivers, the Vilnia and the Neris, some 194 miles from the Baltic, Vilnius was settled as a trading post deep in the woodlands of Lithuania. The town is first mentioned in written records in 1323 AD, when German Jews were invited to relocate to the capital of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania by Duke Gediminas, who promised religious tolerance and commercial opportunities. Over the following decades under the ambitious duke and his sons, the duchy expanded until it encompassed most of modern Lithuania, Belarus, the Ukraine, Transnistria, and portions of Poland and northern Russia. With the Union of Lublin in 1569, the city became an important mercantile center in the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VILNIUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>During this period, Vilnius changed dramatically from a backwater post to a cultural and political center. Migrants were welcomed by the authorities, and thousands of Slavs, Germans, and Jews moved into the booming city. In 1579, King Stefan Báthory founded the institution that would evolve into the 'Vilniaus universitetas,' the oldest university in the Baltic States, which quickly became one of the most important scientific and cultural centers in Europe. Artistic and craft guilds of various types were established, and the city served as the primary center for trade between Scandinavia and the interior of Poland and northern Russia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VILNIUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>All this ready coin meant that the inhabitants – when they weren’t fighting the Poles, Swedes, Russians, or Germans – could live the good life. Although labelled a “Baroque” city, Vilnius boosts a blend of architectural styles – Gothic, Renaissance, Neo-Classical, and so forth – in its well-preserved and unique Old Town (placed on the UNESCO World Heritage List in 1994). Museums and monuments of all sorts dot the city. The Gediminas Tower, Cathedral Square, and stately Palace of the Grand Dukes, the House of the Signatories and national museums and libraries have managed to survive occupation by many enemies … and since independence in 1990, again form the heart of Lithuania.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_YEREVAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>There is evidence of human habitation near the capital of Armenia dating from prehistory. Worked stone tools have been taken from Yerevan cave, dated from tens of thousands of years ago. The Shengavit site in Yerevan was settled around about 3200 BCE, making it one of best-known walled Bronze Age archeological sites in the world. The city of Yerevan itself is almost modern by contrast, originally founded on the site of a fortification called “Erebuni” over 2,500 years ago.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_YEREVAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Armenia was the first nation to adopt Christianity as its religion, early in the 4th century. Yerevan also became famous for its leather working (a leather shoe over 5,000 years old is on display in the History Museum of Armenia). Situated at the crossroads of various empires of Asia and the Near East, it has been ruled by Medes, Romans, Byzantines, Arabs, Persians, the Ottomans, and Russians. The rise and fall of these cultures is still reflected in the surviving architecture and culture of the city.</Text>		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_YEREVAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Ancient churches dot Yerevan. The tiny Katoghike Church contrasts with the magnificent Cathedral of Saint Gregory the Illuminator, the largest Armenian Apostolic Church in the world. Some, however, have been lost, such as the 5th century Saint Paul and Peter Church (though fragments remain in history museums.) The Blue Mosque was closed for a few decades and used as the Museum of the City of Yerevan, but has since been restored and used as a house of worship again.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_YEREVAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Yerevan is also home to Yerevan Chess House. Chess and its predecessors have been played in Armenia since at least the 9th century, and possibly as early as the 6th, and today Armenians continue to represent their country at the highest levels of competition.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ZANZIBAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The island of Zanzibar, part of the so-called “Spice Islands,” has been home to humans for about 20 thousand years after Stone Age savages managed to find their way to it from Africa. Not surprisingly, not much was known about Zanzibar until around the death of Muhammed in 632 AD. But its location made it a prime spot for the trade routes of the Arabs, Indians, and Persians; traders and others from all three migrated to Zanzibar. The island also made a convenient base for slave raids along the coast of east Africa, another major money-maker.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ZANZIBAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Da Gama’s visit in 1498 intrigued folks back home; in 1503 or so, Zanzibar became part of the Portuguese Empire when a small military expedition landed, demanded and received tribute from the local sultan in exchange for peace. But the Portuguese were rather lax landlords, for when a British ship stopped by in 1591 the captain found no Portuguese fort or garrison, only a feitoria.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ZANZIBAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>No doubt part of the Portuguese interest in keeping things peaceful was the cultivation of spices on the islands: cloves, vanilla, cinnamon, and nutmeg among others less valued. Slaves worked the great plantations that sprang up across the colony. Meanwhile, all sorts of trading ships were sailing in and out of the harbors, both European and Asian. The sultans continued to rule from Stone Town (the heart of what is now Zanzibar City) for the next two centuries, so long as the Portuguese got their cut.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ZANZIBAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>But this semi-autonomy came to an end when the British got the wind up over the Portuguese and Arab slave trade. After several decades of negotiations, threats and occasional violence, the Anglo-Zanzibari Treaty in 1873 ended the practice, and Zanzibar’s economy collapsed. The Portuguese pulled out and in 1890 Germany, the only other power with any interest in the region, officially recognized “the British protectorate” over Zanzibar. The protectorate would be unilaterally terminated by the United Kingdom in December 1963, and Zanzibar would join Tanganyika to form Tanzania.</Text>
		</Row>
	</BaseGameText>
</GameData>
