<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<BaseGameText>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_INTRO_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
      <Text>Features are elements of terrain or vegetation that may appear atop the hex's terrain. (For example, a Grassland hex might have Woods or Marsh on it.) Features modify a hex's productivity and might also alter the amount of "movement points" (MP) a unit expends when entering the hex. Features may also provide defensive combat bonuses or penalties to a unit occupying the hex.</Text>
    </Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_BARRIER_REEF_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Meandering about off the coast of northeast Australia, the 2300-km (1400-mile) Great Barrier Reef is the largest structure built by living organisms (so much for manmade “wonders”) and can even be seen from orbit. Built by billions of coral polyps over a half-billion years, it now comprises some 2900 individual reefs and 900 islands, and is home to an incredible diversity of fauna – from 30 species of whales, dolphins, and porpoises to 215 species of birds. Unfortunately pollution, overfishing, tourism, and climate change are threatening the future of the reef; coral bleaching is accelerating and scientists estimate that unless drastic steps are taken, by 2030 AD the Great Barrier Reef will have suffered “irreversible damage” and no longer be “great.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_CLIFFS_DOVER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The famed White Cliffs of Dover stand guard over the narrowest stretch of the English Channel facing the continent of Europe. Composed of chalk streaked with black flint, the cliffs reach a height of 110 meters (350 feet) in places. On a clear day, the cliffs can be seen from France. This natural wonder owes its fame as much to its symbolic value as its natural beauty, which may not last forever (either one); the cliff face is weathering away at about a centimeter a year, and occasionally large pieces break off … thus, visitors are urged to remain well back from the edge (it just wouldn’t do to have an Englishman fall off the White Cliffs of Dover).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_CRATER_LAKE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>John Wesley Hillman was the first non-native to see the lake, which he named “Deep Blue Lake.” The lake has had an identity crisis ever since, having been later renamed “Majesty Lake,” and currently “Crater Lake.”  The local Klamath tribe considered it a sacred site, created during the battle between the sky god Skell and the underworld god Llao. Formed some 7700 years ago when the stratovolcano Mazama in the North American Cascade Range collapsed, Crater Lake is a deep caldera lake. Since no rivers flow into or out of the lake, the fresh waters there are the result of rain and snow; scientists estimate that the water is completely replaced only every 250 years. Not the best spot to refill a canteen when hiking the glorious Cascade trails.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_DEAD_SEA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Dead Sea – known to the Hebrews of antiquity as the “Sea of Salt” and the Arabs as the “Sea of Death,” both appropriate – is a salt lake in the Levant, and the lowest land elevation (420 meters below sea level) on Earth. With a salinity of 34.2 percent, it is one of the saltiest bodies of water on the planet … hardly a garden spot. But it was one of history’s first health resorts, much favored by Herod the Great, and was thought to offer putative therapies for the likes of psoriasis, rhinosinusitis, cystic fibrosis, and osteoarthritis. Mining the shore region has supplied all sorts of trade opportunities, from asphalt for mummification to potash for fertilizer. Mankind has a knack for finding the silver lining in anything … even the Dead Sea.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_EVEREST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mount Everest is the world’s tallest mountain, standing 8848 meters (29029 feet) above sea level, and part of the Himalaya range. One of the “hidden valleys of refuge” designated by the 9th Century Buddhist savant Padmasambhava, and killer of over 250 would-be conquerors since 1922. In 1802 AD, the British launched the Great Trigonometric Survey of India using giant theodolites to determine the highest peaks in the world. A half-century later, in 1858, the Surveyor General of India, Andrew Waugh, announced conclusively that Peak XV (that is, Everest) was the highest. And adventurers have been trying to climb it ever since... “Because it’s there.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_FLOODPLAINS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Floodplains are low-lying areas adjacent to rivers, and prone to flooding each year (or more often) and hence fertile from soil deposits and some of the most productive farmland known. Perhaps the best known are those along the Nile, which helped ancient Egypt become one of history’s greatest civilizations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_FOREST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The bounty of woods has been crucial in the survival of more than one tribe, providing timber, animals, and plants in such variety as to stagger the imagination. Sadly, civilization has too often chopped them down to make room for farms, roads, and suburbs … and then there are those greedy corporations, looking to grow rich from pelts, logs, and metals.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_GALAPAGOS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Islas Galapagos were first visited by a European when the Spanish Bishop of Panama, Fray Tomás de Berlanga, was blown off course on his way to Peru in 1535 AD. No one paid much attention again to the isolated equatorial archipelago until 1835 when the HMS Beagle, with a young naturalist named Charles Darwin aboard, happened by while charting approaches to Pacific harbors. Darwin wandered about Charles Island and noted that the tortoises there differed from those on other islands in the chain. Once he could cut them up, Darwin also found, despite distinct variations, a single species of finches on the islands. Thus originated the Origin of the Species … and mankind’s understanding of just about everything biological (not to mention spiritual) would never be the same afterward.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_ICE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Ice is impassable to ships (more than a few have come to grief, just ask the crew of the Titanic), and not much fun for other travelers. Except maybe the polar bears.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_JUNGLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Dark, forbidding, trackless, deadly – rainforests are only for those explorers with the skill and stamina to survive them … and natives with poisoned darts. Rainforests in Asia, Africa, and South America have provided all sorts of wealth and food, and now expensive pharmaceuticals to modern civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_KILIMANJARO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to Ernest Hemingway, in Masai it is known as Ngaje Ngai, the “House of God.” Composed of three volcanic cones, the highest reaching 5,900 meters (19,340 feet) – making it the highest point in Africa and the highest free-standing mountain in the world – the Kilimanjaro massif lies in northeastern Tanzania. Considered a stratovolcano, two of its peaks (Mawenzi and Shira) are extinct, while its highest (Kibo) is dormant; its last eruption dates back approximately 150 thousand years. After multiple failed attempts, the top of Kibo was finally reached in 1889 AD by the German Hans Meyer and Austrian Ludwig Purtscheller, who confirmed that Kibo did indeed have a crater. Despite the subsequent traipsing about on it, Kibo wasn’t actually mapped until 1964, based on aerial photography done a few years earlier.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_MARSH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Covered with herbaceous rather than woody plants, these freshwater wetlands are generally found along slow-flowing rivers or on the banks of lakes. Home to an incredible variety of valuable things, plant and animal, in some civilizations, towns in marshes and swamps grew into great cities: St. Petersburg, New Orleans, and the Brazilian ones in the Pantanal.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_OASIS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The stuff of legends, and vital for those wandering about the desert, oases sit atop a source of clean and plentiful water. Tales have been told of these wonderful outposts in an otherwise barren and lifeless land … and battles fought to control them.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_PANTANAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Pantanal is considered the world’s largest tropical wetlands, spreading out to as much as 195 thousand square kilometers (about 75 thousand square miles) of water, bog, quagmire, and muck. It is, of course, home to an extremely diverse bio-system of flora and fauna, including some 1000 species of birds and 480 species of reptiles. For centuries, the native Bororo lived happily among these, but by the end of the 1800s they had pretty well been annihilated by disease and Brazilian explorers, slave traders, prospectors, and settlers. Now several Brazilian cities are located within the Pantanal.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_PIOPIOTAHI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Known as Milford Sound by everyone save those stubborn natives - who named it after the now extinct piopio bird - the magnificent natural fjord was once called by Rudyard Kipling the "eighth Wonder of the World." Carved by glaciers, the New Zealand fjord’s cliffs rise vertically from the dark waters while waterfalls fall as much as 1000 meters down the faces. Ignored by early explorers such as Captain James Cook, the fjord remained undiscovered – at least by Europeans – until 1812 AD when it was named after an obscure spot in Wales by the first to sail into it. In 1888 the MacKinnon Pass was located, giving access to the fjord along the Milford Track, one of the best walking trails in the world. Now as many as three-quarter million visitors a year tramp and sail about the sound, making it the most famous tourist destination in the country.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_TORRES_DEL_PAINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The feminist and correspondent Lady Florence Dixie described the three granite towers as “Cleopatra’s Needles” in her 1880 book; she has the dubious distinction of being the “first foreign tourist” to the region. Sadly, she wasn’t the last, for the Torres del Paine Park has suffered three major forest fires since 1985 due to careless backpackers. Fortunately, the three peaks of the Paine Massif, standing 2850 meters above sea level, are surrounded by lakes and glaciers and were relatively untouched by the flames. The park itself encompassing the Torres del Paine peaks was established in 1977 by the Chilean government, and the following year the park was designated a World Biosphere Reserve by UNESCO.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_TSINGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Hardly a vacation spot for the kiddies, Tsingy de Bemaraha is a karst topology of jagged limestone formations, undercut with sinkholes and caves, on the island of Madagascar. Together with the adjoining Strict Nature Reserve (a lot of animals make their home among the intermixed spires and forests, including eleven species of lemurs), it was designated a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1990 AD. The labyrinth of vertical rocks – in places 300-foot high and all razor sharp – is hardly easy to reach (a five-day journey from Madagascar’s capital city) and not for the faint-hearted. Naturalists that have ventured into Tsingy de Bemaraha have had to crawl out seeking medical aid. It's only to be expected when tsingy is the Malagasy word meaning “where one cannot walk barefoot.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_YOSEMITE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Densely forested with pine and flanked by the granite summits of El Capitan and Half Dome, 13-kilometer (eight miles) long Yosemite Valley lies in the western Sierra Nevada. The original inhabitants, a tribe of Mono Lake Paiutes whose principle food was acorns, just didn’t appreciate it; so when the California Gold Rush saw restlessness among the natives, the state formed the Mariposa Battalion to drive them out. A few years later, in 1855 AD, James Hutchings organized the first tourist parties in the valley. The scribblings of artist-author Thomas Ayres generated interest in Yosemite in the far Eastern United States, and soon enough there was a toll road, several hotels, and new hiking trails. In 1864, President Lincoln declared that Yosemite Valley and the nearby tract of giant sequoias were to be “inalienable for all time” … and the United States had its first federally “protected” scenic park.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_COAST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Coastal waters (unless, of course, it’s a lake) beckoned early civilizations to venture out from land, where they found all sorts of riches and good things to eat. Thus, for millennia men had no need (or feared) to sail out of sight of land.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_DESERT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In general, deserts are remarkably useless, except to those creatures and man who have learned to live there. The true deserts of the world – the Sahara, Gobi, Mohave, Great Victoria, and such – have been swallowing men and civilizations since history began.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_DESERT_HILLS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Even less appealing than flat desert, about the only thing desert hills are good for is defending in a battle. Unfortunately, the Bedouins, Tuaregs, Berbers, and other desert tribesmen tended to just charge wildly down them.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_DESERT_MOUNTAIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As far as history is concerned, mountains are inhospitable obstacles to movement, and provide little to no benefit to a civilization … other than as barriers against invasion. Thus, they are appealing only to photographers, hermits, and mountain-climber sorts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_GRASS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Grasslands, blessed with rich and fertile soils, have been the heart of many civilizations, providing the food and open frontiers so necessary for expansion. Unfortunately, every barbarian also realizes this, and so grasslands have been fertilized with blood over the centuries.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_GRASS_HILLS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>One way to protect all those riches was to put troops on top of hills when attacked, for (until bullets and bombs were invented) holding the high ground was a pretty good strategy. Thus, in time, hills were dotted by civilization’s forts and castles, with fine views over the surrounding countryside.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_GRASS_MOUNTAIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As far as history is concerned, mountains are inhospitable obstacles to movement, and provide little to no benefit to a civilization … other than as barriers against invasion. Thus, they are appealing only to photographers, hermits, and mountain-climber sorts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_OCEAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The deep waters of the oceans scared mankind for much of history, braved only by the likes of the Polynesians and Vikings. But, once Europeans began sailing across them and colonizing everything, the world began to shrink … until today, when people cross them without trepidation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_PLAINS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A plain is simply a large, flat bit of terrain, with soil not as rich as fertile grassland but not as dry as desert. Thus, left alone (before all those tractors show up) plains tend to be overgrown with dry grasses and grains … perfect for large herds of animals such as bison, antelope, horses, and barbarians.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_PLAINS_HILLS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Hills in plains tend to be landmarks … just think of the highest point in Iowa, Hawkeye Point, at a stunning 1670 feet (510 meters). Given the flatness all about, these do give nice lines of sight for long distances over the endless, boring vistas.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_PLAINS_MOUNTAIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As far as history is concerned, mountains are inhospitable obstacles to movement, and provide little to no benefit to a civilization … other than as barriers against invasion. Thus, they are appealing only to photographers, hermits, and mountain-climber sorts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_SNOW_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>History offers very few examples of human survival in snow-covered lands in cold climates. There are exceptions, such as the Inuit and Tlingit peoples, but snowy wastes are not ideal places to build a thriving civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_SNOW_HILLS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Very picturesque, very invigorating, beloved of skiers and ski jumpers and other fools. Snow on hills is very nice, and a lot of fun … unless it never melts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_SNOW_MOUNTAIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As far as history is concerned, mountains are inhospitable obstacles to movement, and provide little to no benefit to a civilization … other than as barriers against invasion. Thus, they are appealing only to photographers, hermits, and mountain-climber sorts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_TUNDRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Tundra is the semi-frozen land found in the world's colder climates. Nobody builds cities in the tundra unless they’re desperate for resources (tundra tends to overlay extensive mineral and petroleum deposits) … or they've got nowhere else to go.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_TUNDRA_HILLS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Hills in tundra lands tend to be barren lumps, for the annual melt carries away the soil and seedlings. However, through history, most towns built in the tundra were put on hills … which helped keep the wolves and bears out of the streets.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_TERRAIN_TUNDRA_MOUNTAIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As far as history is concerned, mountains are inhospitable obstacles to movement, and provide little to no benefit to a civilization … other than as barriers against invasion. Thus, they are appealing only to photographers, hermits, and mountain-climber sorts.</Text>
		</Row>
	</BaseGameText>
</GameData>