<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<BaseGameText>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_INTRO_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
      <Text>After a district has been built, it can be populated with buildings. Buildings can be built through the “Production Menu" where districts are built. Some buildings have prerequisites, such as other buildings or technology; these buildings will not be visible in your Production menu.</Text>
    </Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_AIRPORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Technically, an “airport” is any sort of location where airplanes, helicopters, blimps, or other aircraft can take off and land. However, in common usage an airport is a complex for commercial passenger aircraft, consisting of runways, control towers, hangers, terminals, emergency facilities and even parking structures. Man’s tendency to be in a hurry has made airports an inherent part of every city landscape (although most commercial airports are now located well away from the city, given the noise and pollution). Prior to 1930, most airports were small airfields or aerodromes, with runways of less than 2000 feet. In 1939 busy La Guardia in New York City handled nearly a quarter million passengers a month; the most recent statistics for airport passenger traffic list Hartsfield-Jackson in Atlanta as the world’s busiest, with over 92 million passing through it in 2011.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_AMPHITHEATER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When bread and circuses didn’t keep the masses happy, there was always the theater to distract them. An amphitheater is an outdoor arena (modern usage of the term is rather lax) that serves as a venue for performances, sporting events and public speeches. Although there had certainly been public spectacles in various places before, these tended to be staged ad hoc. But when the Greeks began writing plays around 532 BC, they built small, open-air structures (called theatrons) in which to perform these; the Romans, always looking to build bigger and better, created the amphitheater. The Romans built them all over their conquered lands, for every frontier outpost wanted to be civilized. The practice spread outward from the empire to other places, for amphitheaters were great places to stage plays, gladiatorial and Olympic Games, religious spectacles, executions, political debates, concerts, and all manner of other entertainments.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_ARENA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>An indoor amphitheater … an “arena,” from the Latin harena, a fine sand that was very good at absorbing blood in colosseums across the Roman Empire. These days, that has been forgotten by all those who go to arenas to watch sporting events, concerts, and other performances (such as political speeches). The most distinguishing feature of an arena is that the performance area is the lowest point in the main space, with seating for spectators banked up around it. Since the ancients had some difficulty roofing over large areas, it is unknown what might be termed civilization’s first indoor arena, although the famed Colosseum had retractable awnings to cover the spectators’ area. Currently the largest arena in the world is the Philippine Arena in Bocaue, seating about 55 thousand. But likely the best known is Madison Square Garden in Manhattan, fourth of that name, the first opening in 1879 AD under lease to P.T. Barnum. The current Garden, seating between 18 and 20 thousand depending on event, opened in 1968 and has been home to heartache and history ever since.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_ARMORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>An armory (or arsenal, the terms tend to get mixed although there are some significant differences) is the place where arms and armor are manufactured, repaired and/or stored when not being used to kill other people – i.e., during peacetime. Unless planning on facing the enemy, soldiers usually do not carry their weapons and armor about with them (especially if their weapons were lances and their armor plate). The first armories date back to the first professional armies, those of Sumer and Akkad. Every standing army since has had armories, perhaps as simple as a well-guarded (wouldn’t do to let the commoners get hold of any weapons) warehouse or as elaborate as a production facility making muskets. Given that it didn’t make sense to have the weapons on the other side of the city from the troops, the armory was usually near the barracks. Armories have even shaped the course of civilization, for a variety of reasons: the Tower of London, Harper’s Ferry, the Kremlin Armoury, Springfield Armory, the Zeughaus in Berlin, and so forth.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_BANK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Although there had been money-lenders and treasuries before (money, after all, greases the wheels of civilization), banking begins in early Renaissance Italy, in the rich cities of the north such as Genoa, Venice, Florence, Siena and Lucca. During the 14th Century, already wealthy, avaricious families – the Bardi, de Medici, Peruzzi, Cerchi, Gondi and others – not only dominated the commercial banking in their home city-states but established branches across Europe. The oldest bank still in operation is the Monte dei Paschi in Siena, operating continuously since 1472 AD. Banking spread across the Holy Roman Empire and the northern European nations by 1600, and the Europeans took the practice with them when they set out to colonize the world. Although the details have changed dramatically with technology, the basics of banking profits remain the same: checking and savings fees, loans and credit cards, currency exchanges, fund management, and so forth.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_BARRACKS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Militiamen had homes, had jobs, and fed and clothed themselves, waging war only when called out by the government; professional soldiers had no homes, war was their occupation, and they got their victuals and spiffy uniforms from the government. Once writing was invented, professional armies were possible (along with most everything else, including kings and civilizations). Since they didn’t have homes as such, the barracks housed them … usually near the center of town so the soldiers could react to any threat, external or internal. Effectively, the barracks were permanent camps, with such amenities as training grounds, bath rooms, medical facilities, mess halls and gymnasia added. Often these barracks were at least minimally fortified, just in case of trouble. Be it ever so humble, home is where the heart is … in this case, war.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_BROADCAST_CENTER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>It wasn’t long after commercial radio began being broadcast that the first “broadcast center” was built: Broadcasting House, home of the British Broadcasting Corporation (the world’s oldest and largest), in 1932 AD. A “broadcasting center” is a complex (studios, sound booths, antennae, and lots of esoteric electrical equipment) for sending out radio and television waves to home receivers, thus keeping folk passively entertained for hours at a time. The BBC was chartered in 1922 as a government-supported operation to supply edifying entertainment and information to the people of Great Britain. Soon after, a number of Commonwealth nations took the same approach, as did a handful of other countries. In the American model, private broadcasting corporations provided competitive programming, funded by the sale of advertising time to “sponsors.” By 1928, the United States had three national networks (two owned by NBC). These competing (for audience numbers, which translate to advertising revenues) networks each built their own broadcasting center(s) to feed the electronic wasteland.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_CASTLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>From the Latin castellum, a castle is designed to protect the important people (and maybe those who serve them) from their enemies. Surrounded sometimes by moats and mottes, often with palisades and baileys and enceinte, usually with a central keep for when things really went wrong, the great castles were the last refuge during times of troubles. From the walls and towers the dedicated defenders could hurl death down upon the attackers … who, if they were smart, simply laid siege to the pile until those inside starved and sensibly surrendered. Historians are not quite sure (hardly surprising) when castles as such arose, but most attribute the development to an evolution of the walls around lordly homes to protect such from the likes of the Magyars. Muslims and Vikings in the 9th and 10th centuries AD. Proven Roman engineering techniques were adapted to make these outposts of civilization as nigh impregnable as possible. And, in time, royalty decided they might need some in their cities as well, for when the peasants started revolting. Worked well enough, until those peasants had gunpowder.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_CATHEDRAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once there were Catholic churches at every crossroads in Italy, some bishops decided they needed something grander to serve as the seat of each diocese or episcopate. Thus, the cathedral – from the Latin cathedra meaning “seat” or “chair.” The concept of cathedrals begins in 313 AD, when the emperor Constantine adopted Christianity; with that, Christianity went from being a minor faith to the religion of Rome, and the bishops agreed, more or less willingly, to take on the duties and dignity of magistrates across the empire. Since the old Roman magistrates had presided from a throne housed in a highly decorated hall (basilica), it wasn’t long before the bishops (who had never before been seated while presiding over their flock) began building cathedrals, massive edifices designed to impress the peasants with the glory of God. With money, materials and labor “donated” by the faithful peasants, these often took a lifetime to build … but are among some of the most impressive structures in all civilization. The first cathedral was that at Aquileia (c. 319) and they haven’t stopped building them yet.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_ELECTRONICS_FACTORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>With the advent of consumer electronics, the market for all manner of gizmos and gadgets for entertainment, communication and wasting time exploded in the late 20th Century. The Consumer Electronics Association estimated that sales of electronics for personal use – from computers to MP3 players, calculators to digital cameras, and so forth – exceeded 150 billion dollars in 2007 AD. To feed this postmodern addiction, semi-skilled laborers working in sprawling electronics factories assemble standardized parts into an ever-increasing flood of new products. Leading the way in this tidal wave is Japan, with the largest electronics industry in the world, although both South Korea and China are increasingly competitive. The first “modern” electronics factory was built by Sony, founded in 1946 AD. In the 1950s, Japanese engineers pioneered commercial applications for the transistor and in the 1970s and 1980s for the semi-conductor. Japanese innovations in miniaturization and in standardizing electronics manufacturing have kept their factories the most profitable in the most competitive field in consumerism ever seen.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_FACTORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Industrial Revolution came upon civilization, and all those things once made by hand are soon made in factories… and in great quantities. The workshops, where master craftsmen proudly made things by hand, gave way to the assembly line and the mass production of standardized products. The Englishman Richard Arkwright is credited with creating the prototype for the modern factory; in 1769 he patented the “water frame,” a water-powered spinning device, and built Cromford Mill in Derbyshire. In the process, he replaced skilled workers (on spinning wheels) with unskilled migrants who could produce more yarn quicker (albeit of poorer quality); in effect, Arkwright made workers a replaceable commodity in his plant. Soon enough, others copied the formula, and it was applied to other industries as technology brought steam, and then electricity, to the workshops. The final step in the industrialization of the workplace: Henry Ford revolutionized factory production with the first assembly line in 1913, capable of producing a Model T Ford using interchangeable parts in 93 minutes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_FILM_STUDIO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The “Black Maria,” a tarpaper-covered shack in West Orange, New Jersey, built by Thomas Edison in 1893 AD, might generously be termed the first “movie studio”; there Edison used film to capture the antics of vaudeville and theater actors to show to the public in penny arcades, unused theaters, and fairground tents. In 1909, Edwin Thanhouser leased an old skating rink and made commercial films, some 1086 between 1910 and 1917. Meanwhile in Europe, studios such as Pathé (France), Münchner Lichtspielkunst AG (Bavaria). Mosfilm (Russia) and Ealing Studios (UK) were being founded. But, for unexplained reasons, a number of studios sprouted up in and around Los Angeles (the best explanation being that natural sunlight was the best for the crude movie cameras of the time), the first being Nestor Studios in 1911. By 1920, there were a dozen in operation in the suburb of Hollywood cranking out film by the mile to feed civilization’s latest escapist addiction. Although film studios are largely passé (most production taking place “on location”), some remain in operation in odd corners of the globe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_GRANARY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once farming really took off, someplace was needed to put that surplus grain to keep it safe from rats, insects, and other humans. The oldest granaries yet uncovered date back to the pre-pottery Neolithic period in the Jordan Valley, c. 9500 BC. In the Indus Valley, the oldest date to 6000 BC, and the Egyptians were storing surplus grain in “silo” pits as a hedge against poor harvests by this time as well. In East Asia, the Yangshao in China were building elevated granaries along the Yellow River around 5000 BC, and eventually the Koreans (c. 1000 BC) and the Japanese (c. 800 BC) figured it out as well. In modern times, granaries – like all else – have gotten larger, automated, and more complex; the rich farmlands of the United States and Russia, especially, are dotted with huge silos and grain elevators to help feed the teeming masses of civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_GURDWARA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A gurdwara (meaning “the gateway to the guru”) is a Sikh temple, although those of all faiths are welcomed to worship in their own way there. The gurdwara traditionally has a great hall (the Darbar Sahib) where the Guru Granth Sahib is displayed and a Langar where visitors can partake of the free food offered by the Sikh community. The egalitarian complex may also have a nursery, library, hospital and/or classrooms. The very first Sikh guru, Nanak Dev Ji, built the very first gurdwara in 1521 AD on the banks of the Ravi River of the Punjab … so legend has it. The first gurdwaras were the places for the faithful to gather to hear the current guru speak and to sing hymns to Waheguru (loosely, “God”). It was the sixth Sikh guru who finally gave such places the name “gurdwara.” Since meditation and the study of the scriptures are central to Sikhism, the gurdwara is vital to the “proper” moral and spiritual development of a Sikh.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_HANGAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Ships need docks; airplanes need hangars. It was quickly discovered that the early heavier-than-air craft tended to need protection from the weather, repair, and constant maintenance, and all of this was best done inside cavernous structures made of wood and fabric (now, virtually all hangars are made of metal and/or concrete). The bigger the aircraft, the bigger the hangar necessary; XXL hangars (more than 120 meters across) are used to house the world’s largest aircraft: the Airbus A380, Antonov 225, and Boeing 747. But the largest hangars in civilization were those built for the zeppelins and dirigibles, such as the U.S. Navy’s Hangar 1 located at Lakehurst (the site of the Hindenburg disaster). From the S to the XXL, hangars are vital to the operations of military airfields and civilian airports in this fast-paced era (thus, hangars are prime targets in any modern war).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_LIBRARY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once literacy fastened on civilization, it was inevitable that reading materials (books, periodicals, maps, newspapers, scrolls, tablets, documents of all sorts) should be gathered in one place – a library. The first libraries, those of Sumer dating back to approximately 2600 BC, were archives of clay tablets covered in cuneiform script. Over 30 thousand clay tablets have been unearthed in the Library of Ashurbanipal in Nineveh, including the Epic of Gilgamesh. The Library of Alexandria was the greatest and most significant library in the classical world, but it was burned – a fate most great libraries suffer, it seems. While Europe plunged into a Dark Age, libraries flourished under the Muslim Arabs, whose development of papermaking helped considerably in their acquisition of texts from the known world. Although many of these historical libraries were open to all, the foundation of free, public libraries came with the British Public Libraries Act of 1850, a boon to the literate (about 76% in 1870) no matter their low birth.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_LIGHTHOUSE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The sea is a dangerous place, filled with shoals, shallows, reefs, and rocks just waiting to bring the unwary ship to grief. And the weary crew might have a difficult time finding safe harbor. So, in antiquity, not long after men began sailing, signal fires were lit to guide the ship away from danger to port; since such signal fires would be even more visible if elevated, “lighthouses” began to be built by the first seafaring civilizations on promontories. The most famous of the ancient ones: the Pharos at Alexandria, of course, which guided ships into what was once the busiest seaport in the world. For two thousand years since, lighthouses were built wherever there was a need for sailors not to drown and cargos not to be lost. Stone, wood, and brick have given way to steel and concrete construction, and fire has given way to arc lamps, but the principle remains the same.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_MADRASA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A madrasa (madrasah in Arabic or medrese in Turkish) is a secular institution of education, although often with a religious component. Madrasas would specialize in medicine, law, science, philosophy, religion or the education of (horrors) women. Others also taught logic, world history, foreign languages, mathematics, art, and comparative literature. The first madrasa, the Gama'at al-Qarawiyyn, was established in 859 AD by Fatimah al-Fihri, the daughter of a wealthy merchant. During the rule of the Fatimid, Ayyubid, and Mamluk dynasties, the practice of sponsoring madrasas by the ruling, wealthy elite spread across Egypt and the Middle East. The first Ottoman madrasa was founded in 1331 in Iznik, and followed the traditions of Sunni Islam. The madrasas of the Turks and Arabs would, as Europe stumbled through the Dark Ages, keep the best of Western knowledge alive, and blend it with that of the East.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_MARKET_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Whether called a souk (Arabic), bazaar (Persian), mercado (Spanish) or palengke (Filipino), markets have been around since farmers had surpluses and tradesmen had wares to sell to townsfolk. While primitive markets may have operated on a barter system, it was the coming of writing and coinage that made markets profitable and, indeed, indispensable to civilization. Markets were located in towns, both transport hubs and centers of consumption, even when the latter were off the beaten track. Marketplaces in Thebes, Babylon, Athens, Rome, Bangkok, Marrakech, London, Delhi, in all places and all times, offered the exotic, innovative and everyday for sale. Their shape and style may differ dramatically – floating markets, indoor markets, street markets, night markets, market squares, ad infinitum – but the intent is the same: to make a profit for the stallholders.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_MEETING_HOUSE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In opposition to the magnificent cathedrals and churches of the Catholic Church, the Protestants thought worship should be serious and undistracted by art. Hence some Congregationalists worshipped in meeting houses - plain, unadorned buildings built from local resources (usually wood and stone). In the New World, the social and cultural center for most of the Protestant colonies was the meeting house, which served as both a place of worship and of public discourse for the settlers. For many early Quaker, Mennonite, Unitarian, Puritan, Baptist and other pious types, the meeting house also served as the de facto town hall, where political debates, votes and decisions were conducted. All along the Atlantic coast colonies, the first public building to go up was typically the meeting house. Once the separation of church and state became a widespread principal in the new United States, those meeting houses were all converted into town halls.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_MILITARY_ACADEMY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If a civilization is to have a professional army, then it needs professionals to run it. (It helps, but certainly doesn’t guarantee, that that expensive army won’t get wasted anyway.) A military academy is an institution of “higher” learning in the “art” of war, dedicated to training officers. The first military academies were established in the early 1700s in Europe (the oldest, the Royal Military Academy at Woolwich in 1720 AD) to train officers in the “technical” branches of the army, such as the engineers and the artillery. In France, the École Royale Militaire was founded in 1751, the first to offer a general military education. Within a generation, Prussia, Russia, Austria, Sweden and most of the lesser European states had military academies turning out army officers. And why not start teaching boys the ways of war as well, so private boarding schools for pre-collegiate cadets were established in the United Kingdom (such as Welbeck College), France (Saint-Cyr for instance), the United States (Valley Forge Military Academy and others), Russia (the Suvorov Military Schools) and elsewhere.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_MONUMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since humans seem to be a forgetful sort – or perhaps just egotistical – they put up monuments to commemorate all kinds of things – “important” people, events, military victories, deities, or even fictional characters (such as that to Peter Pan in Kensington Gardens). They seem to especially like to stick them up in the middle of cities, so everyone has to see them and walk or drive around them. Monuments come in all shapes and sizes, beautiful and horrid. Triumphal arches, columns, obelisks, memorials and cenotaphs can be found in almost any large urban metropolis, supposedly infusing the inhabitants with civic and national pride. Or, as is usually the case, serving as nesting places for pigeons and recognizable backgrounds for tourist snapshots.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_MOSQUE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>There are strict requirements and standards in Islamic fiqh for a building to be a mosque, and those places of worship that do not meet those are merely musallas (“gathering houses”). Under Sharia law, once a mosque is formally designated as a holy place, it remains that until the Day of Judgment (Yawm ad-Din). The oldest and largest mosque in the world, the Masjid al-Haram, was built in the city of Mecca around 638 AD; it encompasses the holy site of the Kaaba, the most sacred of all locations in Islam. The Prophet himself established other mosques, notably that at Medina. From there, mosques – with their distinctive domes, minarets and prayer halls overseen by an imam – were carried by the swords of the faithful across Arabia, the Middle East and North Africa during the 7th Century. The first mosque built in the Far East – that at Xi’an – reportedly dates to the mid-8th Century. A site of prayer, charity and learning, the mosque is the physical heart of Islamic civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_MUSEUM_ART_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Art museums (or art galleries) are public spaces - paid for by the public, usually in the form of taxes – to house artwork meant to edify and uplift the masses. The art objects may take many forms: paintings, sketches, sculptures, ceramics, metalwork, prints, and now even video. Perhaps the first such effort at bringing high culture to the public took place in 1671 AD, the Amerbach-Cabinet in Basel (now the Kunstmuseum). But the whole idea of such collections for public edification really took off during the Renaissance, with the likes of the Capitoline, Vatican, and Uffizi galleries established. The 1700s saw another wave of iconic collections open: the Hermitage, the Prado, the Louvre, and the first American museum, the Charleston Museum, in 1773. The Louvre was established in 1793, soon after the French Revolution when the royal collection of art was declared the property of the people, beginning the trend of removing art from the grasp of the wealthy and putting it on tasteful display for the public to gawk at.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_MUSEUM_ARTIFACT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Humans generate lots of junk. They are also fascinated with old junk, and so created museums. A museum is a building designed to hold civilization’s most treasured possessions for public viewing. There are museums that contain collections of art, and there are the museums which display fossils, items of historical interest, or pop culture curiosities. There are also museums that house costumes, jewels, weapons, gadgets, or virtually anything else which might be of interest to the humans filing through their halls. The oldest known collection of curiosities put on display was that of Ennigaldi-Nanna’s Museum, c. 530 BC, with enough traffic to warrant labels for the items (a clue to archaeologists that the ruin was a museum). But the whole idea of such collections for public edification really took off during the Enlightenment, with the Royal Armories in the Tower of London, the Musée des Beaux-Arts et d’Archeologie in Besancon, and the Kunstkamera in St. Petersburg being founded. These and other museums are now almost as historic as the junk they display.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_PAGODA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Technically, a “pagoda” is a building style – a tiered tower with overhanging eaves – rather than a building, but for the unenlightened it has come to be the generic term for religious structures in the Far East, mostly Buddhist but also Taoist, Shinto and Confucian. The origin of the pagoda structure can be traced to the stupas of 3rd Century BC Nepal. From there, the architectural style spread across China and East Asia, where the Buddhists adopted it for their buildings housing sacred relics and texts. For Buddhist missionaries, pilgrims and priests, these pagodas became the centers of their faith on Earth with images of Gautama Buddha prominent and plentiful. The building materials and decoration, from unadorned to ornate, varied widely from region to region and faith to faith. But pagodas traditionally have an odd number of levels, the notable exception being the 163-foot “pagoda folly” erected by Sir William Chambers at Kew Gardens in London in 1762 and thought clever by the English.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_PALACE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As soon as some chieftain managed to become a king, he (or she) began to have delusions of grandeur; living in a hut like everyone else just wouldn’t do. A palace is the residence of a civilization's ruler. The term is somewhat anachronistic, since all sorts of things are called “palaces” nowadays, even gambling casinos. Currently most rulers live in ornate buildings called something like “the White House” or “Government House,” but the effect is the same. Palaces (and their modern equivalents) are designed to do three things: to provide the ruler with access to the people and communications necessary to rule, to defend the leader from attack, and to impress upon subjects and foreign visitors the leader's importance and staggering hubris.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_POWER_PLANT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The sole purpose of a power plant (or power station, generating plant, or power house) – be it hydro, nuclear, solar, fossil fuel-fired, tidal or other – is to feed the voracious appetite for electricity that civilization has developed over the past 160 years. Whatever the form, the principle is the same: convert one type of energy into another so that humans can enjoy their comforts. The first power plant was designed and built by Baron William Armstrong in 1868 AD (when scientists were still playing around with electricity in labs) in Cragside; water from a lake was used to turn the dynamos, and the resulting electricity powered lights, heating, hot water heaters, an elevator, and other odd devices in his properties nearby. In January 1882 the first public power plant came online in London, and in September the Pearl Street Station began operations in New York City supplying electricity to lower Manhattan. Although the Pearl Street Station burned down in 1890, it was too late – people were hooked on electric lights, and now over 7300 power plants operate in the United States alone.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_RESEARCH_LAB_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A research lab is an institute devoted to the advanced study of a subject, which might be medicine, physics, chemistry, robotics, clean energy, or new products for TV infomercials. Such labs may be publicly funded or run by wealthy corporations looking for profits; research labs may be attached to universities or they may be independent of academic boundaries and ethics. It is pretty clear that “efficient” research labs are the future of research in every discipline. As civilization’s understanding of the world has advanced, the days of the dedicated scientist working alone in his or her basement and shouting “Eureka!” have all but passed. Whatever understanding Mankind may gain of the natural world, whatever new tech toy may grab his attention, whatever improvement of his daily life may come, whatever horrors may be unleashed, it will likely come out of a research laboratory, whether large (CERN’s Large Hadron Collider) or small (computer simulation modelling).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_SEAPORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The sites of ancient ports were selected to optimize access to land or river routes, protect the anchored shipping, and maximize harbor fees – Guangzhou in Qin China, Piraeus for Athens, Canopus and Alexandria in Egypt, Lothal for the Harappan, Rome's Ostia Antica. More than just a harbor, a seaport offered all the necessities for sea-going vessels and their crews: cordage and carpentry workshops, docks and slips, bars and brothels, warehouses, and so on. The seaports of Europe were the launching points for the exploration and colonization of the world, as well as the naval bases that figure prominently in military history. Commercial empires rose and fell tied to the fate of their seaports: Phoenicia, Srivijaya, Portugal and others. Although less common than those facing the seas, inland ports such as New Orleans or Calcutta gave vast regions access to the oceans. Today the great ports of the world – Port Said, Hamburg, Shanghai, Melbourne, Santos, Hong Kong, Los Angeles and Vancouver, to name a few – are a forest of cranes, a maze of roads and rail, a city of warehouses and storage tanks, all devoted to making a profit from export and import.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_SEWER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Put enough people and animals in one place, pave over the streets, let it rain … and the need for a sewage system becomes evident. At least it did to the Indians; the oldest covered sewers uncovered by archaeologists have been found in the ruins of the Indus Valley civilization. Where to put the runoff from the waste water and sewage was always a problem; the great Cloaca Maxima in ancient Rome, considered an engineering marvel, emptied into the Tiber River (hopefully, downriver from where the city’s drinking water was acquired). In many places, a natural waterway was covered over and served as the sewer system; London’s River Fleet is one such. With the advent of the Industrial Revolution, and the explosive growth of cities, during the early 19th Century many civil engineers urged the construction of integrated, purposeful water and sewer systems; the “Great Stink” of 1858 in London resulted in the first “modern” sewer system, funded by Parliament, and became the basis for all the sewage innovations since.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_SHIPYARD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The earliest known dockyards – dating c. 2400 BC - have been found in the ruins of Lothal in the state of Gujarat, India. Naupactus means “shipyard” in Greek; it is not surprising that that ancient city was known for building warships. Every nation with pretentions of being an empire had its shipyards. Ships were one of the first things to be mass produced; centuries before the wondrous Industrial Revolution, the Arsenal in Venice was able to produce a merchant or war ship in a day, using pre-manufactured and standardized parts on an assembly line. With the advent of iron and steel vessels, shipyards became more like factories than ever, with massive drydocks to build the greatest ocean-going vessels ever … but it took more than a day. At the sprawling Harland &amp; Wolff shipyard in Belfast, the RMS Titanic was laid down in March 1909 but not launched until May 1911, with nearly a year still until completion and its fateful maiden voyage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_SHRINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>To appease a god (or goddess), put up a shrine. Whether simple – a big rock in a forest clearing next to a stream – or elaborate – a marble edifice of soaring arches and fluted columns – the purpose is the same: someplace for the faithful to make pilgrimages to and offerings at. Inevitably the site where some prophet (or perhaps just a saint) performed a miracle, had a revelation, spoke to the masses, or ascended to some form of heaven, civilization’s landscape is peppered with shrines. These holy places are the stuff of nearly every religion, but are usually torn down when a new religion takes over the locale, and a new god must be appeased.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_STABLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>What the barracks were for cavalry soldiers, stables were for their mounts. Indeed, the horses and mules of the military were generally better off than those peasants that took care of them. In most places, the stables also encompassed the barracks of the cavalry unit, from the Imperial Roman turma to Britain’s Household Cavalry. In addition to the stalls, mangers, feed storage rooms, grooms’ quarters (unless they slept with the horses), the military stables also provided large enclosures for training and drill, and of course there were the veterinarian’s quarters. In time, in some places such as England, the term “stable” even came to refer to the headquarters of a cavalry regiment. Besides the military stables of the land, there were often royal stables and mews, where the monarch’s personal mounts and carriages were kept; these usually had some form of mounted royal guard stationed within. Today, most cavalry stables have been replaced with the less glamorous “motor pools.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_STADIUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A stadium is a better version of the colosseum, with a wider selection of snacks and more restrooms. The oldest known stadium, an open-air venue dedicated to worshipping sporting competitions, was in the western Peloponnese and served as the site of the ancient Olympic Games, first held c. 776 BC. Greek and Roman stadiums have been found in the ruins of many cities, a testament to their culture of competition. With the growth of leisure and the popularity of organized sports in the Victorian Age – notably football (soccer for the uncivilized) in Europe and baseball in America – stadiums were being built at a furious pace across the globe. Most of those industrial-age stadiums were built of wood, such as that at Lansdowne Road in Dublin (1872-2006) or the South End Grounds in Boston (1871-1914). These days, modern concrete-and-steel stadiums can hold upwards of 100 thousand screaming, obnoxious fans for a sporting match, rock concert, or political rally.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_STAR_FORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When cannon came to combat, those old, high, straight city walls didn’t stand up very well. Thanks to the unrelenting warfare in Italy during the Renaissance, military engineers there devised the “star fort” (more properly, the trace italienne) in the mid-15th Century AD. The design of a star fortress is evident from any sketch: a flat, low- and thick- and slope-walled structure composed of many triangular bastions, so positioned as to provide covering fire for each other, all surrounded by a glacis to deflect cannonballs and a ditch to deter infantry. Star forts were used by Michelangelo in his defensive designs for Florence, and later the concepts were refined by the engineer Peruzzi (for Siena) and by the author Scamozzi. Against the oft-invading French and Hapsburgs, Italian cities soon dispensed with traditional fortifications and surrounded their cities with star forts. The efficacious design spread out of Italy in the 1530s and 1540s to become the standard across Europe by the time of the great military engineer Vauban.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_STAVE_CHURCH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>After they got past their pagan ways, stave churches were wooden, post-and-beam constructions built throughout medieval Scandinavia once the Vikings converted to Christianity. In Sweden alone it is estimated that over a thousand stave churches were scattered about, the oldest dating back to the mid-1100s. Besides their religious function, these often served as meeting halls, cultural centers, courthouses, and even as marketplaces. Early stave churches were palisade constructions, with steeply pitched roofs to shed the heavy snows. The churches had elaborate wooden carvings, usually Christian in design but occasionally depicting pre-Christian heroes and myths. Later, only the corner posts were set in the earth, with planking covering the frame. Currently 30 stave churches remain standing, all but two in Norway.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_STOCK_EXCHANGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Stock exchanges exist for people who like to gamble in a refined fashion, speculating on the rise and fall of the value of “stock” – shares of ownership in “publically traded” companies. With advice from stock brokers, who always get a fee, anyone can wheel and deal in stocks, bonds, or other securities. The practice has its genesis in the creation of tradable bonds by Italian banks in the Renaissance, a creditor stake in a company or enterprise (such as a trading voyage). The Dutch East Indies Company, formed in 1602 AD, was the first corporation to put up shares for sale, offering delayed dividends (a portion of its annual profits) for speculative investment by anyone who could afford to buy. All those new middle class folk couldn’t resist, and soon enough other companies were doing the same. In time, an Englishman of dubious repute named John Castaing, operating from Jonathan’s Coffee House, began posting a regular list of stock and commodity prices and serving as a broker in these for a fee; this marks the beginning of the London Stock Exchange. The practice, despite the South Seas Bubble and the Tulip Mania and all the other scams and scandals, has been around ever since.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_MBANZA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mbanza is Kongolese for “city,” or in some cases simply “settlement.” By the time the Portuguese arrived in central Africa, M’banza Kongo was already a large city, rich from trade and craft manufacturing, but most of the population lived in the valleys that surrounded it in residential neighborhoods – perhaps as many as 100 thousand people. While these small towns might have a market and a workshop, the important things – churches, palace, schools, clinics, tax offices – were located in the hilltop capital. They were linked to M’banza Kongo by several roads up the slopes, and these were quite crowded at times such as feast and tax days. All this in 1648 AD according to the visitor Francesco da Roma. So not only did the Kongolese give civilization suburbia but also “rush hour.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_SYNAGOGUE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Traditionally, the term synagogue (Greek for “assembly”) is used to describe all Jewish temples and is a place both of worship and of study. Worship and prayer take place in the main room, the sanctuary. The prayer may be led by a rabbi (“teacher”) – but not necessarily, and many synagogues do not have a rabbi in attendance. Communal worship can occur whenever a 'minyan' (ten Jews) convenes. Although synagogues existed before the destruction of the Second Temple in Jerusalem in 70 AD, one of its rabbis – Yohanan ben Zakkai – promoted the idea of establishing individual houses of worship wherever the scattered Jews might find themselves. Thus, ever since, any individual Jew (king, wealthy patron, scholar, etc.) or group of Jews (Sephardic, Hasidic, Karaite, Orthodox, Reform, etc.) can found a synagogue.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_TEMPLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A temple is that structure reserved for spiritual activities – prayer, communion, sacrifice, and the like – devoted to a deity. Virtually every organized religion has temples of some sort; unlike shrines, these are planned piety, the power of God made manifest. Temples are also business concerns, what with all the tithes and donations, and so serve to feed, clothe, and support the priests, acolytes, vestal virgins, monks, rabbis, etc. The oldest known temples, found in Mesopotamia, date from the 10th Century BC and are simple affairs. But over time temples became ever more elaborate and magnificent, and had a significant impact on civilization – such as the Temple of Karnak in Thebes, the Parthenon in Athens, the Mahabodhi Temple in Bihar, or the Temple of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints in Salt Lake.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_UNIVERSITY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>An institution of “higher” learning since the first c. 1100 AD, the modern university has its roots in the Catholic cathedral and monastic schools dating back to the 6th Century. With the exception of the University of Paris (founded c. 1150), most of the early universities were begun by the kings and queens of the land – at Bologna (1088), Oxford (1167), Modena (1175), Cambridge (1209) Padua (1222), Krakow (1364) and many others – as an alternative (and curb to) the Catholic schools. In contrast (and defiance) to the Catholic Church, these “public” universities espoused “academic freedom”; the first such was the Constitutio Habita in 1155 of the University of Bologna, which granted rights and protections to the scholars studying there as guaranteed by the Holy Roman Emperor Frederick Barbarossa. The universities offered studies in law, medicine, logic, philosophy, certain sciences, and the classics then; now young scholars can get “degrees” in basket-weaving, sports management, music therapy and the like.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_WALLS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Until things like gunpowder, bomber aircraft, and nuclear missiles made them rather pointless, city walls were pretty important if a city wanted to stay inviolate. If a town wanted to keep its citizens relatively safe and its stuff relatively secure from the barbarians at the gates, it needed a relatively strong wall surrounding it. The Sumerian city of Uruk is the oldest known settlement completely enclosed by a wall, in this case supposedly built by the god-king Gilgamesh. Some of the early settlements in the Indus Valley – such as Kot Diji – had massive stone-and-brick walls for protection. On the other hand, if the city was inhabited by awesome warriors, it could generally get by without walls – Sparta and Rome survived for several centuries before walls were built. Today, what portions of city walls remain are either ignored or consider part of the “local color.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_WAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Buddhist monasteries in Cambodia, Thailand and Laos are termed “wats” (Sanskrit for “enclosure”). The wat often encompassed a school, and hence were both holy and educational. A wat generally consists of a temple containing statues of the Buddha, a prayer room, a room containing religious texts, a pavilion for relaxation, a library, study hall, bell towers, drum towers, and living quarters. Wats come in two types: those granted wisungkhamasima (royal patronage) and those not (samnak song). They abound across Southeast Asia, and architectural styles are as varied as the peoples – although the living quarters for the monks and novices are invariably separate from the sacred structures. Often ornately decorated and gilded, wats are some of the most distinctive and historic structures in Malaysia, including the famous one at Angkor, Cambodia, constructed in the early 12th Century under the patronage of King Suryavarman II.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_WATER_MILL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A water mill uses flowing water to turn a water wheel which is geared to turn other wheels for grinding, spinning, sawing or pounding all manner of useful things: grain, lumber, textiles, ore, metal, paper, and so forth. Most folk think of water mills as gristmills, those adapted to producing flour from grain … and that is certainly the earliest type found. The Greek engineer Philo of Byzantium (c. 280 to 220 BC) left an account of the workings of a water mill; the Roman Vitruvius offered the first technical description of building one, his an undershot wheel with a gearing device. So useful was the water mill that by the time of the Dark Ages, they could be found near every settlement, and (unlike a lot of knowledge that got lost) the Europeans managed to retain the essentials to construct and operate water-driven gristmills. Later on, steam power and electrical power replaced the water wheels, being more efficient and economic; today, only barbarians would use actual water mills to grind their corn and wheat.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_WORKSHOP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A workshop is for work … that is, for working wood, metal, glass, ceramic, and anything else needed to make something worthwhile. Stocked with tools and simple machinery, for hundreds of years workshops have been the abode of master craftsmen making everything from doors to doorknobs, from glassware to horseshoes (a blacksmith’s forge is a type of workshop). Ancient workshops date back to the earliest settlements of civilization, stamping Mankind as “homo faber.” By the Middle Ages, the workshop “economy” was well in hand, with practices gradually becoming ever more rigid – as in the case of the apprenticeship system, whereby young boys were bound to master craftsmen who taught them the intricacies of their skilled work. Apprenticeships generally lasted seven years, whereupon the apprentice became a master and could acquire his own workshop (those that didn’t were journeymen). However, the Industrial Revolution put paid to the entire system, as factories could mass produce the items cheaper (albeit of poorer quality).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_ZOO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The oldest known menagerie (or “zoological park,” i.e., zoo) has been excavated at Hierakonpolis and dates to c. 3500 BC; according to archaeologists, it contained hippos, elephants, hartebeest, baboons, and wildcats. In the 12th Century BC the Chinese empress Tanki had a “house of deer,” and the later Wen of Zhou established a 1500-acre menagerie. Alexander the Great had live specimens of unusual animals sent back to Greece to be displayed, and most of the Roman emperors had extensive collections of animals for the citizens to ogle. Humans have always been fascinated by watching caged animals, but no one is quite sure what the animals staring back at the humans are thinking; probably better not to know. The oldest existing zoo, the Tiergarten Schoenbrunn in Vienna, evolved from the exotic animal collection maintained by the Habsburg dynasty and was opened to the public in 1765 AD. Whipsnade Wild Animal Park in England opened in 1931 as the first drive-through “safari” park … a supposed “advance” over the traditional zoo full of cages.</Text>
		</Row>
	</BaseGameText>
</GameData>