<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<BaseGameText>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_INTRO_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
      <Text>In Civilization VI, the term "unit" refers to anything that can move around the map. There are a number of types of units in play – military units, Builders, Settlers, Great People, and the like. Military units form the bulk of available units.</Text>
    </Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_AIRCRAFT_CARRIER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>It was likely inevitable that someone would have the insane idea of flinging an airplane off a moving ship at sea. That someone was Commander Charles Samson of the British Royal Navy in 1912 AD from the deck of the HMS Hibernia, following the example of the American Eugene Ely, who had been the first to takeoff from a stationary ship (USS Birmingham in 1910) and later land on one (USS Pennsylvania in 1911). Then, despite the nay-sayers, came the HMS Ark Royal, originally laid down as a merchant ship but converted to a “flat-top” for launching planes; she was commissioned in September 1914, just in time to serve throughout WW1. By the late 1930s, various navies – notably the Japanese and the American – had designed large aircraft carriers, meant to bring airpower to bear across the expanses of the Pacific against those behemoth battleships that ruled the waves. Soon enough, they issued in the end of the battleship, commencing with the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor in 1941. These days, naval task forces are centered on the carriers, with every other ship dancing to their tune.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_AMERICAN_P51_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>With the coming of WW2, it was quickly apparent that America’s fighter aircraft were obsolete and not-up-to-snuff against the German and Japanese fighters, so the United States sold the old planes to the British and Russians and developed the P-51 “Mustang.” Designed to specifications supplied by the British Purchasing Commission as a long-range, high-altitude, single-seat fighter and fighter-bomber and bomber escort – able to outperform the best Luftwaffe fighters above 15000 feet and outlast the Japanese fighters – the prototype was unveiled in September 1940. By 1943, Mustangs were in service on every American front, knocking the enemy out of the skies with abandon. Even with the advent of jet fighters, the old warbird served during the Korean War as a fighter-bomber. Afterward, those that weren’t scrapped were sold as surplus, most of which were converted for the obscure sport of air racing or restored for the obscure spectacle of air shows.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_AMERICAN_ROUGH_RIDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The First United States Volunteer Cavalry – better known to the unenlightened as the “Rough Riders” (the nickname taken from Buffalo Bill’s “Congress of Rough Riders of the World” … and describing Teddy’s unruly recruits rather well) – was a regiment raised by Theodore Roosevelt in 1898 AD for action in the Spanish-American War. Roosevelt had been a staunch supporter of America acquiring a colonial empire by almost any means, and when troubles arose in Cuba the United States took advantage of the opportunity to beat up the moribund and bankrupt Spanish Empire. Roosevelt immediately resigned his post as Asst. Secretary of the Navy and raised a volunteer regiment of 1060 cowboys, ranchers, miners, college athletes, and other rough sorts from Arizona, New Mexico, Texas, and Oklahoma. Although a cavalry unit, they served with distinction – mostly afoot, as at the famous charge up San Juan Hill (actually, Kettle Hill – but that’s Americans abroad for you) on July 1st. Afterward the Rough Riders were part of the siege of Santiago, until Spain surrendered in August, whereupon the volunteers returned home and went about celebrating in their own ways.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_ANTIAIR_GUN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The minute generals started using aircraft, other generals started shooting at them, usually with artillery. The unsporting use of balloons by the Union army to gather intelligence in the American Civil War compelled the Confederates to develop methods to bring them down to earth. Nothing very practical was developed for anti-aircraft purposes until WW1, when the British decided a few weeks into the conflict that something was needed to dissuade the Germans from flying over their coasts with Zeppelins; the QF 1-pounder “pom-pom” was the first artillery piece designed as a dedicated anti-aircraft (AA) gun. Soon, everyone had some type of “ack-ack” to fire at the growing number of warplanes buzzing about, both on the battlefield and on the home front. During WW2, there were lots of AA guns deployed, but they weren’t very effective against the new breed of fast aircraft; post-war studies showed that the vast majority of bombers still reached their targets (on the order of 90%). And thus, as jet aircraft made an appearance, so too did AA missiles.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_APOSTLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>An “apostle” (from Greek, meaning “one who is sent away”) is a messenger and ambassador for the chosen deity of a given religion in an attempt to convert the faithless. In Christianity, where the concept is most prevalent, the Twelve were mere disciples before scattering out as ordered by the resurrected Christ to spread his “Word.” For Islam, an apostle is a prophet, specifically one sent to teach Allah’s truth: Ibrahim (Abraham in the Hebrew bible), Musa (Moses), Dawud (David), Isa (Jesus), and of course Mohammed. These days some churches simply appoint their own apostles; among the Latter-day Saints, for instance, an Apostle is a member of the priesthood with high authority, and in the Bahá’í faith the apostles were designated as such by Shoghi Effendi, the Guardian.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_ARABIAN_MAMLUK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Although the term mamluk simply means “property” or “owned slave” in Arabic, most think of the military caste in medieval Islam as the only mamalik (the plural form) in history. They are certainly the most famous. Although there is disagreement among scholars, most agree that the mamluk slave-warriors arose during the reign of the Abbasid caliphs of Bagdad sometime around the 9th Century AD. These warriors were primarily of Kipchak, Circassian, Georgian, and Balkan tribes, captured or sold into slavery, and proved devoted converts to Islam, superb horsemen, and vicious adversaries. Over time the mamluks became a political power – as in Cairo where they established a sultanate – in many Muslim kingdoms, where they sometimes served as kingmakers (well, sultan-makers). So successful and influential was the mamluk caste that it survived 1000 years until wiped out by the Ottoman general Muhammed Ali Pasha in 1811.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_ARCHAEOLOGIST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Archaeologists study human behavior in the past, primarily through the excavation and analysis of human fossils, the ruins of buildings, and the remains of human artifacts. Although controversies rage about the ownership of artifacts, treasures, and human remains recovered, thousands of archaeologists still operate around the world at excavations sites, in museums, and on university campuses. These men and women work to undercover the common beliefs and daily activities of various peoples throughout history, furthering our understanding of our own history.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_ARCHER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Another hunting tool that proved very effective for killing other people, the bow as a weapon was perhaps first used in the Paleolithic Era. Archery was likely developed in several places more-or-less simultaneously, and except for Australia, it was used on every continent by all sorts of primitives. Until the advent of gunpowder, and even after in some cases, it was the primary light projectile weapon. Not much good for melee though; therefore archers were usually integrated or protected by heavier infantry, the first combined-arms formations in the history of warfare. Over centuries, archers became more specialized, eventually requiring years to become experts at their craft. But most civilizations had elite archery units that could dominate a battlefield under the proper conditions – such as against mired heavy knights at Agincourt, or bare-chested berserkers at Stamford Bridge, or the misguided troopers of the Seventh Cavalry at the Little Big Horn.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_ARTILLERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Field cannons have come a long way since Gustavus Adolphus introduced them, evolving into field artillery of all sorts, small and large. In point of fact, any mechanism capable of throwing or firing a rock or shell is “artillery,” but the term is generally used to refer to large, breech-loading cannon with rifled barrels to improve accuracy. With the advances in metallurgy and industrial production available, and the Crimean War showing the deficiencies of the decrepit British cannons, a government contract was awarded to William Armstrong to design a suitable replacement. The result of his engineering was the first modern artillery piece in 1855 AD, capable of both direct and indirect fire. In 1897 the French improved on the design, producing the French 75, perhaps the most ubiquitous artillery piece in history. The guns have gotten bigger, more reliable, more accurate, more deadly – and the generals more pleased – as the years have passed since.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_AT_CREW_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Although the first appearance of tanks on the battlefield was hardly auspicious, by the end of WW1 it had become obvious that something needed to be done to keep them from grinding one’s infantry underfoot. By the opening of WW2, most countries’ arsenals included some small-caliber (none larger than 50mm) artillery pieces designed to punch through the armor plating of armored vehicles, causing havoc within for the crew, engine, and/or ammunition. But with the advances in tank design and tactics, Germany and then Britain created increasingly larger anti-tank guns, manned by a crew of stalwarts … for, since they had to be in the open to operate the gun, the crewmen were vulnerable to just about everything flying about the field. By the end of the war, the Germans relied on their famed 88mm gun, the Americans had 105s, and the Russians were using 122mm howitzers firing over open sights.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_BATTERING_RAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As the walls protecting towns got higher and thicker, so too did the gates. Eventually, it wasn’t enough to have a bunch of expendables hammering away at the gate carrying a thick pole. In its simplest form, a battering ram is a heavy log suspended from a framework that can be swung against walls and gates, eventually – theoretically – knocking them down. Over time, the ends were capped with metal, wheels were added for mobility, and coverings protected the users from boiling oil, rocks, arrows and other discomforts. So useful were battering rams that, if they couldn’t be constructed from materials nearby, ancient armies would drag them along on campaigns. Pliny the Elder even described their use in mining for breaking down hard rock (although a bunch of slaves with picks was a lot cheaper). Battering rams were used right through the Middle Ages, until the advent of gunpowder brought cannons into the art of war.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_BATTLESHIP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The evolution of the dreadnought that dominated the waves of the early 20th Century was the battleship … bigger, faster, with bigger guns and thicker armor, able to sink anything else (including each other) afloat with a single salvo. The first “true” battleships to see action appeared at Jutland in 1916 AD, where – mixed with a motley collection of dreadnoughts and battle-cruisers – the German and British ones fought to a draw. In the inter-war years, the battleship evolved into the behemoth of popular thought, despite the Washington Naval Treaty of 1922 and other bits of international paper that tried to limit their size and armament. Not only was WW2 the golden age of the battleship – and all the best known sailed those troubled times: Bismarck, Hood, Arizona, Yamato, and Missouri among many others – it also witnessed its demise. By the end warplanes, submarines, radar-guided missiles and other technological marvels had relegated battleships to floating shore batteries and rusting tourist attractions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_BIPLANE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Before WW1, the airplane was a clever curiosity for getting grown men excited. Airplanes were fragile, underpowered (gliding as much as flying), clumsy, limited in distance and payload, expensive, and generally biplanes, since two wings served better than one for maneuverability and lift in the face of all these limitations. By the end of WW1, the airplane was a dreaded machine of war, able to spot enemy movement at a distance and then rain destruction down upon it. The biplanes of the 1914-1918 conflict became ever-more specialized as the war progressed, from the nimble fighters to the dependable recon planes to the lumbering bombers soon flying over enemy cities dropping explosives on civilians. By the end of the war, however, the wood-and-fabric biplanes were disappearing, being replaced by metal covered, single-wing craft capable of better speed and faster climb. But by then, the exploits of heroic, gallant men in their brightly-painted biplanes had already entered the psyche of war.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_BOMBARD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The oldest representation of a bombard – a muzzle-loading, smoothbore proto-mortar that was used to throw stone balls against fortifications during sieges – was found in China; the 12th Century AD Buddhist cave-sculpture depicts a demon firing one. In the Western world, English monarchs were certainly using them in the 14th Century, for Edward III had some at Crécy in 1346 and Henry V captured Harfleur using bombards in 1415. But with the largest weighing several tons and all notably inaccurate, bombards were not practical for field operations, soon enough being replaced by cannon; emplaced bombards, however, remained in use for centuries, usually protecting ports and sea passages. Among the last and largest, the Dardanelles Gun built by Munir Ali in 1464 weighted in at 16.8 tons and helped protect the straits for the Ottomans for a long, long time (being fired for the last time at a British fleet in 1807).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_BOMBER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Raining destruction down from a great height is enjoyable, especially if punishment is unlikely … just ask any misbehaving urchin over an ant hill. Although some tried using dirigibles and zeppelins as long-range bombers during WW1, these had some definite disadvantages – notably that they tended to blow up when struck by a bullet. So, even before that war, several aircraft designers had turned their attention to creating heavier-than-air craft that could carry loads of bombs over enemy lines to strike at their heart; the first two airplanes built solely for bombing were the Italian Caproni and the British Bristol, both debuting in 1913 AD. By the end of WW1, bombers for both tactical (battlefield) and strategic (urban) use had seen action on every front. These lumbering biplanes were gradually replaced during the inter-war years by faster, heavily armed, sturdy, and long-ranging monoplanes capable of crossing oceans. Now both sides could engage in “terror bombing,” putting civilians in the heart of the action, such as the German “blitz” on London or the American firebombing of Japanese cities. And it all culminated with a pair of bomber crews dropping atomic bombs.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_BRAZILIAN_MINAS_GERAES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Intended to be the first step in Brazil becoming an international power, the Minas Geraes-class were two battleships of 11,800-tons launched in the early 20th Century. While these didn’t do much in making Brazil a power to be reckoned with, the Minas Geraes and sister ship São Paulo did start a South American naval arms race, and caused quite a stir in the United States and United Kingdom (who weren’t real keen on having battleships in South American waters that weren’t theirs). The design plans for the new class took two years to complete, and then were tossed when the new HMS Dreadnought launched in 1906 made them obsolete. Finally the keels of the new design were laid down, and in September 1908 the Minas Geraes launched, followed by the São Paulo in 1909. Their careers weren’t much to speak of – centerpieces in suppressing a naval mutiny and a couple of rebellions. And they met an ignominious end; the Minas Geraes was scrapped in 1950, and the São Paulo sank en route to the scrapyard in 1951.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_BUILDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Every era has had the men and women who lay the foundations … the farms, fences, mines, roads, bridges, ditches, and all the rest that add up to “civilization.” Whether slaves, wage-slaves, contractors, or actually working for themselves, these “builders” spread out into the wilderness and tame it, making it productive and profitable. Then they keep it all running and in repair. No civilization can survive without these men and women (and children, at least until the early 20th century). While technology and machinery has certainly helped, the work of all this building and maintaining the infrastructure of a nation is still demanding, dirty, and dangerous; in 2013 AD, there were 828 fatalities in the construction industry in the United States, and 46 in the United Kingdom.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_CARAVEL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As Iñigo Arieta, the Spanish commander who escorted Columbus to sea in 1492 AD, put it, caravels were “corredoras extremadas, buenas para descubrir tierras.” The Nina and the Pinta were caravels, and Columbus praised the Nina for its maneuverability, speed and safety. Developed in the 15th Century and used extensively in the 16th, the caravel was a speedy sailing ship with lateen-rigged main- and mizzen-mast, sloping bow and high stern castle. It appears that the classic (there was a lot of variation) caravel design was a melding of an earlier Iberian fishing vessel and the Arab qarib plying the Mediterranean. Small, light and shallow-drafted compared to other sailing ships, it was perfect for exploring all those coasts and rivers the Europeans were finding during the Age of Exploration. Likely the first vision unenlightened savages had of European culture was a caravel looming out of the darkling mist. After the explorers came the conquistadors, priests, adventurers, traders and eventually settlers … and so the unpretentious little caravel spread civilization round the globe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_CATAPULT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>No one is quite sure when or where someone figured out it was a lot easier to use a machine to hurl a big rock, but it is known that the Greeks were using catapults as early as the 3rd Century BC. In point of fact, the term catapult comes from the Greek for “downwards” and “to toss.” Catapults use tension in a twisted rope and/or bent wooden cross-arms to throw missiles a fair distance; since they are relatively inaccurate, catapults worked best against large, slow-moving targets (such as towns and forts). As history progressed, catapults were constructed such as to be able to be transported in pieces and assembled before a battle or siege. The last time they were used in warfare was during the early stage of WW1, when the French used them to launch grenades at the German trenches. Nowadays, they are used just for hurling pumpkins and other edibles in annual competitions among geeks.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_CAVALRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Technically, any unit that fought from horseback (or these days motorized or even helicopter transport) – archers, knights, lancers, dragoons, hussars, uhlans, cossacks, cuirassiers, etc. – is considered “cavalry.” But when the common sort think of the term, they envision sabre- and rifle-armed bravadoes mounted on magnificent steeds … the most mobile and noble (a misperception left over from the Age of Chivalry) of the traditional military branches. By the time of the Seven Years and Napoleonic wars, the standard cavalry were increasingly armed with pistols, sabres and small rifles, and thus able to fight either dismounted or from horseback. Speedy and maneuverable, they served as reconnaissance and raiding units, battlefield stalwarts, and pursuers of the defeated. Able to ride down the enemy under suitable conditions or gallantly run away when not, cavalry served in every military campaign through WW2, when horse-borne cavalry had its last hurrah.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_CHINESE_CROUCHING_TIGER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>After the Chinese discovered gunpowder c. 9th Century AD, they used it just for fireworks and making pretty, colorful explosions. But eventually someone figured out it was pretty useful in warfare too, and soon enough flintlocks and cannon were all the rage in Asia. According to Dr. Yongxiang Lu, the little-known Chinese “Crouching Tiger” lay somewhere between a bombard and a cannon, one of the earliest uses of gunpowder in warfare. A crude device, it was basically an iron tube, sealed at one end, wrapped with thick ropes to reinforce it and with two short legs at the front to elevate the barrel slightly (so the shot didn’t plow up the ground instead of smashing the enemy). It is known that the Crouching Tiger saw action c. 1368 at the beginning of the Ming dynasty, and was still being used as late as 1592 against the Japanese in Korea. When fired, it is reported to have had a range of about 800 paces, which no doubt made the enemy very uncomfortable since it outranged anything else at the time.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_CROSSBOWMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The crossbow – easier to master than the bow and hence perfect for peasants, who really didn’t have much time to practice archery – is in essence a small, heavy bow set crossways on a mechanism for drawing and releasing a short arrow (termed a bolt or quarrel). Invented in eastern China, it is first recorded in use during the aptly-named Warring States Period, c. 4th Century BC. The famed Sun Tzu devoted no less than two chapters in his influential 'Art of War' to the use of the crossbow. Around the same time, a sort of crossbow ancestor made its appearance in Greece, and the Romans may have used a few. But it is during the Middle Ages that the crossbow dominated the European battlefield. Combined with pikemen, another weapon that didn’t require a lot of skill to use, massed crossbowmen could turn aside almost any threat. The only downside to the crossbow was the skill necessary to construct one. But, until the advent of muskets, it was the best thing available to those unruly peasants.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_DESTROYER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Originally developed in the late 19th Century to keep those annoying torpedo boats away from the dreadnoughts and first seeing action during the Russo-Japanese War in 1904, destroyers have come to fulfill many duties for the world’s navies: patrol, escort, anti-air, and anti-submarine. The first ships to be designated “torpedo boat destroyer” (TBD or simply “destroyer”) were the six of the British Royal Navy’s Daring class (1892) and Havock class (1893) and Ferret class (1894); with light armor, displacing under 300 tons, armed with a single 12-pounder and several smaller guns and with one or more torpedo tubes, soon enough other navies copied the design. Tasked with screening friendly ships and attacking enemy ones, destroyers served throughout WW1 and proved especially effective against submarines stalking merchant shipping. By WW2, destroyers were even faster, more maneuverable, carrying enough ordnance and supplies for long-range missions; in both oceans they were to be the workhorses of the contending navies. Since, the 1960s guided-missile destroyers have been added to the mix.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_EGYPTIAN_CHARIOT_ARCHER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The maryannu (the singular form marya, meaning “young warrior” or “youthful hero”) was a hereditary caste of chariot-mounted nobility, found in several societies in Bronze Age Middle East. In Egypt, they rode in two-man light chariots, which offered a more stable base for archery than did horseback, given the length of the bows common at the time. And the marya could carry more ammunition. But there were some significant disadvantages for the young heroes such as the limitations of terrain and the maintenance of the vehicle and horses on long campaigns. Nonetheless, the maryannu were a powerful elite in the pharaoh’s army; the best record of their effectiveness in battle is at Kadesh, c. 1274 BC, where they carried the day for Ramesses II. There are lots of images left behind depicting the ancient Egyptian maryannu chariots (one of the indelible images of that civilization), and six well-preserved specimens were found in the tomb of Tutankhamun (who passed over around 1323 BC).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_ENGLISH_REDCOAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The red (or, more accurately, the shade rose madder) coat of the British infantry evolved from the ceremonial uniforms of the early 1600s; it was officially adopted in February 1645 AD when Parliament drafted the regulations for the New Model Army, with the 12 regiments of foot all wearing red coats with different colored facings to distinguish between them. For the next quarter-millennia most of the British infantry wore such, making them splendid targets among the trees, dunes, jungles and hills of the Empire. The rationale for such a choice was that, despite the fiction it was because bloodstains were disheartening for the men, red coats were instantly identifiable on the field, and hence helped maintain order and morale. The term “redcoat” became a source of pride for the British, and a curse word for just about everyone else.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_ENGLISH_SEADOG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Heroic privateers to the English, pirates to everyone else. From 1560 to 1605 AD, Elizabeth I gave permission to her “Sea Dogs” to attack the ships and colonies of other nations – especially the Spanish – at will, usually without the nicety of being at war. The likes of Sir John Hawkins and Sir Francis Drake and Sir Walter Raleigh (in fact, many of these pirates were knighted) raided across the Caribbean and even reached the California coast to ply their bloody trade: grabbing as much treasure as they could for the English crown … and themselves of course.  In England’s hour of greatest need, the Sea Dogs spearheaded Elizabeth’s defense against the Spanish Armada in 1588. Hawkins is also known as the pioneer of the British slave trade, and Drake took part in the Rathlin Island Massacre of some 600 men, women, and children off the coast of Ireland.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_FIELD_CANNON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Field cannon – the earliest form of mobile gunpowder artillery – dates back to the wars of Gustavus Adolphus, a bastardization of the Ottoman hand cannon and the heavy siege artillery used throughout Europe. The Swedish king needed increased mobility and devastation from his guns if he was going to conquer the north, and so he developed 4- and 9-pounder demi-culverins and a 12-pounder cannon (the traditional method of distinguishing type of cannon is by weight of shot); each gun was able to be serviced by three men and hauled by two horses. He also organized them into batteries, rather than scatter them about through the ranks. And the Swedes pioneered several types of specialized ammunition, including canister for blasting massed enemy infantry. So effective was Adolphus’ field guns and his tactics for their use that soon enough every nation in Europe and beyond had adopted his innovations, and the art of war again changed dramatically.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_FIGHTER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>And fighters filled the skies … well, eventually. Fighter aircraft were developed during WW1 to counter the dirigibles, balloons, recon, and bomber aircraft that populated the skies above the battlefield. Small, slow, fragile, and lightly armed by later standards, these first fighters – the original “pursuit” pilots used everything from grenades to grappling hooks to try to bring down enemy craft – were made effective in the role of killer when the 'stangensteuerung' (interrupter) gear was designed by Anthony Fokker in 1915 and fitted to the German Eindecker, making it the most feared fighter at the time. By the end of the war, thousands of fighters had taken to the sky … and been shot down by the hundreds. In WW2, fighters were generally metal monoplanes, and tasked with all sorts of things: strafing and bombing ground targets, interdicting or protecting bombers, patrolling over vital things, reconnaissance missions, and of course, shooting each other down. Modern jet fighters are even faster and more heavily armed than those vintage WW2 warbirds, but the missions haven’t changed much.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_FRENCH_GARDE_IMPERIALE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>From a small cadre of veterans under the direct command of Napoléon Bonaparte, formed in 1799 from the union of the Guard of the Directory and the Grenadiers of the Legislature (both of those effete democratic bodies soon enough done away with by the emperor), the Garde Impériale grew during the Napoleonic Wars to be a division strong. The Garde was divided into three echelons depending on experience: the Old, the Middle and the Young. Napoleon favored his Garde, giving them higher pay as well as better rations, equipment, and living quarters. Nonetheless, the Old Guard were outspoken in their complaints, often directly to Napoleon himself, earning them the nickname les Grognards (“the grumblers”) among the rest of the French troops. Serving in every campaign during the wars, at Waterloo they were committed in desperation to secure a victory, but the Middle Guard retreated (for the first and only time) under withering fire; the Old Guard and some Young Guard units stood their ground to cover the Emperor’s withdrawal, only to be virtually annihilated by the British and Prussian cannon. Thus came to an inglorious end the most elite (according to the French and to wargame designers) of all military units in history.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_FRIGATE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Over the centuries the frigate has evolved from a square-rigged three-master in the 1700s too small to stand in the line-of-battle to the fast guided-missile toting warship, nimble enough to avoid the really big ships. But the role of the frigate in naval warfare hasn’t changed: patrol and/or escort duties. The British Royal Navy declared a frigate to be any full-rigged “rated ship” carrying at least 28 guns on a single continuous deck; but despite the Admiralty’s best efforts to define a “frigate,” these came in all sizes and configurations, even ironclads by the mid-1800s. Modern “frigates” are frigates in name only; commencing with WW2, the label was applied to anything smaller than a destroyer. The introduction of missiles to modern naval warfare made frigates even more lethal, and cost-effective. Why build a blundering great battleship, or even a cruiser or destroyer, when a “cheap” frigate would do?</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_GALLEY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>With a shallow draft, slender hull, minimal decking, and propelled by oars, the galley was the first boat (or ship, if grandiose) dedicated to warfare. Although most had sails on a single mast that could help, galleys were propelled primarily by human sweat. Galleys tended to stay in shallower waters near shore, not being particularly seaworthy. But these were the mainstay of the early Phoenician, Greek, Carthaginian and Roman navies in the Mediterranean … as well as barbarian pirates everywhere. Initially carrying just archers and spearmen for floating melee battles, eventually rams, catapults and even cannon were added to their armaments, making them useful even into the early Medieval Era. But in time the galley – and all its descendants, the biremes, triremes, dromons, etc. – were made obsolete by the more maneuverable (and bigger) sailing warships. And those didn’t need a bunch of sweaty and grumbling oarsmen.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_GERMAN_UBOAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The 'Unterseeboot' – U-boat – struck fear, and anger, in the hearts of Germany’s enemies during two world wars. The first German-built submarine, the 26-foot long Brandtaucher (“fire-diver”), sank during its initial test dive in the harbor at Kiel. This was followed by several submersibles built in Germany, which were sold to the Greeks, Ottomans, and Russians (all had rather ignominious careers). Finally the Germans got it right; the U-19 – they finally quit giving the boats names – was launched in 1912 with two-stroke diesel engines, four torpedo tubes and two deck guns, and able to dive to 164 feet. At the opening of WW1, Germany had 28 U-boats in service; in the first ten weeks, these sank five British cruisers. So effective were the U-boats that the Treaty of Versailles forbade the construction of German submarines. But, the U-boat fleet was rebuilt, and by the end of WW2 the boats had sunk some 2779 ships (confirmed) totaling 14.1 million tons – roughly 70% of Allied losses in all theaters. In 1955 West Germany was allowed to have a navy again … and promptly started building U-boats, the latest being the non-nuclear U-35, commissioned in March 2015.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_GREAT_ADMIRAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Some are born with salt water in their veins, and so take to a life at sea. In the past, these were the “great” admirals, leading voyages of exploration, trading shots across the bow with other warships, and terrorizing innocent merchant vessels. Once men found that they could sail across open water and not (usually) drown, ships of all sorts took to the shallow and deep seas. Yi Sun Shin, Cristoforo Colombo, Horatio Nelson, Isoroku Yamamoto, David Farragut, and the list goes on of those who made a name for themselves at sea. Thanks in large part to their efforts, the world shrank and civilization expanded. But, maybe they had no choice. As Jacques Yves Cousteau (who would have been a heck of an admiral if he were so inclined) wrote: “The sea, once it casts its spell, holds one in its net of wonder forever.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_GREAT_ARTIST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Artists are the visionaries of civilization. They daub paint on canvas or chip away at stone, and leave it to others to find vision and meaning therein. They interpret the world and give beauty, brilliance, form, and color to the mundane; these are those who paint the pictures, carve the statues, take the photos, and make the films that define and reinforce our humanity. Sometimes they are appreciated in their lifetime; usually, not. Sometimes they make a living with their art; usually, not. However, the work of these artists can, occasionally, surpass its time and place, enlightening and elevating a people, making a civilization far greater than its material wealth and worldly power.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_GREAT_WRITER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Great writers are those men and women who express our desires, insights, fancies, foibles, fears, and joys in the written word. History has been marked by their voices; indeed, “history” is one of their voices. Whether in poetry, in novels and stories, for the stage or screen, these are the artists who have defined their civilizations and cultures. Some write prose and poetry about imaginary worlds; others write tracts of philosophy, politics, religion, and science about how our world is or should be. And let’s not forget those who put down facts on paper. Whatever their muse, whatever their intent, their words echo through time, binding us all together ... or sometimes setting us all apart.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_GREAT_MUSICIAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>It has been said that “music is the soul of a people.” If that is indeed the case, then “great musicians” are the guardians of that soul. Whatever the form, whatever the beat, whatever the instruments, no other art speaks to our emotions like music. Since it does, it is also the most subjective of the arts; what is heavenly harmony to one is just a cacophony of noise to another. That rather broadens the definition of what is “great” music; perhaps the best way to judge this “greatness” is how long a piece has continued to be played and appreciated by others. But from the time that men first beat out a rhythm on logs to the modern electronic orchestra, great composers and performers have expressed the collective sorrows and joys of each civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_GREAT_ENGINEER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Engineers design and build workshops, schools, and homes; “great” engineers design and build wonders. Before the day of pre-fab buildings, uniform ticky-tack housing “estates,” stressed concrete and I-beam girders, these were the men (and women) who celebrated civilization in towering monuments, grand palaces, massive temples, vital dams and bridges, and structures of every kind. It’s their work that archaeologists dig up, tourists gawk at, and children learn about in school. Give thanks too for the indoor plumbing, electrical lights, and autobahns (along with everything else that makes life comfortable) that they designed and built. Without the great engineers dreaming in stone and steel, constructing skyscrapers, giving the world sports stadiums and shopping malls, how else would anyone even know civilization when they stumbled out of the wilderness?</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_GREAT_GENERAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Every age of civilization has had its “great” generals, those who change the course of history by being cleverer, braver, or simply luckier than their peers across the battlefield. These are the men who can convince other men to follow them into hell … and perhaps out the other side. They are innovators in the ways of death, inventing new weapons, formations, tactics and strategies to win wars. Or finding new benefits in the old ways of killing. Every person reading this can name dozens of great generals, for their names echo down to us in legends, histories and monuments. Some are leaders of their people, warrior-kings and president-generals; if not already the head of the government while becoming “great,” they are often awarded (or cursed with) that mantle afterward. And then they write their memoirs, provided they survive their wars.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_GREAT_MERCHANT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Of the four things that determine the course of civilization, greed is probably the most pervasive. Once folk settled and started farming and mining, there was always someone who found that others wanted what they had in plenty, and were willing to pay for it. And so merchants fanned out across the globe, trading in everything from grain to gold, hemp to human beings. The most adventurous among these were always seeking new markets, and hence were explorers who brought back knowledge of distant peoples and customs. Some of the greatest discoveries were the product of the greed of these adventurers. Their travels also enriched their nations in more material ways, for the taxes and profits from their trips funded great works of engineering, education, colonization, art, and war. Without the great merchants, civilization would have been much poorer.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_GREAT_PROPHET_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Holy men are common; “great” prophets somewhat less so. Some prophets have “visions”; others just have insights into life, the way it should be lived and how we might be better. Some wander and teach, while others build temples and churches. And some just have good public relations. Whatever the foundation, these are the ones who create religions, spread the faith, or challenge the beliefs of others … sometimes all three. They warn mankind about his hubris in thinking he can know everything or control anything. Every great religion has its great prophets, no matter how or what they worship, those who have been touched by the divine … and each one has altered the course of civilization as profoundly as any general, scientist, artist, or leader.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_GREAT_SCIENTIST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Great scientists try to offer innovative and insightful notions of how the world does work … as opposed to philosophers and prophets who offer thoughts on how the world should work. In some cases, the lines between these – especially as the notion of directed mutagenesis, quantum physics, asymptotic math, and other theoretical constructs take hold – can be very thin indeed. One of mankind’s best, or worst, attributes is curiosity, and this is something great scientists have in plenty. They pry into everything natural and unnatural, and the results of their “scientific method” can be a boon or a curse, and often both, to their fellows. Despite the academic arcade that issues advanced degrees in every scientific cul-de-sac possible and the monolithic corporate research institutes (for these days science is a lucrative business), there is still room for the occasional great scientist to come along and change everything yet again.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_GREEK_HOPLITE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Give a bunch of citizen-soldiers ten-foot iron-headed spears (called doru), put them in a tight formation shoulder-to-shoulder, and the hoplite phalanx appears. In the 8th or 7th century BC, the Greek city-states first began to raise hoplite units – composed of those “free” citizens who could afford the bronze armor and the doru – for fighting among themselves. As the Persians found out, hoplite phalanxes were pretty effective against others as well. Although enemy archers might pick off a few (most of the arrows of the time were too light to penetrate the bronzewear of the Greeks), a phalanx of hoplites could generally sweep everything from the field in front of them; the greatest threat came from exposing their flanks, or losing formation moving over rough ground. The hoplite-phalanx survived for almost 400 years, through the age of Alexander the Great still dominant, until it came up against the Roman legion, faster afoot, more flexible in formation, and more adept with their short swords once they slipped past those unwieldy spears.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_HEAVY_CHARIOT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Ox carts – sort of proto-chariots – were first built by early Indo-European peoples in Mesopotamia around 3000 BC. Not long after, c. 2500, horses were domesticated on the Eurasian steppes, a practice that quickly spread. And not long after that, horses got hitched (usually side-by-side) to the carts, which had been made lighter – often just a platform on two wheels with a low railing – and more maneuverable. Besides practical uses for chariots in transport and racing, chariots were very useful in war, giving ancient armies a mobile arm of their military. The Hittites were the first master charioteers in warfare, manned by three men in nimble chariots drawn by two horses. The Egyptians ran roughshod over their enemies using a similar contraption. The Persians were the first to build heavy chariots, with a four-horse team and sometimes scythes on the wheels, which proved really effective in smashing through enemy infantry lines.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_HELICOPTER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Chinese children played with them c. 400 BC; da Vinci designed one in the early 1480s; the Frenchman d’Amécourt demonstrated a steam-powered aluminum one in 1861 (although it never got off the ground); in 1907 two Frenchmen, the Breguet brothers, finally built an engine-powered helicopter which lifted its pilot two feet off the ground. And in 1933 the German Focke-Wulf company designed and built the world’s first twin-rotor helicopter, intending it for military use, even as Igor Sikorsky was doing the same in the United States. Used rarely during WW2, the helicopter was primarily employed as transport in the Korean War, and finally as gunships during the Vietnam War. Able to hug the terrain and avoid detection (until too late) by flying “nap-of-the-earth,” during the Cold War it became the primary “tank-buster” in both the U.S. and USSR armies. Today, helicopters are as useful as they are ubiquitous in military operations, doing everything from recon, to medivac, to troop insertion and recovery, to providing close air support with guns and missiles.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_HORSEMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Before the Iron Age, the role of horsemen was largely filled by light chariots, useful both for reconnaissance and in battle. Though occasionally used by commanders and couriers, the horses of the age were too small to carry much weight and were damn expensive. Around 2000 BC, however, those living in the Central Asian steppes domesticated and cultivated larger, stockier, and hardier breeds. Armed with spears, swords and eventually bows, these horsemen generally raised hell … and changed the face of warfare. Soon enough the Greeks to the west and Chinese to the east adapted mounted warriors for their own purposes, then everyone around did as well. But it was the development of the stirrup attached to a sturdy saddle that made horsemen the dominant shock weapon on the battlefield; the earliest saddles with stirrups date from c. 300 AD, and over the next four centuries the innovation spread across Asia and into Europe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_INDIAN_VARU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Although not the most reliable of battle-mounts (as apt to trample friendly troops as enemy when panicked), war elephants were a staple in Indian warfare for centuries until the advent of gunpowder. In pre-gunpowder combat, the 'vāru' (“royal elephant”) served two purposes. Their scent tended to terrify horses, thus rendering the enemy cavalry relatively useless. Second, they could usually break through even the strongest line of infantry, especially if armored, crushing spearmen and archers and everything else in their path (and reaching 25 kph on the run). Too, elephants were notoriously hard to kill, and there are records of them surviving as many as sixty arrows. Usually surmounted with a howdah or other platform for archers, the vāru could wade right into the fray. But, in case the elephants did go berserk and start squashing their own side, the driver carried a spike and mallet to kill them with a blow to the skull.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_INFANTRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As the first half of the 20th Century moved forward, two of the most destructive wars in civilization, marked by remarkable advancements in the technology of killing each other, occurred. Through it all, the infantryman marched into battle, grimly facing every horror – machine guns, mines, gas, strafing and bombing from the air, and all the rest out of Pandora’s Box – that the greatest scientists of the age could invent. The task of the foot soldiers hadn’t changed much since the spearmen and swordsmen of antiquity: take and/or hold whatever ground the generals decided was important. But the infantryman’s own bag of tricks became ever more lethal, with magazine-fed rifles, automatic pistols, submachine guns, flamethrowers, grenades and all sorts of other clever devices. Since armor didn’t stop such, it was discarded for mobility and camouflage. By the end of WW2, infantry could hold their own against most any threat … provided enough of them survived.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_INQUISITOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Every faith has its inquisitors, those charged by the church to find the non-believers, back-sliders, and evil influences among the flock. But it is in Europe that the role reached its apex, as the Catholic Church during the Medieval and the Renaissance periods strove to insure the Jews, Moslems, and Protestants (not to mention scientists, artists, and philosophers) didn’t corrupt the faithful. The Catholic inquisitors were on the front lines in this struggle, as they banned and burned books, and disposed of heretics, all in the name of the Lord. In some cases, with the support of the secular government, as in Isabella’s Spain or the Holy Roman Empire, all made legal by the papal bull 'Ad extirpanda' in 1252 AD. Despite some excesses it can be said that inquisitors did keep the faith – whichever faith it may be.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_IRONCLAD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The best-known clash between ironclads – those steam-propelled, lumbering behemoths covered by iron or steel plating – at Hampton Roads in May 1862 AD ended in a draw. The CSS Virginia had earlier wreaked havoc on the Union’s traditional warships there, and while there was a lot of fighting still to come, the age of wood and sail in warfare was doomed. But the American ironclads weren’t very seaworthy, and tended to sink in open water. The British Royal Navy built the first classes of “seagoing ironclads” (actually armored, iron-hulled frigates) in the early 1860s, and soon enough they added steam-engine driven screws to the designs. Seeing how the Virginia had handled wooden warships far larger, every nation scrambled to build ironclads. The first fleet action fought on the open water between ironclads was near the island of Lissa in the Adriatic between the Austrian and Italian navies; of the 19 ironclads involved, two went to the bottom. But, like that battle, the age of the ironclad didn’t last long.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_JAPANESE_SAMURAI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Until the ‘ashigaru’ (peasant) infantry were armed with muskets, the samurai (“those who serve in close attendance”) dominated warfare and politics in Japan for nearly a thousand years. Although the roots lie in the Nara period, it was during the Heian period c. 800 AD that bushido (“the way of the warrior”) was codified and a number of noble clans adopted its philosophies. By the time of the Heiji Rebellion of 1160, the samurai clans dominated the landscape, with various factions fighting over the shogunate, defeating the Mongol invasion, and otherwise building an impressive historical legacy of fact and myth. Throughout the Edo period, Japan was unified and at peace, and so the samurai became refined - writing poetry, trimming bonsai, and occasionally practicing ritualistic suicide (seppuku) when dishonored. Unfortunately, the Emperor Meiji instituted a number of reforms in 1868 – including the end of the shogunate and abolition of the samurai class.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_JET_BOMBER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As fighters got faster and more lethal, for a brief period jet bombers were considered necessary by Cold War air forces … until intercontinental ballistic nuclear missiles promised the ability to rain destruction on distant cities with less fuss. The United States designed the XB-70 Valkyrie, for instance, to carry nuclear warheads across the pole to Russia – only two were ever built. The B-1 Lancer was somewhat more successful; with a speed of Mach-2 it could (hopefully) outrun the nuclear blast so the crew might survive – about 100 of the B-1B version were put in service as “low-level penetrators.” But in general, the old B-52s and Soviet Su series worked just as well (although their attack would be a one-way trip), and were a lot cheaper. In modern air forces, the distinctions between bombers, fighter-bombers and fighters have blurred considerably, such that most aircraft in service today could be considered “jet bombers.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_JET_FIGHTER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The best propeller-driven fighters of the World War II era could fly about (at best) 650 kilometers per hour (400 mph) and could carry one or two machine guns, and perhaps a small bomb or rocket or two. The Germans decided this wasn’t enough to stop the Allied bomber fleets, and so they developed the first operational “jet” – the Messerschmitt 262. While it didn’t change the course of this war, it did for all those afterward. With the obvious success of the Me-262 (although it did tend to occasionally blow up), after the war everyone started designing and building new fighter jets: British Meteor, American F-86, Russian MiG-15. By the end of the Korean War, jet fighters formed the backbone of every major air force. At the time of the Vietnam War, jet fighters could carry a couple 20mm cannon, ten or so missiles, and dozens of rockets and bombs, as well as reach supersonic speeds.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_KNIGHT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the Middle Ages, a knight was usually the wastrel son of a noble family who, having served his apprenticeship in war as a page and squire, had been raised to honorable rank and bound to chivalrous conduct (more an ideal than a practice). Since the mounts and accoutrements and life-style of a knight were extremely expensive, it just wasn’t for the commoners (they got to be foot-soldiers). The knightly tradition arose from the Roman equites, an equestrian order that comprised the lower of the two aristocratic ranks of the Empire. Through the Dark Ages (and slightly beyond) knights dominated the open battlefield, able to trample the fleeing commoners. Unfortunately, not many battles were fought on dry, open ground. Too, eventually the unchivalrous commoners were armed with pikes and longbows, the bane of mounted knights. And so the day of the knight passed away, despite those archaic “knightly” orders still scattered about.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_KONGO_SHIELD_BEARER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Kingdom of Kongo’s “army” was a mass (or mess) of archers with a smaller contingent of heavy infantry, which carried swords and shields. The colonial Portuguese referred to the latter in their accounts as adagueiros (“shield-bearers”) while in the few surviving native documents the Swahili term ngao mbeba is used. While the archers were militia conscripts in time of war, there is some evidence that the standing ngao mbeba were supported by stipends from the king. Perhaps as many as 20 thousand were garrisoned in the capital, with smaller contingents in the provinces under the command of the local authority. Under king Afonso I, a small unit of Portuguese-armed native musketmen was raised, and eventually the old shield-bearers were replaced by the deadlier youngsters.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_MACHINE_GUN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since the days of the arquebus innovative gunsmiths had sought for a rapid-fire firearm that required little training or skill to use. Stoper’s revolving arquebus in 1597 Nuremberg, the “Puckle Gun” in 1718 in London, Belton’s multi-shot flintlock in 1777 all had their proponents; but it was left to Richard Jordan Gatling to perfect an infantry weapon with controlled rapid fire, automatic loading, portability, speedy reloading of ammunition canisters, and operated by a simple hand-crank. The Gatling gun was immensely popular among military types of all nations, and it laid the foundation for the development of the machinegun, which stalemated WW1 and dominated WW2 infantry combat. In time, the weight was reduced without loss of rate of fire, machineguns becoming submachineguns (such as the Thompson so beloved of Prohibition-era gangsters) capable of being fired from the hip.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_MECHANIZED_INFANTRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>With the coming of the gasoline engine to the battlefield, and all those tanks and trucks zipping about, the foot-slogging infantry had trouble keeping pace. Between the world wars, various nations studied how this could be improved. But it was Nazi Germany, with its emphasis on blitzkrieg, that devoted the most attention to “mechanizing” the infantry to keep up with their panzers before they tore across Poland, France, North Africa and Russia. Since trucks couldn’t quickly traverse the sort of ground encountered in these places, the German engineers had designed the first half-track (the Sd.Kfz 251) to carry infantry and their supplies while keeping up with the tanks. Add in some tracked artillery and AA guns, and one had an independent battlegroup, capable of holding its own against anything the enemy had. So successful were the Germans that every other combatant emulated them, to the point where most infantry today are “mechanized.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_MEDIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>It takes a brave person to rush onto a battlefield unarmed, especially to provide trauma care in the front lines. Although “protected” by age-old edicts and the Geneva Convention, being a military medic is not conducive to good health. Surgeon Dominique Larrey developed the first ambulances volantes (“flying ambulance”) – mobile field hospitals – for Napoleon’s Grande Armée; he also recruited and trained volunteers to aid the wounded and carry them back to the field hospitals. Not only did it improve the survival rate – which certainly boosted morale – but it insured that at least some would survive to fight again. During the American Civil War, Major Jon Letterman of the U.S. Army of the Potomac not only developed and standardized new equipment for saving lives (this in an age when amputation was the usual cure), but expanded the medic’s role to dealing with diseases and other ills of the draftees. Today, army medics and naval corpsmen are integral to every nation’s military.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_MILITARY_ENGINEER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Military engineers – as opposed to “combat” engineers who are crazy enough to rush into battle carrying tools and explosives rather than weapons – are tasked with building fortifications and other structures and creating and maintaining lines of supply and communication. The most victorious armies of the past – Roman, Chinese, Ottoman, British, etc. – all had superior military engineering units, to which much of their success was owed, both for protecting their own troops and knocking down the enemy’s defenses. Just ask the Gauls at Alesia (52 BC) or the Zealots at Jerusalem (70 AD). Following the fall of Rome in the west, military engineering – like just about everything else – entered a “dark age,” not to be revived until the mid-Middle Ages, when once again sieges were prevalent. By the end of the age, military engineers were again an integral part of any victorious army. Throughout the Napoleonic, Crimean, various civil and world wars, military engineers were divided into ever-more specialties. These days, a military professional needs a degree in civil, electrical, mechanical, architectural or even environmental engineering to be given the chance to build things … or tear them down.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_MISSILE_CRUISER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term “cruiser” was first used in the mid-17th Century AD to refer to a warship that could operate independently of a fleet – fast enough to run away from anything with bigger guns and big enough to blast apart anything with smaller ones. During the next couple centuries these were often commerce raiders, and occasionally used in fleet actions to screen the main body. So they didn’t figure prominently in naval affairs … until the advent of long-range missiles. While a number of navies invested in the design and construction of missile cruisers during the Cold War (even the mighty Peruvian navy had one), only the Americans and Soviets have kept theirs afloat. The first of the U.S. Navy’s Ticonderoga-class cruisers was launched in 1981, arguably the most powerful vessels still in service, armed with 122 launch tubes with a staggering variety of surface-to-surface, surface-to-air, and anti-submarine missiles, thus able to kill just about anything.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_MISSIONARY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Inevitably, in every religion, there are those who “hear the word” and then go out to spread it. Throughout history, the preachers and proselytizers have gone abroad, often at great risk – hence, all those martyrs and saints - to convert the non-believers into their faith, whichever faith it may be. That is not to say that missionaries don’t also do good works of a more practical sort: schools to teach, clinics to heal, social welfare programs to support, thrift shops to cover, and all the other benefits of civilization. Whether with a sword or a smile, the primary goal of the missionary is to share their faith and so gain new faithful. Whereas they once actually had to go out on missions to do so, now they can tele-evangelize, which is so much more safe and comfortable.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_MOBILE_SAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Like all the neat weapon systems, the Germans were first with the idea for a surface-to-air missile; in 1941 AD Friederich Halder proposed a “flak rocket” to counter Allied bombers, but scientific infighting delayed any serious work until 1943, and although several prototype systems were developed none were ready for deployment by the end of World War II. Meanwhile, the U.S. Navy, spurred by the success of Nazi glide bombs and the Japanese kamikaze assaults, produced the SAM-N-2 Lark, a ramjet-powered antiaircraft missile for use at long distances … it too was operationally unused when the war ended. While the Allies puttered along with SAM designs, the Soviets created the S-75 Dvina, the first successful (it knocked down a Taiwanese bomber over China in October 1959) one. The Vietnam War was the first modern war in which SAMs figured prominently, leading to the “man-portable antiaircraft missile” (MANPADS), by the 1990s pervasive in guerilla and terrorist operations around the globe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_MODERN_ARMOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Modern armor is significantly better than those wonderful Panthers, T-34s, Cromwells and Shermans that tore things up during World War II. Today's main battle tanks (MBTs) are bigger, faster, have far better armor and weapons, and, perhaps most importantly, are provided with sophisticated computers and communications equipment which greatly improves their power and survivability on the modern battlefield. What an MBT cannot just blast apart it can run over. A modern tank can scream across the battlefield at 60 kilometers per hour while firing with pinpoint accuracy at a target hundreds of yards away, a targeting computer minutely adjusting the tank's barrel, compensating for each bump or pothole. Infantry rarely carry weapons strong enough to destroy thick-skinned modern armor – except of course, for their radios, which they can use to call in artillery or helicopter gunships. Unfortunately, MBTs don’t work well in the irregular, anti-insurgent warfare now in vogue.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_MODERN_AT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>World War I carried the warning that tanks (once the kinks were worked out) would come to dominate the 20th Century battlefield. The German blitzkrieg operations in the early months of World War II proved that. While anti-tank guns were all well-and-good for stopping enemy armor, on the fluid battlefields of that war the poor grunts needed something more immediate than waiting for the AT guns to arrive, set up, and start firing. Thus the evolution of MPATS (man-portable anti-tank systems). By the end of the first “war to end war” anti-tank rifles were in use. But it became a race between better armor and better MPATS. The second war brought better AT rifles, rocket-propelled grenades (RPGs), bazookas, and panzerschreck, recoilless rifles, and eventually (after the war) man-portable anti-tank missiles such as the American Javelin and Russian Kornet. The battlefield suddenly became a dangerous place for those armored behemoths.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_MUSKETMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If an arrow or quarrel could stop an armored man, just think what a small, fast-moving ball of lead could do when it passed through the metal into the squishy bits below. Replacing the unwieldy arquebus as the preferred firearm in the early 1700s AD, the musket was a smoothbore, muzzle-loaded weapon triggered by a match- or cap-lock mechanism – the archetype being the British “Brown Bess,” which served the Redcoats so well from 1722 through 1838. Sure, frontier settlers also used them around the world for hunting, protection and killing the natives, but it was in the wars of Europe that military tactics evolved to make use of the musket en masse. In China the hand cannon had evolved into the musket, and the Ming and Qing dynasties made extensive use of them. But it was the Europeans and Ottomans who used them to best effect against each other, with elite units armed with muskets.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_NATURALIST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The conservation movement can be traced back to the Royal Society’s John Evelyn and his study 'Sylva,' published in 1662, advocating conservation of England’s forests. Although sometimes linked to environmentalism, it differs significantly in that conservation aims to preserve resources expressly for continued sustainable use by humans. Conservationists have focused primarily on the setting aside of natural areas for recreation and education, and the active protection of wildlife and plants for their inherent value. Near the end of the 19th Century, politicians took a hand in this valiant effort; American president Theodore Roosevelt became a leading (and powerful) conservationist, using his office to establish the U.S. Forest Service and to create five national parks, four game preserves, 51 bird sanctuaries, and 150 national forests – some 230 thousand acres in all. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_NORWEGIAN_BERSERKER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to a number of Old Norse sources, the berserkers (Ulfheonar or “Odin’s special warriors”) were Vikings who fought in “an uncontrollable, trance-like fury.” Other sagas note they forsook armor and went into battle bare-chested wearing wolf pelts, and were “mad as hounds, bit their shields … they slew men but neither fire nor iron had effect upon them.” Pretty impressive, even to the other fun-loving Norsemen. King Harald Fairhair supposedly used them as shock troops in the front ranks of his army c. 800 AD, and other Norse kings kept some as royal bodyguards, depending on their fierce reputation to keep the unruly in line. As the pious Christians said, “From the fury of the Norsemen, good Lord, deliver us.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_NORWEGIAN_LONGSHIP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>'A furore Normannorum libera nos, Domine.' The famous prayer, usually uttered by hapless folk upon first sight of the sails of the Vikings’ longships, sums it up. From Ireland to the walls of Paris, the longships carried the fierce Norsemen to kill and plunder. But they also carried Norse explorers across the North Atlantic to Iceland, Greenland, and North America. And traders as far as Rome and Constantinople. Indeed, the longships were the apex of European naval design from the 9th through 13th centuries. Viking longships came in various types; by far the most infamous is the drekkar, a graceful, narrow, shallow-draft vessel, ornately decorated (dragons and snakes and the like), used primarily by those who went raiding. Not only were the drekkar able to sail deep waters, but their shallow draft meant these could navigate up rivers … useful in pillaging cities like Paris.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_NUCLEAR_SUBMARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The conceptual design of a nuclear-powered submarine was first proposed by the American Naval Research Laboratory in 1939 AD; it was finally realized with the launch of the U.S.S. Nautilus in 1954, which could stay underwater without surfacing for four months … although why one would wish to do so was never explained. Since underwater craft were ideal for launching nuclear-tipped ballistic missiles without warning, it was the perfect Cold War weapon, there not being much other use for such craft. Thus the Soviet Union soon followed the United States in filling the seas with nuclear submarines, beginning with the ill-fated K-19 in 1959. Despite reactor accidents, breakdowns and sinkings, both sides rushed to build ever larger SSBNs. At the height of the Cold War, some five to ten new nuclear submarines were being commissioned each month. Although the pace has slowed somewhat, today six countries deploy nuclear-powered “strategic” submarines (i.e., those meant to kill cities, not other ships): United States, Russia, China, France, United Kingdom and India.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_OBSERVATION_BALLOON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Military sorts began using balloons to carry intrepid aeronauts aloft for intelligence gathering and artillery spotting during the French Revolutionary wars, a practice that reached its highpoint during WW1 and then declined in the face of advances in aircraft design. The French Aerostatic Corps was formed in 1794 to use tethered hydrogen-filled balloons for reconnaissance, providing intelligence on enemy troop deployments during battle – the first one at Fleurus in June that year. However much the observation balloon may have contributed to the decisive French victory there over the Austrians, the device was here to stay (so long as the cable wasn’t cut and it floated away). Throughout the American Civil War, the Second Boer War, and various other conflicts, the use and design didn’t change much. The “kite balloons” of WW1 gave more stability, higher altitudes and were able to fly in more extreme weather conditions; it was the apex of using balloons in war, for by 1917 those unsporting pilots in their nimble biplanes were shooting them down by the dozens. So much for floating tranquilly above the muck.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_PIKEMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A pike is, basically, a very long spear, used for thrusting the sharp point into someone instead of throwing it at them. Very effective against other foot soldiers and especially against horsemen of all types. Indeed, besides longbowmen and muddy ground, the pike was about the only thing that would dissuade mounted knights from riding the peasants down. Thus, the pike was best used in mass formations, as by the Greek phalanx or Swiss mercenaries or German landsknechts. However, as it’s difficult to hold a pike with two hands and a shield simultaneously, pikemen tended to be vulnerable to archers and swordsmen; they weren’t much good in a melee. But if it could maintain close ranks, a pike-armed mass could roll right over the opposition, and could anchor the flanks against knights. During the heyday of its use in the Renaissance Era, the pikes became longer and longer, eventually some being 22 feet or so.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_PRIVATEER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Plausible deniability.” That principle of avoiding responsibility operated as well in the Age of Sail as it does today. The only difference – and it was a cutlass-edge thin one – between a pirate and a privateer was having a piece of paper, a letter of marque in hand granted by a sovereign. Privateers were privately-owned ships (anything from simple sloops to brigs and caravels) commissioned by a government to “gain reparations for the crown for specific offenses [by other nations] during time of peace” … or prey upon enemy shipping in time of war. After the crown took its share of the spoils from the privateer’s raids, the rest – the larger half – went to the owner and crew. Since just about everyone in Europe had a grievance against the Spanish during the colonial era, the 17th and 18th centuries were the heyday of privateering, especially by those English sea dogs coddled by Elizabeth I and by the French Protestant corsairs (who attacked just about everybody).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_QUADRIREME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Ancient shipbuilders just kept adding banks of oars to the basic design of the galley until they reached the quadrireme, a galley with four banks, each oar rowed by two men. Pliny the Elder reports that no less a scholar than Aristotle ascribed the creation of the quadrireme to the Carthaginians, likely during the 4th Century BC. Their first recorded use was during the siege of Tyre by Alexander the Great, at that time marching south to invade Egypt. After his death, the design proved popular among his successors, squabbling over the empire. During the later Punic Wars, quadriremes were used by both sides. Historical sources (not always reliable) state that these had a displacement of about 60 tons and carried around 75 marines. With their wide, shallow draft, quadriremes were ideal for operations in shallow coastal waters.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_RANGER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Ranger” has a lot of meanings: a person who roves or ranges; one of a body of armed guards who patrol a region; a soldier trained in commando tactics to make surprise attacks. These days, the common perception of a ranger encompasses all of this. The military use of rangers traces back to the frontier wars between North American colonists and the indigenous natives, who were adept at “irregular” warfare in the trackless forests and swamps. Colonel Benjamin Church, commissioned by the Governor of Plymouth Colony to harry the savages during King Phillip’s War in 1676, raised a body that was to use the enemy’s own tactics. By the time of the American Revolution, there were several Ranger companies in action against the British, who complained mightily about the methods these colonials used – ambushes, raids, demolitions, sniping, and the like. According to the 'U.S. Army Ranger Handbook,' not much has changed since.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_ROCKET_ARTILLERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Chinese Wu forces were firing off gunpowder-fueled rocket artillery as early as the siege of Yuzhang in 904 AD, although these were more colorful than deadly (save, perhaps, to their crews). The metal-cylinder ones used by the Tipu Sultan of Mysore in the 1780s and the British Congreve rockets in the 1790s weren’t much better. So it wasn’t until the German Nebelwerfer and Soviet Katyusha models of the Second World War that rocket artillery was anything but a curiosity on the battlefield. It was only after the war that designs in rocket artillery made them a mainstay for NATO and Warsaw Pact armies, poised to devastate Europe when the much-anticipated World War III broke out. The minimum recoil of rockets means that lighter carriages are needed, hence these can be more mobile (in fact, some can fire on the move); and advanced ones employ guidance systems, allowing for better accuracy against moving targets.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_ROMAN_LEGION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The legion was the most efficient and effective fighting force in history … well, in its time anyway. A fully-equipped, fully-staffed Roman legion could march across any terrain, laying a road as it did, built a fortified camp at the end of it, and then take any foe or take any wall. During the Empire a legion was composed of infantry, recruited exclusively from Roman citizens, along with the cooks, armorers, engineers, artillerists, medics and command staff (as well as the usual camp followers and sutlers) necessary to operate in the field for years at a time. The light infantry, archers, scouts, and cavalry were generally auxiliaries, provincial non-citizens (those who survived to be honorably discharged gained citizenship) assigned to a legion as necessity dictated. Extremely disciplined (usually), the legion’s heavy infantry were armed with pilum (throwing spear) and gladius (short sword) and conquered most of the known world (granted, a bunch of barbarians and decaying empires) at the time.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_RUSSIAN_COSSACK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The kazaki were members of semi-democratic, semi-nomadic, semi-militaristic communities along the steppe-shores of the Dnieper, Don, Ural, Volga and other rivers cutting across the Ukraine. It isn’t clear when these Slavs started settling in the region after the collapse of the Khazar kingdom, but it is likely after the Mongol tide receded, so perhaps late 13th Century AD. A mixture of horse barbarians and “civilized” peoples, by the 1600s the Cossacks were a loose confederation of tribes and independent communes. Internal politics notwithstanding – and the various Cossack hosts fought among themselves as much as against their neighbors – they became a force to be reckoned with, light cavalry par excellence. In time, early 17th Century or so, some of the hosts took service with the growing Russian kingdom to the north, providing a buffer against the Crimean Tatars and Ottomans to the south. The Cossacks would thereafter figure in every war the Russians fought, until virtually annihilated by Stalin following WW2.</Text>
		</Row>		
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_SCOUT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Over the centuries many people have been termed “scouts” (including teenagers in neat uniforms camping out and earning “merit badges”). But fleet-footed warriors adept at wandering the wilderness and spying on the enemy have existed since the days of hunter-gathers. These “specialists” were the eyes and ears of early civilizations, spreading out from settlements, exploring new lands, and seeking the enemy. In time, they became ever more specialized, and are an inherent and vital part – even today – of any military formation. Knowing where the opponent is and what he is up to is still vital to avoid getting slaughtered.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_SCYTHIAN_HORSE_ARCHER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term “Saka” may refer to the Persian and Sanskrit word for the Scythians, or it may refer to a specific tribe among those horse-barbarians to the north of Assyria. Most of the confusion seems to the ambiguous usage of Saka among the ancient “historians” – Herodotus, Strabo, Pliny the Elder, and that lot. Herodotus states that the Saka were horse archers, riding without saddles or stirrups, and distinguished by wearing quilted trousers, open tunics and “high caps tapering to a point and stiffly upright.” These horse archers were feared in the open, mostly for harassing a moving column or raiding the baggage trains, but not very good in a stand-up fight. As Alexander the Great had shown at the battle of Jaxartes (329 BC) the Saka had no staying power, and could be readily driven off by massed infantry in depth supported by ample numbers of foot archers, whose greater range and rate of fire gave them a distinct advantage over the mounted ones.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_SETTLER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since the first Neanderthal crawled out of his cave, scratched himself, and wondered if the grass was greener on the other side of the hill, there have been those willing to leave behind everything familiar in the hopes of finding a better life over that hill. These are the settlers, the ones who scattered mankind over the globe. Whether they travelled by water or by land or by air, the pioneers eventually came to a place they liked, usually one that offered good soil, clean water, and some prospect of safety … but not always. Some ended their journey in desert, marsh, ice field, or mountain valley. And, inevitably, among hostile natives. The reasons they left their old homes behind were as varied as the terrain they traversed: hunger, wealth, ambition, adventure, fear, freedom, and above all the hope for their descendants to have what they did not. Where they stopped became villages, towns, cities, and civilizations. And, the cycle began again …</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_SIEGE_TOWER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Climbing walls up ladders - while the defenders above hurled boiling oil, rocks and pointy objects down - wasn’t conducive to high morale among the troops, and so the Neo-Assyrians invented siege towers around the 9th Century BC. At the time, most of the towns in Mesopotamia were surrounded by mud-brick walls, generally sufficient protection against attackers, but the siege towers of the Assyrians allowed them to get over the walls relatively unscathed; thus their empire spread virtually unchecked for three centuries. It was an idea whose time had come, and soon enough all the ancient civilizations had siege towers in their arsenals. In simplest form, a siege tower was a covered wooden tower on wheels; once pushed near the offending wall, a gangplank was dropped to bridge the gap and happy warriors rushed into the town or castle. Made ever more sturdy and efficient by those master engineers the Romans, the siege tower was used throughout the Medieval Era, until gunpowder finally made them obsolete.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_SLINGER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Like most early weapon systems, the sling evolved from a tool for hunting game to one for killing people. Simply a pouch between two lengths of cord, the sling was used to swing a projectile – a stone, lump of lead, or anything else convenient – in an arc until such time as it was launched. Although a thrown stone doesn’t have the lethality of an arrow or bullet, it can still do a lot of damage. If nothing else, a rain of well-aimed stones gives an enemy pause before rushing in. And, until composite bows were invented, it had a considerable range advantage over bows and spears. In addition, wasn’t hard to find ammunition. With the exception of Australia, ancient slings have been found in archaeological digs all over the world. Even a barbarian can sling a rock. And, as the First Book of Samuel points out, a slinger can bring down even a Goliath …</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_SPANISH_CONQUISTADOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Spanish conquistadores (“conquerors”) were the soldier-explorers who colonized the world for Spain from the 14th through the 18th centuries. With the end of the Reconquista in 1492 AD, there were a lot of veteran Spanish soldiers at loose ends; luckily, shortly thereafter the Spanish discovered a New World, just ripe for conquest and conversion to Christianity (the latter actually did motivate some). The conquistadors would spread across the Americas, Africa, Asia, and even Oceania, exploring, exploiting, and even settling down in places. Drawn primarily from the ranks of light horsemen, the combination of European tactics, weapons, mounts, and ruthlessness meant most of the natives had little chance of defeating the conquistadors … and that small chance only due to sheer numbers (provided enough of them were willing to die). There is no doubt that without the likes of Cortes, Pizarro, de Balboa, de Soto and others chasing fortune, there would have been no globe-spanning empire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_SPEARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>At some point in the prehistory of civilization, some Neolithic warrior decided his club would be more efficient if he sharpened the end of it. And, hence, the spear. But the point kept getting dull from all the stabbing of animals and people. Soon enough the savages were hardening the points by charring them over fire (another recent discovery); the next innovation was attaching napped stone heads to the stick. And eventually, metal spearheads. Spears are fairly simple to master; and so were popular among the early militia that were the staple for most ancient armies. Spears can be produced fairly quickly and cheaply. And they worked well against those horse-riding barbarians. Over the centuries the spear went through endless evolutions, culminating with the bayonet, which a soldier can stick on the end of his rifle to make a spear for eviscerating the enemy once again.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_SPY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Despite the scribblings of Ian Fleming, Alistair MacLean, and Tom Clancy, the doings of most spies are far less glamorous – in fact, downright grim – or rewarding than most think. While employed in various times and places throughout history with more or less success, espionage has been a useful policy of the state only since Francis Walsingham in Elizabethan England developed most modern methods of uncovering or concealing state secrets (such as cryptography, forgery, seduction, blackmail, assassination, and more). And it is rare that spies do so for noble reasons; most are either well-paid or blackmailed into undertaking such a dangerous career. Although there have been some notable periods when spy-craft was rampant, none matched the era of the Cold War in methods or activities across the globe. But the “romance” was drained from the spy business with the advent of electronic and satellite information gathering that the superpowers seized upon in the 1990s. Bond would be terribly disappointed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_SUBMARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When those madcap Confederates in the Hunley sank the USS Housatonic in 1864 AD, it launched a new age of naval warfare; unfortunately, the Hunley also sank itself, taking its crew to the bottom as well. Nevertheless, the submarine had made its stealthy appearance. The submarine, submersible, U-boat is a craft made for sneaking up on a target while underwater and then sinking it with torpedoes … or if possible surfacing and using its pathetic deck-guns. Germany pioneered their use as merchant raiders – really effective ones – during WW1, and expanded upon it during WW2, eventually sinking some 14.5 million tons of enemy shipping (including the odd warship) from 1939 through 1945. Advances in ballast tanks, power plants, control planes, hull plating and such sparked a “submarine-race” between the post-war superpowers culminating in nuclear-powered, deep-diving boats … armed with nuclear missiles that could be launched at population centers. What has the Hunley wrought?</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_SUMERIAN_WAR_CART_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The nigh constant wars (more like backwood feuds than armed conflicts) between the Sumerian city-states helped develop a couple of innovations in killing that would spread across the ancient world. The first battle ever recorded for posterity was between Lagash and Umma c. 2525 BC as depicted on the “Stele of Vultures.” Among other things of interest, the stele shows the commander Eannatum riding in a “chariot” – actually, more a four-wheeled cart pulled by asses (the animals, not the humans). The Sumerian war-cart was a four-wheeled device composed of a woven basket mounted on wooden, solid wheels; it was manned by a crew of two carrying battle-axes and lances and pulled by a yoke of four onagers (those Asiatic asses). Although shown on this and other stele, there is considerable debate as to whether the war-carts were actually used in combat, or served more as a “battle taxi,” carting the commander around to strategic locations where he could dismount and lead his troops personally in the melee. Whatever the function, the Sumerian war-cart was the genesis for the later horse-drawn war chariot.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_SWORDSMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The “Art of the Sword” – although those first Bronze Age wielders probably weren’t very artistic – goes back to the time when a sword was little more than a large dagger, short and sharp. The most ancient swords yet excavated date to c. 1600 BC. Swords came in many types: some sharp along both edges, some just along one, some thin with a sharp point, some heavy. As often as not, a civilization’s favored type was its most distinctive aspect. It might also be noted that the evolution of the sword had a significant impact on the evolution of iron-working, mining and smelting … all rather useful technologies. Virtually every culture in history had swords, and used them proficiently against each other. In time, too, the increasing use of the sword in melee led to advances in armor, and soon enough there was an “arms” race between these military technologies. Today, the sword has been relegated primarily to ceremonial and sporting uses … but swordplay remains deep in our blood (so to speak).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_TANK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Like so many efficient ways of killing the enemy in great numbers, the “tank” was first used to any effect during WW1 and perfected during WW2. It is essentially an armored, self-propelled (on caterpillar-type tracks), self-contained fighting vehicle. The concept had been around a long time, and visionaries such as Leonardo da Vinci and Hebert G. Wells had offered simplistic views of an armored leviathan that could dominate a battlefield. But it was the stalemated fronts of WW1, dominated by barbed-wire, machineguns, artillery and mud that brought the concept to fruition. The tank (so-named on the first shipping manifests to mislead enemy intelligence) did not make a good first impression, being used solely as infantry support in the final Allied victory. The defeated learned their lesson, and in WW2 the Germans unveiled the blitzkrieg, the use of massed tanks to blow holes in the enemy lines, then pour through and overrun everything behind. Today, the battle tank is the mainstay of every nation’s army – or at least any big enough to matter.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_TRADER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As soon as there were villages, there were traders. At first they used poor, dumb brutes – horses, mules, camels, llamas, men – as beasts of burden to carry gems, precious metals, spices and anything else that would turn a profit in a distant village. Every civilized, and many not, land was crisscrossed with trade routes, and these routes – such as the great Silk Road from China to the Middle East – shaped boundaries and civilization as surely as did any war or religion. In time, some traders took to the seas; many of the earliest written records are inventories of commercial goods in ships’ holds, and archaeology shows evidence of sea-going cargo ships in the Mediterranean and Red seas by the beginning of the first millennium BC. As longer voyages of trade were undertaken, cargo ship design was constantly revised; and the beasts of burden were replaced by truck convoys. But the same principle drives trade still … the human need to make a profit.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_WARRIOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to the dictionary, a “warrior” is a person engaged or experienced in warfare. In primitive societies, that’s just about everyone since everyone fought everyone else. After all, it didn’t take much training to bash someone in the head with a rock or club, just some stamina and a strong stomach. Thus, early tribes and settlements did not have a professional standing army; that’s a benefit of civilization. Instead, all the able-bodied served in a loose militia, called to face a crisis and then returning to their farms and villages when it was past (or sometimes before). It would be centuries before some ancient kings had the foresight and wherewithal to maintain an army, with specialists in various weapons replacing the old warriors.</Text>
		</Row>
	</BaseGameText>
</GameData>