<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<BaseGameText>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_INTRO_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
      <Text>Governments let you customize your civilization to match your play style. They offer different combinations of slots that elect different types of social policies, as well as offering distinct bonuses. Social Policies represent the way you choose to govern your people. Will you be an authoritarian ruler, sacrificing a little freedom for discipline and increased productivity? Will you organize your civilization to have a strong military, or will you concentrate your efforts on expanding [ICON_Culture] Culture and borders? There are 4 types of policies, each of which may be slotted into a corresponding slot in a given government.</Text>
    </Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_CHIEFDOM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to anthropologists, a chiefdom is “an autonomous political unit comprising a number of villages … under the permanent control of a paramount chief.” So much for anthropological definitions. In point of fact, a chiefdom is a rigid hierarchy based on kinship, rule gained by ascribed status rather than achieved status, marked by centralized authority and pervasive inequalities. Influence, prestige and power is granted by the chief to an elite – thus making them, obviously, the elite, and his strongest supporters against all those lesser folk within and without the villages. Complaints against the status quo tend to be dealt with … harshly.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_CHIEFDOM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The first to write about chiefdoms was the Indian philosopher Kautilya; his 4th Century BC work notes that chiefdoms are complex social structures consisting of the chief, a warrior aristocracy, commoners, serfs and (naturally) slaves. But anthropologists argue that such structures are inherently unstable, prone to cycles of collapse and fragmentation and recreation. Rather like the Germanic chiefdoms that tore Western Rome apart. Nonetheless, chiefdoms can be of some use to more civilized sorts; the Yuan, Ming and Qing dynasties declared select tribal tusi to be imperial officials serving as judge, jury and usually executioner for local legal matters.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_AUTOCRACY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“One man, one vote.” A fine principle, especially for the ruler in an autocracy … he (or she) is the one man. Power in an autocracy is vested in the hands of a single person, subject to neither legal restraints, political oversight, nor – all too often – common sense. Historically, the prime examples of autocracy have been exemplified by absolute monarchs and military dictators. While perhaps plagued by distrust and fiscal excess and the occasional bloody coup, the great advantage to autocracy is that when immediate and definitive action is necessary, critical decisions are quickly made (unlike more liberal governments where counselors, nobles, or even commoners get to voice their opinions).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_AUTOCRACY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>This means that the palace is able to muster resources – serfs or soldiers – for whatever seems important at the time to the autocrat. Some of the great wonders of civilization – the Sphinx, Great Wall, Taj Mahal, Hermitage, etc – have been the fancy of autocrats. Some of the best armies of civilization have been those of autocrats (useful for keeping an eye on their people as well as invading neighbors). And autocrats don’t have to worry much about the annoying media; they control it to insure that their legacy in history has the proper spin.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_CLASSICAL_REPUBLIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Cleisthenes’ Athens, Rome, Poland-Lithuania, various times in France, the United States, Texas (when it had pretentions to being a nation), Ireland and Vietnam; history is full of republics: democratic, federated, confederated, socialist, unitary, “people’s” and other sorts. In a republic, power rests with selected individuals who represent the citizenry and rule in accordance with the law as embodied in a constitution. Although one of the earlier forms of government, in the 1800s quite a few nations became republics as absolute monarchy waned (or more often was overthrown with extreme prejudice). In 2015, some 147 of the world’s 206 nations were “republics.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_CLASSICAL_REPUBLIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Thomas Paine and Thomas Jefferson, two of those uppity British colonists, argued that a republic with a strong constitution was the “best” form of government because it has several advantages: it best represented the “will” of the people and thus had their support and service; the freedoms enjoyed under it guaranteed that citizens could reach their “full” potential; stability in its affairs insured domestic and foreign relations were beneficial and fair; that same stability and freedom allowed for steady economic growth and the highest common welfare. Of course, most of these benefits depend to a great deal on how the representatives are “selected” and the bureaucracy that grows to support them. Thus the differences between 5th Century BC Athens and the Socialist Republic of Vietnam.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_COMMUNISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Karl Marx’s legacy to civilization: communism. In its pure form, communism is a socio-economic system of government built upon the common ownership of production, shorn of class, money, the state apparatus, and most other markers of capitalism. One might consider it the extreme form of socialism, a response to the inequitable economic and social changes triggered by the Industrial Age. There are some advantages to the communist approach: full exploitation of resources (including people), accelerated production and scientific research (as envisioned by the five-year plans), an equitable distribution of wealth (lessening social unrest), rapid response to crises, uniform approaches to the common welfare (health, education, security and the like). At least in theory; in reality communist nations took a detour on the road to utopia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_COMMUNISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>With the erosion of personal freedoms and a solely materialistic approach to problems, most communist nations fell behind in the race to progress. Didn’t help that the bureaucracy too often proved corrupt and inefficient (in part, due to the apparatus of state security) and that paranoia led to a massive (and expensive) military complex. In the case of Soviet Russia, its avowed aim for a world-wide revolution managed to alienate most other nations. Although the Soviet Union collapsed under economic and social pressures, five neo-communist states survived the upheaval of the 1990s: China, Cuba, North Korea, Laos and Vietnam.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_DEMOCRACY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A democratic government is one in which the people are involved in making policy decisions, either directly or through elected representatives. If the elections are fair (however interpreted), the system insures civil liberties, active participation, human rights, and a rule of law. However, majority rule rules – and that can have its own disadvantages. While freedom of speech, freedom of political expression, freedom of belief, and freedom of the press all sound wonderful, these can bring discord, instability, apathy, paralysis, and violence in the face of national challenges. On the other hand, such individual freedoms can lead to bursts of artistic and scientific creativity, economic abundance, and cultural benefits … assuming the bureaucracy doesn’t overwhelm the said individual.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_DEMOCRACY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>With roots in ancient Greece, the original democracies were generally “direct” democracies, in the sense that the franchised (i.e. those who could vote – generally excluding women, slaves, those without property, etc) voted on each important matter in assembly. But as the population grew, this proved impractical. Thus, most democracies evolved as did the Roman Republic, with the citizens (however determined) electing representatives to voice their collective views and guard their collective interests. Like most types of government, democracy has both flaws and benefits … but it has proved the most enduring.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_FASCISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Fascism – authoritarian nationalism – evolved in the chaos caused by the First World War and the world-wide Great Depression. The nature of war, society and technology underwent such extreme changes that fascist movements sprang up in many countries (including democracies such as Great Britain, the United States, France, Italy, Germany and others) around the globe. In some, fascist political parties managed to seize power through guile, bloodshed or even elections: Italy, Germany, Spain, Portugal, Hungary, and Nationalist China, where Chiang Kai-shek considered fascism to be the “practical” solution to rapid modernization. Other nations, notably several across South America and Asia, embraced a neo-fascist stance.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_FASCISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Marked by militarism, nationalism, modernism, repression, and opposition to Communism, fascist governments embody totalitarianism, in which the state seeks to control all aspects of both private and public affairs. In terms of economics, fascist systems might be considered socialism with a capitalist veneer; in the midst of the Depression it seemed the best compromise between the boom-and-bust cycle of liberal capitalism (with its class conflict) and revolutionary Marxism (with its persecution of the bourgeoisie). To give the devil his due, fascism was ruthlessly efficient in times of unrest and in the organization of national resources, bringing stability and security to the people. But its reliance on militarism for economic expansion led to the Second World War and the violent end of civilization’s fascist experiment.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_MERCHANT_REPUBLIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the early Renaissance, a number of small, wealthy, trade-based nations embraced republican ideals, notably across Italy and the Baltic. In these “mercantile republics,” the leaders – usually a council of merchants headed by a doge or mayor – were elected by the citizenry with the primary duty of increasing the city-state's collective wealth. Thus, while military affairs were of importance, these were usually focused on opening or guarding trade routes. And diplomacy was centered on such matters as tariffs, customs duties and financial matters. In short, a pragmatic approach to governing. Although occasionally the leaders suffered misguided visions of glory, as when the aged Doge Dandolo joined the Fourth Crusade and helped sack Constantinople.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_MERCHANT_REPUBLIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In general, these mercantile republics arose in regions of Europe where feudal control by an absolutist monarchy was minimal or absent completely. In the Holy Roman Empire, 51 “free imperial cities,” many later composing the Hanseatic League, established chartered mercantile republics. To the east, two Russian cities – Novgorod and Pskov – pursued republicanism into the 15th Century until Muscovy put an end to any pretensions of independence. But it was in Italy that mercantile republican aspirations reached their culmination, with powerful city-states such as Venice, Genoa, Pisa, Florence and others dominating the landscape until the Napoleonic Wars subsumed their greed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_MONARCHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Sovereignty vested in a single individual – king, queen, prince, whatever – ruling until abdication or death (or, in the case of a revolution, often both). The successor to all this power is usually determined by heredity, next in line in the (more-or-less) direct royal lineage. That is a monarchy, quite popular during most eras of civilization. Monarchies come in many flavors. An absolute monarchy is one in which there are no restraints on the wielding of power. In a constitutional monarchy, the ruler’s power is somewhat constrained by law … no “off with his head” without a trial, for instance. In an electoral monarchy, the ruler is elected, usually by some form of special convocation (such as that for the Holy Roman Empire).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_MONARCHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Absolute monarchies work rather well, provided the ruler is as gifted as Elizabeth I, Frederick the Great or Qin Shi Huang. Otherwise, the nation tends to slip in stagnation. And for the truly inept revolution looms: Charles I, Louis XVI, Tsar Nicholas II, and a long list of others. Rather more stable and successful are constitutional monarchies, many of which began as elective monarchies. Most of the world’s current monarchies are constitutional, with the ruler serving in a symbolic, traditional, patriotic and propaganda role. Which is not to say that their role is not influential or important ... just look to the Queen of England or Emperor of Japan.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_OLIGARCHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Like all of civilization’s important words, the Greeks coined the term “oligarchy” to mean “ruled by the few.” Whether distinguished from the hoi polloi by family ties, religious or military prestige, personal achievements, or other attributes – Aristotle used the term to refer to rule by the rich, and Plato in The Republic argued for rule by an educated elite – the oligarchs determine what issues should be on the political agenda, debate these, and then decide “for the good of the people.” Depending on the qualifications imposed to be an oligarch, oligarchy is a fairly efficient form of government; although it does have an unfortunate tendency to become tyrannical.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_OLIGARCHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Not surprisingly, the most notable oligarchies in history are found in ancient Greece – Corinth, Sparta, Thebes, in fact all the major city-states… except the democratic Athenians. However, recent works by political scholars such as the German sociologist Robert Michels argue there is an “Iron Law of Oligarchy” whereby all forms of government tend inevitably towards oligarchy. Even in representative democracies, the practical demands of governance results in the concentration of political power in a small group, in a monolithic bureaucracy, and in rigorous means to control dissention. Which may be a good thing, as the historian Spencer Weart claims that oligarchies rarely make war on each other.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_THEOCRACY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“As God Wills” is the mantra for a theocracy, whatever the religion. A theocracy is, simply, a form of government in which some deity is the immediate authority, usually personified by human representative(s) who interprets the “Word” for the common folk. In a pure theocracy the civil leader has a direct connection to God – Moses for the Israelites, Muhammed for the Arabs, Joseph Smith for Deseret, the Pope for Vatican City, the Ayatollah for the Islamic Republic of Iran. However, most of civilization’s examples of “rule by God” are in fact quasi-theocracies, in which the ruler is a demi-god or can claim a divine commission to rule. In such, the notion of separation of church and state is a heresy. And everyone knows what happens to heretics.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_THEOCRACY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In ancient Egypt, the pharaoh was believed a demi-god, as was the emperor of the Aztecs. In most quasi-theocracies, such as the Roman Empire before Constantine, the ruler’s connection to the divine was somewhat more tenuous … but effective in insuring secular obedience nonetheless. Due to their nature, theocracies tend to have a high level of patriotism (hence, answering the call for war is a matter of faith as well as civic duty), to be well organized as a temple, and enjoy higher productivity (again, as a matter of faith). The downside is that they tend to be rigid and slow to react, and hence prone to collapse in the face of crises.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_AESTHETICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Aesthetics, focused on the nature of art and good taste, was a product of early philosophers concerned with the creation and appreciation of beauty (forget that foolishness about “eye of the beholder”). By the late Middle Ages, aesthetics had evolved to the point where it did not encompass the functionality or utility of a thing, but rather only its beauty of form, color, contrast, and other aspects. Hence, those soaring Gothic cathedrals. Just before the Renaissance got rolling – and all sorts of folks got involved in judging aesthetic appeal – Medieval thinkers were already developing general theories on proportion, perspective, and harmony for all the arts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_AGOGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Attic Greek, “agoge” meant “rearing” – the rigorous education and training mandated for all Spartan males. Besides cultivating loyalty to Sparta, the state schools included instruction in military arts, pain tolerance, hunting, dancing, singing, public speaking, and all manner of things that make for a warrior. There was also a form for Spartan girls, although the curriculum was somewhat different (intended to prepare them to give birth to warriors). The practice of agoge waned in the 3rd Century BC throughout Greece, but was revived in some places after the Roman victory in the Achaean War.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_ARSENAL_OF_DEMOCRACY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A year before Pearl Harbor, in October 1940 AD, President Roosevelt used a radio broadcast to the American public to promise military supplies to beleaguered Great Britain … while the United States stayed out of the actual fighting against all-conquering Nazi Germany. During that broadcast Roosevelt used images of America as the “arsenal of democracy” to argue against the isolationist and non-interventionist doctrine the country had followed since the end of the bloody First World War. In effect, rather than take on the Axis directly, Roosevelt pledged American aid as the principle arms supplier for the Allied effort in total war. Although Roosevelt broke a number of international and American laws to do so, it was pledge he kept.</Text>
		</Row>	
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_BASTIONS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A bastion is an angular bulwark projecting out from a fortified wall, usually with two faces and two flanks; from the flanks missile fire could be directed along the wall against attackers that would otherwise be screened from above. Although more common in the Middle Ages, early examples can be found that were constructed during the Roman Empire. The Romans fortified their cities with massive, mortar-bound stone walls, and later – when those annoying barbarians started pushing past the borders – added bastions to several of these (such as the Aurelian walls of Rome and Theodosian walls of Constantinople).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_CARAVANSARIES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As caravan routes expanded across the Middle East, Central Asia, and North Africa, the need for places where pack animals and human handlers could pause for rest, shelter, provisions, and safety – for a fee, of course – grew. Public caravansaries were complexes built outside the walls of towns and cities; private ones usually took the form of walled enclosures in the middle of nowhere with storerooms and sleeping quarters, stables, and kitchens. The largest could accommodate hundreds of camels, mules, or horses. The oldest recorded caravansaries were found along the Persian Empire’s Royal Road, stretching some 1600 km (1000 miles) from Sardis to Susa.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_CHARISMATIC_LEADER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>German sociologist Max Weber defined charismatic authority as “resting on devotion to the exceptional sanctity, heroism, or exemplary character of an individual person, and of the normative patterns or order revealed or ordained by him.” That pretty well sums it up, for charismatic leaders shape the lives of their people, for good or bad, or sometimes both simultaneously.  “Charisma” comes in two sorts: 1) a compelling charm that inspires obedience, 2) a divinely conferred power or talent for leadership. In ancient days the latter tended to be the case (at least, those barely civilized folk thought so); recently, it’s been all about charming the media.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_CHIVALRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Before it was reshaped by Christianity, our romantic notions of chivalry were introduced to Europe by the Moors of Iberia through their tales of knightly adventure for the sake of glory and love; once 'The One Thousand and One Nights' was translated into French in the 12th Century, there was no putting the genie back in the bottle. More often idealized than practiced, Charlemagne’s chevalerie (“horse soldiery”) believed chivalry to include a code of conduct that elevated loyalty, honor, forbearance, hardihood and largess above all other knightly qualities (like trampling the godless). All those things that nutcase Don Quixote was raving about.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_COLLECTIVE_ACTIVISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The problem with collective activism, according to the American economist Olson in 1965 AD, is that coercion or some incentive must be present in order to get a group of individuals to act in the common interest. In the latter half of the 20th Century, a number of activist leaders (Gandhi, King, Mandela, etc.) called for non-violent collective actions – boycotts, rallies, strikes, sit-ins, marches, petitions, educational programs, and such – to effect social, economic, political, and environmental changes. In industrial nations with semi-democratic governments, these have proven effective (sometimes). Collective activism has now gone viral, with social media and the internet now encouraging public support (financial, if nothing else) for these movements.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_COLLECTIVIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As a result of a looming famine and two million ton shortfall in grain in 1928 AD, Stalin claimed the grain was being hoarded by kulaks. At a plenary session of the Central Committee in November 1929, the Politboro embarked on a program of collectivization of agricultural production in the Soviet Union … by force. Between 1929 and 1940, over 91% of all agricultural production was “converted” into collective farms (kolkhozy); the rural, peasant-owned farmland was subjected to industrialization and mass production to feed the exploding urban population and supply cash exports (since most capitalist countries wouldn’t trade for anything else with Russia). Although more efficient and controllable, collectivization never saw Soviet agriculture reach pre-Revolution production levels.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_COLONIAL_OFFICES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once national governments began taking a hand in (and taking over) overseas colonies founded by trading companies, military adventurers, and religious fanatics, the ad hoc administrations of such distant outposts needed a firmer hand. Thus, the Spanish formed colonial offices, and were soon emulated by the other colonial powers. In the late-1500s AD the Spanish monarchy formed the Council of the Indies (although it didn’t assume its final form until a century had passed), a hierarchical organization to rule over the colonies since the king couldn’t be bothered. Initially two viceroyalties were established (two others later); Spanish viceroys had judicial and legislative control of their territory, and – more importantly – had direct access to the colonial treasury.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_COLONIAL_TAXES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mercantilism held that great powers needed colonies to serve as a “cash cow” to maintain a healthy home economy; what better way to squeeze cash out than through taxes on all and sundry, taxes that their citizens at home often didn’t have to pay. Whereas most of the colonial powers – Portugal, Spain, France (to a small extent) and others – levied taxes overseas, it was the British who faced the wrath of their ungrateful colonists over the practice. The Sugar Act, the Stamp Act, the Townshend Revenue Act, and finally the Tea Act contributed to the subsequent revolution … so perhaps colonial taxes weren’t the best policy after all.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_COLONIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The urge to procreate is a basic human trait, as true of civilizations as of individuals. In early times, these were usually established by maritime city-states on distant (relatively) shores; the Greeks and Phoenicians scattered them around the Mediterranean coasts in what they considered uninhabited lands. The Romans created colonial cities on the fringes of their empire across Western Europe, North Africa, and West Asia. Early Chinese dynasties pursued a similar policy. Through the troubled Middle Ages, the only people to undertake large-scale settling were the foot-loose Vikings, but once other Europeans began crossing the oceans they all started planting colonies all over the globe … and squabbling over who got what.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_CONSCRIPTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Military conscription is found in most ancient civilizations without professional armies (distinguished from the ilkum and corvee systems, which tended to be devoted to more pacific activities). Rather, levies of more-or-less able-bodied and more-or-less trained “recruits” were necessary in times of unrest. Although armament and ability varied considerably, such levies generally fought as infantry under their king or his designates. However, early wars didn’t last long; it was in everyone’s interest to get the battles over with in time for harvest, as most of the conscripts were farmers. But, at least, they were cheap.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_CONTAINMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As the Cold War opened, the United States opted for a policy of “containment” of the Soviet Union, the “evil empire” of communism. George Kennan, a career Foreign Service officer, formulated the policy which became the basis of the Truman administration’s response to threatened communist expansion. It was controversial, to say the least. Eisenhower refused to intervene in the Hungarian Uprising in 1956, but Johnson used it to justify American involvement in Vietnam. Nixon and Kissinger rejected it completely in favor of working towards détente with Russia and China through expanded trade and cultural exchanges. Reagan returned to the strategy by sending aid to a variety of anti-communist insurgents, notably in Afghanistan, leading to the eventual collapse of the Soviet Union.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_CORVEE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Although the term refers to the medieval practice of paying one’s taxes through unpaid labor – typically a certain number of days each year – “corvée” has been around since ancient Egypt. From roughly 2600 BC onward, the Old Kingdom used such “taxes” to build pyramids, temples and monuments. Imperial China had a similar system in place; Qin Shi Huang and subsequent emperors imposed it for public works such as the Great Wall and the Grand Canal. By the Middle Ages, corvée was embedded in the feudal system, with tenants required to perform construction work on the private lands of their lords. Thus, throughout history the gentry had nice homes and tombs while everyone else had hovels.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_CRAFTSMEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The craft guilds of the Middle Ages not only protected craftsmen (and their customers from shoddy work), but insured that there would be ever more craftsmen. An aspiring craftsman would pass through various levels of training and responsibility – from apprentice to journeyman – before being tasked with producing a “masterpiece.” If that was acceptable, the candidate would be a master craftsman, capable of producing the finest of works in their craft, be that jewelry or carpentry. As new crafts evolved across medieval Europe, new craftsmen swelled the growing cities: cobblers, barbers, brewers, curriers, farriers, apothecaries … a nigh endless list of the middle class.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_CRYPTOGRAPHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Cryptography prior to the modern age was primarily a matter of encryption, often simple transposition or substitution cyphers, making a message nonsense without a key. Like a game for bright children. By World War II, however, cryptography was mostly a matter of mathematical theory and computer science … hardly child’s play. Cryptographic algorithms were designed around computational assumptions and integer factorization. At England’s Bletchley Park facility during World War II, research culminated in Colossus – civilization’s first electronic, digital, programmable computer – built to decrypt the Lorenz cipher. Now nations, corporations, and hackers devote immense blocks of computing time and analysis to cryptosystems … creating them and breaking them.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_DEFENSE_OF_MOTHERLAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Although the term “Motherland” has been adopted by a number of groups to refer to their homeland, it is most closely associated with Soviet Russia and especially the defense of Russia against the Nazi German invasion during World War II. During the course of that struggle, Russia lost some 26.6 million people, 16 million of them civilians – roughly 13.7% of its 1940 population. The spirit of defiance and extreme sacrifice by the common people against foreign invasion is credited with the victory, for there certainly was little love for the brutal Soviet regime itself among them. These days, in Russia 23 February has been set aside as “Defense of the Motherland Day.” Less bloodily, in the late 1800s the Indian nationalist movement referred to their homeland as 'Bharat Mata' (Mother India) with no sacrifice too great for her freedom.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_DIPLOMATIC_LEAGUE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The ancient Greeks were enamored of diplomatic leagues – loose and limited alliances between city-states, cobbled together for a variety of purposes. In the Archaic Period, the Amphictyonic League was a religious association of tribes. By the end of the 7th Century BC, Sparta was the most powerful city-state in the Peloponnese; to counter its influence some 150+ cities formed the Delian League in 477 BC under the leadership of Athens. It spent most of its existence fighting off Persian invasions. Around 338 BC, Philip II of Macedonia formed the Hellenic League … and Alexander conquered (briefly) the known world with it. The Achaean League existed between 280 and 146 BC, formed to resist the Romans. Didn’t help.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_DISCIPLINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Discipline has been necessary for victory since the first “armies” blundered into each other, with breaches of discipline punished by anything from demotion to death (in various unpleasant ways). At first, in the days of civilian militia, the rules were fairly simple … basically, follow orders, no matter what. With the rise of professional armies, military law became codified and more convoluted, although punishment hasn’t changed much – between 1942 and 1961 AD 160 members of the American military were executed under the auspices of the Uniform Code of Military Justice for various crimes, including desertion, mutiny, and murder.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_ECOMMERCE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In 1979 AD, Michael Aldrich demonstrated the first online shopping system, the beginning of electronic commerce (or e-commerce). From that primitive launch, e-commerce now uses computer networks (notably the internet) for such activities as electronic funds transfers, online marketing and sales, virtual shopping, supply chain management, electronic data exchange, inventory management. E-commerce allows consumers to electronically exchange goods and services with no barriers of time or distance. In 2012, e-commerce sales topped one billion dollars for the first time, and has expanded significantly since to blur the boundaries between conventional and electronic commerce even more.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_ECONOMIC_UNION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Under the impetus of globalization, smaller nations have found themselves unable to compete with the larger states in terms of capital, labor, production, and raw materials. To that end, a number of economic unions – trade blocs composed of a common market and a customs union, often with some sort of unifying currency – began to coalesce in the 1980s. Member nations agree to common product and business laws, free cross-border movement of goods and services, joint external trade regulations, and so forth. A number have been cobbled together over the past few decades: CARICOM, the Eurasian Economic Union, Mercosur, but undoubtedly the biggest and most influential is the European Union created by the Maastricht Treaty in 1992 AD.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_ELITE_FORCES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since the Hittite and Assyrian kings formed palace guards, every professional army has included elite forces, specialized military units trained to conduct unconventional, high-risk combat missions. And they usually have really spiffy uniforms. Elite units came to prominence in World War II, especially in the totalitarian nations; Germany employed the likes of the Brandenburger Regiment and Skorzeny’s SS Jager Battalion to devastating effect, while Fascist Italy had several specialized naval units. Since the war, units such as the Russian Spetsnaz and American Green Berets have carried on that tradition of ruthless efficiency (and distinctive uniforms).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_EXPROPRIATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Expropriation – as opposed to eminent domain, which usually involves some form of compensation – is the government taking private property for a purpose deemed to be in “the public interest.” Often this is land, but in the 20th Century it became a major element of nationalization, as governments sought to redress perceived wrongs or stabilize their economies or lessen foreign influence (or all three, as in the case of the Mexican expropriation of American oil company holdings in March 1938). Communist policies in the 1920s and across Eastern Europe after World War II saw the expropriation of virtually all foreign holdings in those countries.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_FEUDAL_CONTRACT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>For commoners not serfs nor indentured servants, villeins – not to be confused with “villains,” although that may be mere terminology – were the vassals enjoying a feudal contract with a manor lord. They were legally free but subject to the lord’s authority. Under the feudal contract, the lord had the duty to provide a fief for his villein, to protect him, and to provide justice in the king’s court for him. In return, the lord demanded fealty and the right to services attached to the contract (military, labor, taxes, and such). To violate the oath of fealty was a felony, like a breach of contract but with stiffer penalties.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_FINEST_HOUR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>On 18 June 1940, Prime Minister Churchill addressed Parliament on the state of the war against Nazi Germany, given over in large part to praising the Royal Air Force’s battle against the Luftwaffe. Although the phrase “their finest hour” did not refer specifically to the RAF, it has come to be most closely associated with its pilots. Churchill noted, “it is a very great pity that we have not got an Air Force at least equal to that of the most powerful enemy within striking distance of these shores.” While Churchill did not call for increased investment, this speech served as the impetus for the British government to devote most of its production and training resources to planes and pilots for a year.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_FIVE_YEAR_PLAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The five-years plans of Soviet Russia were a series of economic development guidelines devised by a state planning committee appointed by the Communist Party; the first was initiated in 1928 AD, and the last was in operation when the Soviet Union dissolved in 1991. Fulfilling the plan was the primary motivating factor for a Soviet bureaucracy that became unwieldy attempting to do so. However, the initial successes of the early plans motivated other communist nations, such as Mao’s China and Castro’s Cuba, and even some capitalist states to adopt this method of promoting and coordinating economic development. Most have sensibly abandoned such a restrictive and often unrealistic approach.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_FREE_MARKET_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In a “free market” system, the prices for goods and services are set by consent between sellers and buyers dependent solely on the forces of supply and demand, rather than a government, monopoly or other controlling authority. There are two pillars to a free market: voluntary exchange and private property. Compelling intellectual arguments in favor of private ownership of all things would not be made until John Locke did so in the 17th Century. A century later Adam Smith would offer the most concise argument (he is considered by normally dour economists as the “father of free market economics”) for a laisse-faire economy, which he proposed benefitted everyone (greed being good) in a civilization equally.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_FRESCOES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term fresco literally means "fresh" in Italian, and describes a style of painting that boomed during the Italian Renaissance. More than simply a picture painted on top of a wall, frescoes are created by applying water and color to wet plaster, allowing the pigment to absorb and dry into the plaster itself. Though perhaps the most famous fresco is the Sistine Chapel ceiling, created by Michelangelo, this technique can be found throughout history. One of the earliest examples of frescoes can be dated to c. 2000 BCE by the Minoans. Though it has fallen out of common fashion, a style similar to frescoes, known as Mexican Muralism, was rekindled in the 20th century.</Text>
		</Row>				
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_GOD_KING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Not satisfied with being mere kings, some ruling dynasties took on the mantle of divinity to insure obedience, prestige, and infallibility. Egyptian pharaohs were generally believed to be incarnations of the god Horus. In imperial China at times the emperor was considered the “Son of Heaven,” ruling under the “Mandate of Heaven” with his commands believed sacred writ. Some Roman emperors were declared gods by the Senate, but generally after their death, so godhood didn’t interfere with their duties. Although all this godliness was eventually replaced with the divine right of kings to rule, it has echoed throughout the course of civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_GOTHIC_ARCHITECTURE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Distinguished by ribbed vaults, flying buttresses, pointed arches, overlaid tracery … and gargoyles, lots of gargoyles. Gothic architecture dominated construction of monumental European buildings from the mid-12th through the 16th centuries. Arising from Romanesque styles, it was the architecture of choice for cathedrals, abbeys, castles, palaces, guild halls, and all sorts of buildings meant to impress and awe the commoners. With cavernous interiors and soaring rooftops, these were perfect for the pomp and pageantry kings and bishops so loved. Sadly, a slew of Gothic revivals spanned the mid-18th through early 20th centuries, largely for stunningly ugly university structures, replete even with gargoyles.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_GRANDE_ARMEE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>At its peak just prior to the invasion of Russia, Napoleon’s Grande Armée numbered some 680 thousand men, drawn primarily from France but also including contingents from 11 other nations (95 thousand from Poland alone). It has been widely acknowledged by military historians to be one of the greatest fighting forces ever assembled, and under the command of Napoleon and his generals, tactically superior to anything it faced. The Grande Armée was originally the force Napoleon had assembled for the invasion of England but renamed in 1805 AD and put to other uses – like conquering most of continental Europe. It would serve as the template when most of the powers decided they too needed a large, national army.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_GRAND_OPERA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As if opera isn’t enough (and it certainly is for many folks), for a period from the late 1820s through the 1850s “grand opera” was all the rage in France. The genre was marked by four or five acts, large casts and orchestras, lavish costumes and stage effects, with plots based on dramatic historical events. The first of these monumental productions was La Muette de Portici by Daniel Auber; set in 1647 revolutionary Naples, it ends with the eruption of Mount Vesuvius and the heroine throwing herself into it. There was not a dry eye in the theater after it premiered, and for nearly two generations European audiences flocked to grand operas.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_GUNBOAT_DIPLOMACY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Gunboat diplomacy – or, in Teddy’s words, the “Big Stick” policy – is the pursuit of foreign policy objectives through conspicuous demonstrations of overwhelming military force, with the threat of open hostilities underlying the display by the more powerful nation. Roosevelt himself described it as “the exercise of intelligent forethought and of decisive action sufficiently far in advance of any likely crisis.” The term came into popular usage during the period of European imperialism, as the colonial powers used the presence of warships to force concessions from native kingdoms. The policy proved very successful, especially as employed by militaristic autocracies … until the natives managed to obtain modern weaponry.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_HERITAGE_TOURISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Heritage tourism, defined by the National Trust as “traveling to experience the places, artifacts, and activities that authentically represent the stories and peoples of the past.” Well, more-or-less authentic, since it doesn’t include the bad food, dysentery, bugs, lack of sanitation, and other dangers of that past. Think Colonial Williamsburg today, rather than in pre-Revolution America. Heritage tourism is booming, especially in the United States as people seek to find their “roots” and legitimize their present. Rather than museums, these tourists seek operating railways, interactive battlefields, working farms and ranches, native villages … all emulating a period in the past for which they hanker.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_ILKUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Conscription was first instituted during the reign of Hammurabi (around 1750 BC). Under this ilkum system, the Babylonian Empire could call upon anyone to serve in the army during time of war; during the plentiful times of peace, his subjects were instead required to provide unpaid labor for other activities deemed important – building projects, harvesting crops, producing trade goods, and anything else the “good of the state” might require. (In return, the conscripts gained the right to hold land.) Over the following centuries, various other empires instituted similar systems, eventually evolving into the feudal system so popular with the peasants of medieval Europe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_INDUSTRIAL_RELOCATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>During World War II, the largest relocation of industrial plants was undertaken by the Soviet Union following the Nazi invasion; in November 1941 AD alone, 1503 industrial facilities, large and small, were moved eastward. In later stages of the war, both Germany and Japan also undertook relocation of industrial plants, though not on such a scale. Since the war, “industrial relocation” has come to refer to moving industry from advanced countries to developing nations (for a variety of reasons, mostly dealing with lower costs, less regulation, and access to raw materials). While there are some benefits to the developing country – tax revenue, technology transfer, increased employment, and such – there are also some distinct, readily imagined disadvantages.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_INSPIRATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Some new ideas come from trial and error; others, from inspiration (artistic, imaginative, or perhaps divine). Whatever the source, inspiration has brought about many notable advances in scientific knowledge and technology. Commonly known as the 'Eureka' moment (as any mad scientist knows), the term comes from a story about the Greek polymath Archimedes’ sudden epiphany c. 250 BC concerning how to prove whether a crown was pure gold or not. Inspiration cannot be called upon as desired; in fact, a recent study by Mareike Wieth and Rose Zacks suggests that insight and innovation are greatest when an individual is not at his/her best. So there’s hope for us yet.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_INSULAE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once people came pouring in on all those roads that led to Rome, they had to live someplace in the urban sprawl; thus, the 'insulae,' a kind of apartment building built of stone and concrete (which the Romans invented), evolved as housing for the lower and middle class plebs. Five or six stories high (although some were larger), the ground floor was taken up by shops with residential apartments upstairs … the best being those nearest to the ground. But the insulae were prone to collapse, and fire was an ever present danger. Augustus and later Nero set construction standards; nevertheless, by the 4th Century it is estimated that there were around 42,000 to 46,000 insulae in the city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_INTEGRATED_SPACE_CELL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The 2007 anti-satellite test by China, in which it shot down one of its own aging weather satellites, sent shock waves through the Indian government. Even though both the United States and Russia had the capability to shot down satellites in orbit, India now faced a doomsday scenario, for it depended heavily on its satellite systems for military, commercial, and public services. This led India to proclaim the Integrated Space Cell operational in June 2010 (although it may have been in place long before), the largest constellation of remote-sensing satellites – 11 operational thus far – in a “defense architecture” for a space war.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_INTERNATIONAL_SPACE_AGENCY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>An “International Space Agency” doesn’t exist yet … but it’s only a matter of time. Given the creation of the UN Office for Outer Space Affairs, established to promote peaceful international cooperation in the exploration (and, likely, exploitation) of space, as well as the “utilization of space sciences and technology for sustainable economic and social development” of its member states, it may well be under UN control. Multinational space organizations such as the ESA (European Space Agency, established in 1975) will also likely form a vital element of any such future agency. And, no doubt, one of the first projects will be assumption of managing the International Space Station, currently a joint project of five participating national space agencies and protected by a web of intergovernmental treaties and agreements.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_INTERNATIONAL_WATERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“International waters” is the term that refers to the notion that certain bodies of water transcend (supposedly) national boundaries and are free to passage by all; while it can be applied to some lakes, rivers, and swamps, in general it is used in relation to oceans and seas. While all nations can claim sovereignty over their territorial waters extended out 12 nautical miles (22.2 kilometers), they have no jurisdiction past that limit. Although the concept of “freedom of the seas” dates to the 17th Century, it was not codified until several United Nations conventions were passed in the 1960s.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_INVENTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since the fall of Rome, things hadn’t changed much in Europe – although to the east, the Arabs had certainly been busy inventing all sorts of things. The old knowledge and technology of the ancients defined the European world. But with the Renaissance, as the Church’s strictures on curiosity loosened, all sorts of tinkerers like Leonardo da Vinci and Johannes Gutenberg began inventing “new” things. Too, many of the Islamic inventions, from the crank-connecting rod to the guitar to the toothbrush to the vertical-axle windmill, seeped into Europe by way of the Moors. All this inventing would lay the foundations for the Scientific Revolution still to come.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_LAISSEZ_FAIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Laissez-faire economics is the capitalist’s holy grail, for all private transactions are completely free from any sort of government involvement or oversight – including tariffs, subsidies, trade regulations, limits on monopolies, price controls, labor affairs, or any other such nonsense. The debate on laissez-faire economics dates back as far as the Han, Tang, Song, and Ming dynasties in China when officials and merchants argued for centuries on how much government involvement was necessary or justified. In the modern age, as multi-national corporations became ever more influential, the debate intensified, with Adam Smith acknowledging deep moral ambiguities and John Maynard Keynes condemning laissez-faire economics outright.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_LAND_SURVEYORS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once the idea of ownership of the land was ingrained in humanity, methods for determining boundaries were necessary. In ancient Egypt, a rope with knots could be used with simple geometry to re-establish boundaries after the annual floods along the Nile. Land surveyors were also at work around those old monuments tourists are now enamored of; Stonehenge was laid out by surveyors using pegs and ropes, as was the Great Pyramid of Giza. The Chinese Liu Hui described methods of surveying in works published c. 263 AD. But it was the Romans who first acknowledged land surveying as a profession; there, surveyors were known as Gromatici, so named after the Groma instrument dating back to ancient Mesopotamia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_LEVEE_EN_MASSE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In response to reverses at the hands of the First Coalition, the revolutionary National Convention of France decreed a "levée en masse” in August 1793 AD, a “requisition” of all able-bodied, unmarried men between the ages of 18 and 25. While there had been conscription in many countries previously, the French approach meant that unprecedentedly large armies could be raised and put into the field … giving French generals the numbers to pound their many enemies into defeat. The levée in times of crisis was a major development in the history of modern warfare, leading to increasingly larger forces with each successive war, culminating in the enormous armies of the First and Second world wars.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_LIBERALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Although liberalism as a political philosophy would come to the fore later in the “Age of Enlightenment,” its roots lie in the Glorious Revolution in England of 1688 AD. As a result John Locke and Algernon Sidney were among several English philosophers who argued for a new worldview founded on the principles of liberty and equality, that government’s primary purpose was to protect its citizens’ liberty, lives and property – even from itself. Thus, spurred by the Renaissance and Reformation, liberalism promoted freedom of speech, the press, religion, markets, and the freedom to enjoy most of the deadly sins. Conservatives have had their knickers in a twist ever since.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_LIGHTNING_WARFARE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Lightning” warfare, better known by the German term blitzkrieg, is a strategy that concentrates motorized forces to create a high-speed breakthrough of an enemy’s lines. Using combined arms and tactical air power, it seeks to keep an enemy off-balance, penetrating deep into the rear and attacking units flanking the breakthrough. The effects could be devastating, especially to morale (soldiers don’t like to be surrounded). Pioneered by Heinz Guderian and perfected by Erich von Manstein and Erwin Rommel, so effective was the blitzkrieg in Poland, France, and Russia that the Soviet Union and Western Allies adopted it to ultimately defeat Nazi Germany.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_LIMES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Limites (the plural of limes) delineated the fortified frontiers of the Roman Empire, signified by fortified cities and military outposts. Hadrian’s Wall was often referred to as the Limes Britannicus; the far eastern edge facing the desert was the Limes Arabicus … the Limes Germanicus, Limes Alutanus, etc., etc. The military bases of the limites were designated as castra (fortresses of the legions) and castella (bases guarded by auxiliaries, usually local native infantry). Although the empire always looked to its defenses, the period between 40 and 280 AD was the highpoint of building limes. Indeed, Roman writers of the time presented the limites as a sort of sacred border beyond which civilized people did not go.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_LITERARY_TRADITION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Every linguistic group has developed a literary tradition; in part, it is what distinguishes one civilization from another – the passing down of stories which give meaning to human experience. Early literary traditions were oral (such as the tales of Homer), but once writing progressed beyond daubing pictographs on walls, the various literary forms were immortalized, and no longer had to be memorized to be passed on. In ancient China, its oral poetry was collected in works such as the Shijing and Songs of Chu. And the Western literary traditions were largely set by the early Greek and Roman authors, and by the Bible.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_LOGISTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the late 16th Century AD, the size of armies in Europe increased dramatically, and forces of 100 thousand were not unheard of (although these reported numbers may have included the horde of camp followers as well). Given the state of transport and roads in the Renaissance, in general when operating in enemy territory an army would forage (i.e., pillage) to maintain itself. But this didn’t supply much that was now necessary – munitions, siege guns, uniforms, medical supplies, booze, and all the other things that keep soldiers content. Thus, the baggage trains that attended armies grew; during the Thirty Years War for some mercenary armies this amounted to a wagon for every 15 men.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_MACHIAVELLIANISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>By definition “Machiavellianism” is “the employment of cunning and duplicity in statecraft” (in psychology it is defined as one of the dark triad personalities, but that’s another thing). In his works The Art of War (1521 AD) and The Prince (1532), Machiavelli advocated that effective rulers routinely employ espionage, deception, and assassination to insure their interests … which were the interests of their state, of course. While a number of kings took his advice to heart, it was Queen Elizabeth’s “spymaster” (actually he was the Secretary of State) who developed the best Renaissance spy network, employing linguists, scholars, authors, engineers, soldiers, and diplomats to seek out and analyze secrets (both internal and external).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_MANEUVER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once warfare moved past the stage of small masses of men just having at it in a club-thumping melee, maneuvers gave the more nimble warriors a distinct advantage in battle. The concept of using rapid movements to keep the enemy at a disadvantage is almost as old as the idea of war itself. Tactical maneuvers are intended to be used on the battlefield, while “maneuver warfare” covers all that leads up to forcing an enemy to fight at a place or time they’d rather not. Both types came to prominence with the advent of chariots and cavalry … and their importance hasn’t diminished since.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_MARITIME_INDUSTRIES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In some ancient places, men took to the seas, exploring, fishing, trading, and fighting. And in some of those places, maritime industries – the construction and outfitting of ships – haphazardly arose, making these men somewhat better at this exploring, fishing, trading, and fighting. Although the Egyptians built the first sea-going ships, the Minoans were the first great seafarers of history, trading as far away as Sicily while their King Minos conquered the other Aegean islands. The Phoenicians built a maritime “empire” of loosely-allied city-states. In far India, the Mauryan Empire (4th Century BC) developed the earliest known state organization for shipbuilding, and “invented” the science of navigation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_MARKET_ECONOMY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Whereas for several centuries laissez-faire economics operated, by the mid-19th Century such free-wheeling markets faced – for a variety of reasons – opposition; governments in the industrializing countries intervened on the behalf of workers and the general populace, enacting factory standards and consumer protection laws and breaking up monopolies. Arose “market economies,” in which purchase and production of goods are based on principles of supply and demand. Market economies can range from regulated markets to various forms of state interventionist models. In reality, neither market economies nor free markets exist in “pure” form, since throughout the 20th Century, governments regulated most businesses to varying degrees. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_MARTIAL_LAW_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Martial law is that legalism by which military law “temporarily” supersedes civil law, declared by a government whereby it doesn’t have to worry about such niceties as civil rights, habeas corpus, civil courts (civilians defying martial law can be tried by military tribunals), and can impose curfews, travel bans, rationing, and such at will. In effect, all power is transferred to the military, and is removed from the previous executive, legislative, and judicial authorities (some of whom may well be imprisoned themselves). There are many potential reasons for imposition of martial law “to restore order”: following a coup (as in Thailand in 2006) or a natural disaster (the San Francisco earthquake), perhaps during labor unrest (the Colorado Coalfields War) or war (as in Hawaii from 1941 to 1944).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_MEDINA_QUARTER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>All Arab cities with some history left have their medina – an urban residential quarter typically walled, with narrow and maze-like streets, in some places less than a meter (39 inches) wide. To a follower of Islam, the Prophet decreed that a just and ordered city was obligatory, and so the design of medinas reflected communal values, often containing at their heart fountains, mosques, and markets. Because of their winding, narrow streets, they also served as defense against invaders… and they are also free of auto traffic, and usually of motorbikes, and even bicycles as well.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_MERCHANT_CONFEDERATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>More commonly referred to as a commercial league, a merchant confederation was created to protect the economic interests and diplomatic privileges of merchants in cities and kingdoms along trade routes. Although such confederations rarely had official standing, several – such as the Company of Merchant Adventurers of London (founded in 1407 AD) and the even more powerful Hanseatic League (formed c. 1356) – had enormous influence. These, and others, could dominate the trade in a specific commodity or across a specific region for lengthy periods. These merchant confederations would reach their peak during the 15th and 16th centuries, but rapidly decline afterward.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_MERITOCRACY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Plato, among others, advocated meritocracy as the most sensible form of public administration … in his case that rulers should be philosopher-kings whose right to rule came from their intellect and insight. Simply put, a meritocracy is a system in which the most talented and worthy gain advancement in the government bureaucracy, rather than, say, those who are close personal friends of the current ruler (or congressman), or those from a certain tribe or caste or religion. Most civilizations swing back and forth between some form of meritocracy and some less sensible method of choosing those who run things. This pattern repeats itself until the sun explodes and all life is wiped off of the face of the planet.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_MILITARY_FIRST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When the United States entered World War II, it was woefully unprepared, and it took months to put America on a war footing. As a result of the Cold War, the administration adopted an amorphous strategy of “Military First” for spending and research, leading to an informal alliance between military and corporate interests in influencing public policy. In his farewell address in January 1961, President Eisenhower first referred to the “military-industrial complex.” Currently, U.S. military expenditures account for about 47% of the world’s total arms production, and in 2011 the United States spent more on its military than the next 13 nations combined. “Military First” indeed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_MILITARY_ORGANIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A highly-rigid, hierarchical military organization first came into widespread use with the Roman Army. Until the so-called Age of Reason however, throughout the Middle and Renaissance periods, most military organizations were rather ad hoc affairs. The rise of mostly professional, national armies changed that. And professional armies needed professional officers, not just those appointed to command due to connections or wealth. The first national academies opened to fill the military hierarchy – the oldest the Royal Military Academy at Woolwich in 1720 AD – offering training for aspiring officers. An established military organization provided opportunities for the gifted graduates to rise rapidly through the ranks … and have the chance to be brilliant. Occasionally, that even happened.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_MILITARY_RESEARCH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>While there were some instances of government military research before, the funding of science with military applications has had a transformative effect on research since the opening decade of the 20th Century. World War I was termed the “chemists’ war” as scientists funded by their governments raced to develop more and more lethal chemicals and countermeasures against the newest gases; meanwhile physicists were building bigger and better guns, bombs, and machines. World War II marked an even greater investment in military innovations, culminating in that mushroom cloud over Hiroshima. The sheer scale of military research funding since has had a profound effect on civilization … especially as some (but not all) new discoveries also have civilian applications.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_NATIONAL_IDENTITY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>With emergence of a “public sphere” and an integrated national economy in various 18th-Century European civilizations, people began to identify with their country at large rather than the smaller town or province in which they resided. National symbols, anthems, flags, myths, and traditions were elevated in the citizenry’s collective psyche as being somehow important. The convulsions of the American and French revolutions augmented this development with widespread appeals to patriotic nationalism. Prussian-born Johann Herder was the prophet of this new creed and originated the term “nationalism” to describe an inborn pride in one’s origins, language, and culture. Then came the many wars of nationalism, and a new level was added to the chauvinism.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_NATIVE_CONQUEST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The first wave of European colonization began in the early 15th Century AD when the Portuguese established trading posts along the coast of Africa on their way to the Far East. But when the Spanish discovered the Americas, soon followed by the Portuguese, English, French, Dutch, Swedes, and anyone else who could sail the oceans, the settlement of “empty” lands took on another tone. For, of course, these lands weren’t empty, but full of natives that had been there for millennia. When the new arrivals clashed with the locals, it turned out poorly for the natives, thanks to Europeans guns, cannons, horses, and diseases. The natives never had a chance.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_NATURAL_PHILOSOPHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>From the days of Aristotle, natural philosophy was the study of the physical world, the first systematic “science.” Every other science – biology, physics, chemistry, astronomy, mathematics, and all – has its roots in natural philosophy, and most of Aristotle’s predecessors such as Parmenides, Heraclitus, and Democritus centered their beliefs on the natural order. Aristotle’s conceptions of the laws that govern the real world, set down in the Corpus Aristotelicum (the bits that survived), prevailed into the Middle Ages. Although the empirical study and understanding of everything would separate into various scientific disciplines, it all began with natural philosophy. And now the boundaries between the disciplines are getting blurry again.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_NAVAL_INFRASTRUCTURE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If a civilization was going to have a naval and merchant fleet, it needed a lot of other things – docks, slips, wharves, warehouses, breakwaters, lighthouses, not to mention all those stevedores, shipwrights, harbor pilots, and others – to float ships and keep them afloat. Without this naval infrastructure, navies don’t last long. In the Middle Ages, for the first time, some kingdoms devoted substantial planning and funds to their naval facilities. For instance, the threat of Ottoman expansion brought the Venetian Republic to establish extensive shipyards (including the famous Arsenal), while the Fatimid Caliphate and Byzantine Empire needed efficient naval infrastructures to keep killing each other for two centuries.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_NAVIGATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Early “navigators” plotted their course by the stars; although hardly an exact science, by the European Medieval Age navigation had been elevated to one of the “seven mechanical arts.”  This was due in part to a few inventions to help mariners keep from going astray (although they tended not to leave sight of land). Since estimating speed and direction by the seaweed going by was rather inaccurate, the Han Chinese devised the mariner’s compass around 206 BC. The next great advance came in the Middle Ages when Arabic sailors improved the kamal, used for celestial navigation, into the astrolabe. Once mariners began keeping detailed records, the first nautical charts – portolan charts – were drawn … and finding home got more assured.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_NEW_DEAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Great Depression devastated the world. In some countries it led to the rise of totalitarian governments (Mussolini’s Italy, for example); in others, it led to political realignment (Britain) or the rise of Communist parties (France). In the United States, the Depression led to the New Deal, a series of domestic programs championed by then-President Franklin Roosevelt. These laws, executive initiatives, and presidential decrees aimed at relief for the unemployed and poor, recovery for American industry, and reforms to economic oversight. Although most of the New Deal programs have faded away, some of the alphabet soup remains in place: FDIC, FCIC, FHA, TVA, SEC along with the most extensive of all, the Social Security System.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_NOBEL_PRIZE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Not wanting to go down in history as the “merchant of death” (no matter how justified) that a French newspaper referred to him as, Alfred Nobel in his will left about 94% of his great wealth to the establishment of five prizes to be awarded annually. These prizes – in physics, chemistry, medicine, literature, and peace – were to be given to “those who, during the preceding year, shall have conferred the greatest benefit on mankind.” On the fifth anniversary of Nobel’s death, in December 1901, the first were presented. Since then, the Prize has become the highest honor a scientist can receive, bringing recognition, academic advancement, and new research opportunities. To date (and increasing each year), some 870 individuals and 23 organizations have won Nobel Prizes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_NUCLEAR_ESPIONAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Nuclear weapons tremendously shift the balance of power in favor of the countries that possess them. Nuclear espionage is the unauthorized trading of any confidential information relating to nuclear weapons – such as design and production methods. Even as the first nuclear weapon was being developed by America, this form of espionage was present. Klaus Fuchs, a theoretical physicist who worked at Los Alamos during the Manhattan Project, was caught delivering nuclear secrets to the Soviet Union. The delivery systems of these weapons advanced and so too did the methods of securing those advancements – and yet the sale of nuclear secrets continues, allowing smaller nations to covertly affect their standing in the balance of power.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_ONLINE_COMMUNITIES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Where “community” was once defined by place, now it is defined by common interests, common concerns, or cat videos. Virtual communities have proliferated with the expansion of the internet, notably via portable devices. Through chat rooms, forums, e-mail lists, and social networking services, many people now have thousands of “invisible friends” … along with, or instead of, the real ones next door. The trend towards belonging to an online community is spreading; as of 2013 AD, there were 20 major virtual communities with over 100 million members each.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_PATRIOTIC_WAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Every war fought by the people is, in a sense, a “patriotic war” (after all, other than religion, it is the most effective way to convince folks to kill each other). But in the 20th Century AD, the term patriotic war has designated those conflicts where, according to Communist doctrine, the proletariat has risen to defend itself against a foreign threat. More generally, it refers to a war to defend the homeland, or in this case, the “Motherland.” First applied to the general resistance by the Russian peasantry to Napoleon's invasion in 1812, it was more generally used to refer to the costly defense of Russia against Germany in the Second World War.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_POLICE_STATE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The traditional police state that arose in various countries during the 18th and 19th centuries was a mixture of autocratic reforms, paternalistic benevolence and compulsion … not necessarily repressive, with its emphasis on national security and progress. But the modern police state arose in the 20th Century and presupposes an authoritarian regime, which in turn grants sweeping powers to its law enforcement agencies. Inhabitants of the latter face restrictions on their freedom to move about, express political or social views, and high levels of surveillance (the primary purpose of the “secret police”).  </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_PRESS_GANGS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Impressment was the practice of “recruiting” men into the navy by force (with or usually without notice). Navies of several civilizations used press gangs (armed groups who wandered about and did the “impressing”), but the most well-known was the Royal British Navy, who began using it during wartime in 1664 AD and continued until the Napoleonic Wars. Although the practice fell into disuse after 1814 (impressed sailors did not necessarily make good sailors), it wasn’t outlawed in Great Britain until 1835. Despite lurid tales, press gangs rarely operated outside ports and rarely took anyone but seafarers, longshoremen, and fishermen – anyone not accustomed to the sea tended to die too quickly.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_PROFESSIONAL_ARMY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the early medieval period, serfs and villeins formed the bulk of the armies; barely trained and ill-equipped, other than sheer numbers, they were pretty useless in battle. The idea of a state-maintained “professional” army had faded – as so much else did – with the Roman Empire (although China still had one). But as various nations coalesced out of the ruins, kings began to supplement their mobs drawn from feudal lords with paid professionals. These soldiers were usually housed in barracks and segregated from the civilian population to minimize friction, and the king provided their food, weapons, clothes, and training. They were (almost) always more effective than the amateurs.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_PROPAGANDA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Social psychologists have studied propaganda, and while it cannot change beliefs or convictions, it can reinforce these or cause doubt about other ones. Propaganda shares some techniques with two other mass-media phenomenon, advertising and public relations … and truly it is tough at times to distinguish between the three. Although there have been instances of propaganda ever since the printing press was invented, the coming of film and broadcast brought propaganda to the forefront during the first two world wars, and the subsequent Cold War. So virulent did the propaganda become that the United Nations added Article 20 to the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights in 1966 which prohibited any propaganda for war or any advocacy that could lead to violence.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_PUBLIC_TRANSPORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Public transport – in Asia, run as profit-driven, privately-owned enterprises; in the Americas, generally as government operations; in Europe, a mix of state-owned and private companies – provide inexpensive passenger services to the general public … buses, subways, trams, commuter trains, ferries, and such. The first such organized system appears to have been the omnibus service that operated in Paris commencing in 1662, but it didn’t last long. Omnibuses were reintroduced in Nantes in 1826, and in London in 1829. Shortly thereafter, as London became more crowded and unsanitary, good folk began settling in “suburbs” around the city, a development helped by the creation of the Metropolitan Railway in the 1860s which offered cheap fares into the heart of the capital. Soon, ever industrial city wanted a public transit system too.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_PUBLIC_WORKS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Public works encompass public buildings (schools, hospitals, museums, and so forth), public transport facilities (everything from roads to airports), public spaces (all those parks and squares), public services (sewers, dams, the electrical grids), and anything else (often pork barrel projects) the government might be willing to finance and construct for the “greater” good. In ancient Rome, the Opera publica oversaw construction of projects to benefit the community … all those lovely aqueducts for instance. American politicians took the lead in reviving that idea; in 1791 AD Pennsylvania launched the first comprehensive publicly financed road system, and in 1801 Philadelphia built the first public water system.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_RAID_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>To pillage, plunder, and generally demoralize a foe - there’s nothing like a raid. Since the barbarians couldn’t stand up (usually) to open battle with the armies of the Greeks, Persians, Romans, Chinese, and other civilized sorts, their incursions tended to take the form of extended raids. In time, these and other empires also used raids against the barbarians, often dispatching auxiliaries to devastate their lands … driving off their livestock, burning their camps, and worse. So well did this strategy work that some “wars” were nothing more than a series of bloody raids, and the practice became part of the military repertoire that survives even today.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_RAJ_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When the British East India Company screwed up royally and the British Royal Army had to step in to put down the Sepoy Mutiny, rule of the sub-continent was transferred to the Crown, in the person of Queen Victoria, who was declared Empress of India in June 1858. The British Raj was divided into two aspects: the regions under direct British control, and those ruled by Indian princes (under British “tutelage” of course) … some 565 princely states in 1947 when British dominion ended. Most of these princely states, while nominally sovereign, were under British control regarding their defense, external affairs, communications, transport, and trade (indeed, most of their exports went to England to pay for all this other stuff).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_RATIONALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Rationalism is the worldview that looks to reason (rather than, say, blind faith or magic mushrooms) to explain the world. In this philosophy, reason trumps all other ways of knowing things, including any data gathered by one's five senses. Its roots can be traced back to the great Socrates, but it enjoyed something of a resurgence following Christian repression during the 16th and 17th centuries during the Scientific Revolution. Scientist-philosophers such as Réne Descartes, labelled the “father of modern philosophy,” Spinoza, Leibniz, and Kant altered the way humans viewed their world in profound ways and made rationalism the new faith.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_RELIGIOUS_ORDERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Although the Buddhists (Zen, Shaolin) and Muslims (the various Sufi tariqa) have religious orders of a sort, it was Catholicism that spawned the most famous. In the Catholic Church, founding a religious order must be consecrated by the Pope … it can’t be done on a whim. The earliest that would be recognizable today was the founding of the Order of St. Augustine c. 1244 AD, cobbled together from several earlier mendicant orders of friars. By the time of the Renaissance, all sorts of holy orders were being created: Benedictines, Carmelites, Dominicans, Franciscans, Jesuits, and so forth and so on. And a number of religious orders concerned more with eliminating heathens than saving souls arose during the Crusades, such as the Knights Templar and Knights Hospitaller.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_RESOURCE_MANAGEMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The “efficient and effective development of an organization’s resources when they are needed” … resource management. As corporations grew larger and evolved into multi-national conglomerates it became vital for those wishing to survive to insure that resources were never over-allocated to projects. Perhaps the best method of doing this is “resources leveling” – financial, inventory, human, production output, and even information – avoiding both excess inventories and sudden shortages. The trick is to invest in resources as “stored capabilities” and then “unleash” these as necessary and practical. The spread of resource management principles have allowed corporations to engage in some immense, both in terms of size and duration, yet profitable projects since the 1950s.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_RETAINERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the counterfeit feudalism that prevailed in the late Middle Ages, a society organized along lines of personal service being a “retainer” was the best method to obtain favor in the form of offices, land grants, gifts, and honors from those higher up the nobility chain. In return, the gentry helped fight their lord’s wars or put down rebellions. Not only did the gentry have to fight for the king themselves, but they were required to supply an agreed upon number of lesser nobles and knights as well. These personal retainers were known collectively as the “affinity” of the lord, akin to the celebrity “posses” of today … but more reliable.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_REVELATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Religiously speaking, revelation is the revealing of some form of truth or knowledge through direct communication with a deity or other supernatural entity through various means – burning bushes, graven tablets, voices from statues, drug-induced dreams, and the list continues. Virtually every prophet from Moses to Mohammed to Joseph Smith has claimed the revelation to them personally of holy writ. Whether confabulation or fact, there is no denying that divine revelations have shaped civilization throughout the millennia. Recent scientific studies by Stanley Koren have sought to understand the phenomenon through the use of the “God helmet,” a device for stimulating the temporal lobes … perhaps soon everyone can have revelations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_SACK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since most soldiers weren’t (and aren’t) well-paid, looting was the primary source of income … for those lucky enough to survive the battles, plagues, and punishments. Unlike pillaging the countryside, the chance to sack a built-up place offered much more than mere sustenance. During the Middle Ages, a lord’s encouragement to sack a town, city, or district was the main way to insure loyalty and further willingness to fight. Even the gentry joined in the fun, often claiming the most priceless pieces and best folk to hold for ransom. The bigger and richer the city, the more to go around; thus, some places like Rome were sack-prone (410, 455, 546, 1084, and 1527 AD).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_SATELLITE_BROADCASTS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The first satellite to relay communications was “Project SCORE” in 1958 AD, which captured the world’s attention by broadcasting a greeting from President Eisenhower. Then “Project Echo” in 1960 (and again in 1964) put a passive reflector balloon in low orbit to bounce radio communications from one spot on the globe to another. Meanwhile the communications corporation AT&amp;T launched two multinational (American, British, and French) Telstar satellites, able to bounce broadcasts across the Pacific. These all laid the foundations for current satellite networks capable of sending video and audio and computer signals to anyplace in the world – leading to endless hours of distraction.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_SCRIPTURE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The oldest religious text found so far dates to ancient Sumer around 2600 BC. It was the first example of scripture, a text that is considered to be sacred or central to a religious tradition. The oldest of a still existing religion is likely the Rigveda of Hinduism, composed between 1700 and 1100 BC. The claim of God’s (whoever it may be) Word “made manifest” is an undeniable selling point to would-be converts; it is not surprising that the five largest existing religions all have a primary scripture: Buddhism (the Tripitaka), Hinduism (Vedas and Upanishads), Islam (Qur’an), Judaism (Tanakh), and Christianity (Bible).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_SERFDOM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Although forms of land bondage had been present in civilization before (such as the Roman colonate system), medieval serfdom really began with the collapse of the Carolingian Empire in the 10th century AD. In the period following, local lords needed a ready supply of agricultural labor for their manors, and the peasants needed protection against just about everybody … so the practice of serfdom spontaneously arose in various places across Europe. By the 12th and 13th centuries, serfdom had acquired a strict legal status, for serfs were not slaves and did have rights (however minimal). With the rise of powerful monarchs and central governments, serfdom became less useful, and by 1400 true serfdom was rare … except in Russia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_SIMULTANEUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the wake of the Protestant Reformation, and the mishmash of denominations across Germany, arose the 'simultaneum mixtum' (or Simultankirche), a church in which two or more differing groups (Lutheran, Congregational, Calvinist, and so forth) practice services. Each denomination worshiped at different times and with different clergy, and tolerated the other faiths sharing their space. Although, given its tenets as the “true church” (and all the bloodshed of the religious wars), Roman Catholicism did not generally engage in simultaneum … although a Catholic and Evangelical one operated for some 200 years until 1850 AD in Goldenstedt.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_SKYSCRAPERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Until the Industrial Revolution, any structure over six stories was rare indeed and likely considered a “wonder.” Known as the “grandfather of skyscrapers,” built in 1797 AD, The Flaxmill in Shrewsbury used cast-iron columns and beams to support a five-story brick construction. Sixty years later Elisha Otis invented the “safety” elevator, and architects started to think bigger. In 1885 the ten-story Home Insurance Building in Chicago was christened, incorporating a steel framework, fireproofing, elevators, and electrical wiring … all considered indispensable in modern skyscrapers. Though they don’t really scrape the sky, some of them get pretty tall, like the Burj Khalifa in Dubai at 2,722 feet (829.8 meters).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_SPORTS_MEDIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Professional and college sports have become the remedy to relieve the sheer boredom of civilization (now that most folk don’t have to worry overly about starvation, disease, and war). To feed that craving for excitement, sports journalism rose to the fore in newspapers; according to Tracy Everbach, “flamboyant sports writing in the era of yellow journalism attracted newspaper readers” by the millions. The 1920s ushered in the daily sports page, turned to first more than any section, other than the obituaries. The Associated Press soon added a sports department. In the 1930s, sports media dominated radio, and then shifted to television – with networks paying ever more enormous sums to broadcast live events. And now, sports coverage is inundating the internet.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_STRATEGIC_AIR_FORCE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In order to protect itself and its allies from the “Red Menace,” the United States merged several of the Army air forces in March 1946 AD, forming the Strategic Air Command. Establishing its headquarters on Offutt Air Force Base (near Omaha, about as far from Soviet bombers as could be found), SAC was responsible for the land-based strategic bombers that would rain nuclear destruction down in the much anticipated Armageddon. SAC initially totally 37 thousand military personnel, but continued to grow as its Soviet counterpart – in 1980, the largest air force in the world – did throughout the Cold War. And as its Soviet counterpart had, SAC was put in charge of the ICBM arsenal as well.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_STRATEGOS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the Hellenic world, a strategos meant, literally, “army leader” … although over time it came to mean a “great general.” When the Macedonians overran Greece, it was used by Philip II and his son Alexander for commanders on detached assignments as quasi-representatives of the king. Later, during the Diadochi empires, it was a gubernatorial office combining civil and military duties. In Greek-speaking Byzantium, a strategos was the supreme military officer of a field army, usually groomed from birth for the semi-hereditary position.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_SURVEY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Even prehistoric tribes had “scouts,” those hardy individuals who went out looking for better caves, hunting grounds, and sources of water. Once folk settled down and began clumping together in villages and towns, fleet-footed and eagle-eyed individuals willing to hike over the hills and trudge through trackless forests remained of vital importance, for a civilization that doesn’t know what’s going on around it is blind to both opportunities and dangers. As they surveyed the surroundings and brought back tales of fabulous wonders, scouts not only expanded possibilities, but humanity’s imagination as well.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_SYMPHONIES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Although the first symphonies – instrumental works in three or four movements scored for large orchestras – appeared in the early 1600s, it was during the 18th Century that they took on the form known today. The aristocracy, followed by the rising affluent middle-class, became fans of these extended pieces of music in cultural centers such as Vienna, Milan, and Paris, performed in 100-piece ensembles of string, brass, woodwind, and percussion instruments. Sponsors devoted fortunes to helping aspiring composers, and symphonies came to play a highly visible role in public life in Europe. In the early 19th Century, Beethoven – among others – elevated the symphony even more, from a popular but common genre to supreme musical artwork. It remains so to this day.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_THIRD_ALTERNATIVE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Third Alternative (or Third Position) is a nationalist political philosophy that emphasizes its opposition to both capitalism and communism, instead synthesizing radical ideas from both. Those following this approach favor state ownership of production and the distribution of goods and services to “the productive members of society,” peaceful segregation of ethnic and racial groups within the state, and have recently embraced radical environmentalism. Many political scientists have argued that the movement, which arose in the wake of World War II in countries such as Argentina and South Africa, is not a “third” alternative but rather a mutation of neo-fascism.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_TOTAL_WAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Ancient warfare was generally “total war,” until morality set in and rules evolved. Total war is defined as the mobilization of an entire civilization’s might and the application of that might against an entire enemy civilization – targeting not just its military, but the civilian populace and infrastructure, industrial and agricultural resources, and its will to carry on the fight. For centuries, professional armies and navies conducted “limited” warfare in colorful conflicts (and that’s not just those pretty uniforms), and chivalry and honor marked (supposedly) the battlefield. But with industrialization, the American Civil War and the even more entertaining First World War, utilizing every means to destroy one’s enemy became the preferred strategy. The Second World War was the quintessential total war (thus far).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_TOWN_CHARTERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Traditionally, the granting of a town charter gave it and its inhabitants the right to certain privileges in the feudal system. Townspeople were burghers, as opposed to serfs, and “free” in the sense that they were protected by (and owed allegiance only to) the king rather than the local manor lord. Charters also gave the burghers some semblance of self-government, in that the rich merchants would be allowed to choose a mayor and hold a market or faire under their own auspices … so long as acceptable to the king, of course. As early as the 10th Century AD, German towns were being granted town charters, with their own militia, courts, and taxes … the model for all those after.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_TRADE_CONFEDERATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As international trade recovered after the collapse of the Roman Empire, some traders found it was better to pool their resources and establish their own economic infrastructure than go it alone or trust to the government (whatever uncertain form this took). In short, the merchants of a city or region sought to establish shared trade routes, or establish monopolies in certain commodities, or both. Many of these were foundations for the more formal merchant confederations that could span several cities. Too, trade confederations tended to be shorter lived, as the death of a merchant or trader family usually ended the ad hoc and loosely organized confederation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_TRAVELING_MERCHANTS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Most villages, manors and towns in Medieval Europe were as self-sufficient as possible, so it was the more exotic and expensive luxuries in which a traveling merchant would trade. The Crusades, particularly, introduced the gentry and their vassals (those that survived the fighting) to the finer things … spices, fine woods, incenses, silk, and such. Even as the conquerors acquired a taste for these, the conquest of Palestine opened the trade routes from far corners of the East, and Italian traders were soon bringing all sorts of goods back. From the Italian and Byzantine ports, these imports were carried by traveling merchants, even to distant England and Scandinavia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_TRIANGULAR_TRADE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Triangular trade routes are those that connect three locations, each with a different commodity desired in one of the other two, in a profitable cycle of merchant voyages. As the colonial empires grew, shipping captains sought to make their trips across the Atlantic Ocean ever more efficient. One such was the British colonial route: salt fish and lumber from New England to British colonies in the West Indies, sugar and molasses from the islands to Britain, and manufactured goods from Britain to New England. But the most profitable was surely the transatlantic slave trade operating from the 1500s to 1800s; engaged in by various nations, slaves from West Africa to the Caribbean and American colonies, cash crops and raw materials from there to Europe, and manufactured goods to Africa. And repeat …</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_URBAN_PLANNING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to archeologists, there is evidence of urban planning – or at least something more than haphazard building – in a number of ancient towns found in Mesopotamia, Egypt, and the Indus Valley. They have uncovered paved streets laid out in a grid pattern, and from the 8th Century BC onward most Greek cities were laid out on orthogonal grid plans. But it was the Romans who were masters of urban planning – far more so than other civilizations. Roman city planning focused on military defense, public convenience, and ease of transport through the streets (connecting to those nice roads). As Rome declined, most of these nifty ideas disappeared for a time, although the great European cities still surround a Roman city center.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_VETERANCY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term “veteran” comes from the Latin vetus, meaning “old” (just don’t refer to one that way). Although there had been those lucky ones who had survived military service before, it was the Romans who established the practice of honoring survivors with privileges and rewards. Any non-Roman soldier honorably discharged was granted Roman citizenship (not to be taken lightly). The normal term of enlistment was 25 years, and upon discharge, both Roman and non-Roman veterans were given pensions (the praemia, established by Emperor Augustus) and land grants, usually on the frontiers. Since Roman veterans were subject to recall, the latter meant that reinforcements were never far away when barbarians invaded.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_WARS_OF_RELIGION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>One thing is guaranteed about the faithful: their willingness to kill (or die) for their beliefs. Since the ancient Mesopotamian city-states began bashing each other, religion has been the cause of many a “holy” war – the Israelite conquest of the Canaan city-states, Muslim expansion, and the subsequent Crusades. But none matched the wars of religion that were set off when Luther nailed up his 95 theses. For much of the 16th and 17th centuries, the Protestants and Catholics went at each other with abandon, devastating most of Central Europe and causing astronomical casualties – an estimated 11.5 million in the Thirty Years War and another four million in the French Wars of Religion alone.</Text>
		</Row>
	</BaseGameText>
</GameData>