<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<GameData>
	<EnglishText>		
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NUBIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Situated along the Great Bend of the Nile River in northern Africa, Nubia served as the gateway between the Red Sea and the Nile Delta—a locus of trade that could have spanned from the source of the Nile River to its mouth in the Mediterranean. Unfortunately for Nubia, the Egyptians directly to Nubia’s north had other ideas. The two civilizations would exchange roles as wary neighbor, conqueror, and vassal for millennia, until a series of invaders from distant lands permanently ended their rivalry.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NUBIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The earliest Nubian civilization began in what is today Sudan. The city-state of Kerma was located in a fertile basin just south of the Nile's Third Cataract. Kerma's ideal position beside the Nile made it a center of trade as accessible by land as it was by water. The discovery and exploitation of extensive mineral wealth such as ebony and gold cemented Kerma's ascension. With trade came wealth, and that led to raids from those who wanted wealth but were not entirely convinced that trade was the way to get it.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NUBIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Kerma fortified its city and its routes, slowly extending its influence along the Nile until its allied villages, forts, and trading posts stretched nearly 800 miles (1287 km)—roughly the distance between the First through Fifth Cataracts. At that time, they were a match for Egypt in size and influence.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NUBIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Very little of Kerma has survived since the Second Millennium BCE. If its people had a written language, it was long since lost. Most records of the kingdom exist in Egyptian texts—notably, of various minor conflicts with their Nubian neighbors. They described Kerma as a highly centralized state, but managing extensive territory without a written language is a daunting task.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NUBIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Despite the constant conflict between neighboring kingdoms, Egypt called Nubia "the Land of the Bow” after the formidable Nubian archers who formed the bulk of Kerma's forces. To understand how strong an impression these warriors left upon their opponents, one Egyptian fort subsequently built in Nubian territory was called “Warding Off the Bows”—both proclamation and aspiration.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NUBIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Kerma's strength reached its height in 1580 BCE, but an ill-fated alliance with the Hyksos led to its eventual downfall. The Hyksos were invaders from the east who seized portions of Egypt in the middle of the 17th Century BCE but found great difficulty with a rebellious populace and a surviving Egyptian dynasty based in Thebes. Kerma sought to carve up what remained, crushing Egypt once and for all.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NUBIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>It almost worked. For thirty years Kerma cut deep into Egyptian territory, taking religious and cultural artifacts for themselves, until Egypt finally overthrew and expelled their Hyksos overlords. So extensive and painful was Kerma's invasion that the Egyptians subsequently purged all records of it, along with any mention of the Hyksos "15th Dynasty." What they could not do was erase the accumulated Egyptian treasure in Kerma.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NUBIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Still, the pharaohs remembered their humiliation. Thutmosis I repaid it a century later when he captured the city of Kerma. His successor Thutmosis III pushed even further into Nubian territory, eventually proclaiming the mountain of Jebel Barkal and the nearby city of Napata the new southern border of Egypt.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NUBIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Nubia spent roughly four centuries under Egyptian rule. There were many rebellions, of course, but as time passed Nubian and Egyptian cultures intermingled. Kerma faded and the loyal province of Nubia eventually became the source of Egypt's gold, its route to the Red Sea, and its archers—now feared by Egypt's enemies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NUBIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>By the 10th Century BCE, Egypt's focus on Mediterranean affairs (and the subsequent collapse of Egypt’s New Kingdom) left Nubia to its own affairs. Slowly, over the next few centuries, the Kingdom of Kush rose to prominence when Libyan princes subjugated an overextended Egypt.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NUBIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>In a strange twist of fate, the Kushite King Piye proclaimed divine mandate by the god Amun—an Egyptian god whose temple at Jebel Barkal was constructed by Egyptian pharaoh Thutmosis III—to liberate Lower Egypt from its Libyan interlopers. And with that, the Nubian king seized control of the Nile Delta, formed the 25th Dynasty, and sought to restore Egypt to its former glory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NUBIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>For a time, it did. Piye and his successors made it a priority to rebuild the monuments, temples, and public works that had long since languished under foreign control. This revitalization of Egyptian culture was the 25th Dynasty’s greatest accomplishment—but not a lasting one.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NUBIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_13">
			<Text>No matter how small the wasp’s nest, it is rarely a good idea to give it a swift kick. This lesson was lost on multiple pharaohs of the 25th Dynasty who sought to extend their influence into the Near East. This put them in conflict with the powerful Neo-Assyrian Empire who considered the Near East its vassals. (Piye’s support of Canaan’s rebellion against their Neo-Assyrian overlords did not help matters.) Neo-Assyria’s King Esarhaddon made his position abundantly clear when he invaded Egypt in 674 BCE. In three short years, the invaders had deposed the 25th Dynasty, permanently ending Nubia’s flirtations with empire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NUBIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_14">
			<Text>Nubia’s withdrawal from Egypt ultimately worked out in their favor—after Neo-Assyria’s example, other Mediterranean powers would find Egypt a tempting candidate for vassal. A prudent relocation of Nubia’s capital from Napata to the more distant Meroe provided access to the Greek traders on the Red Sea, then far more lucrative than trade along the Nile. It also discouraged invasion from the north—neither Persia, Macedon, nor Ptolemaic Egypt made any serious effort to extend into the Meroitic Kingdom of Kush.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NUBIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_15">
			<Text>Then, in 25 BCE, Nubia fell afoul of Rome. The Roman general Petronius repeatedly clashed with Nubia’s one-eyed Kandake (or “queen”) Amanirenas. After Roman forces sacked Napata and razed the Temple of Amun to the ground, Amanirenas’s resistance was ferocious enough to convince Petronius that peace was more favorable than conquest. Augustus Caesar signed a peace treaty with Kush that was surprisingly favorable to Nubia, treating them as a friendly protectorate rather than a former belligerent.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_NUBIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_16">
			<Text>Following this period of Roman destruction came the dawn of the Meroitic builders, begun in 1 BCE by Kandake Amanitore (her story is detailed elsewhere). This time of rebuilding ended when the Beja dynasty to their northeast captured Meroe in the 1st Century. Despite attempts by the Beja to expand Nubia, internal rebellion and conflict with the Kingdom of Aksum led to their eventual and permanent conquest.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMANITORE_QUOTE">
			<Text>Provide what the land does not. Your people will love you for it.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMANITORE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Kandake Amanitore ruled Nubia at the turning of an era. A powerful queen, feared by her enemies and beloved by her people, she was one of the last great builders of the Kingdom of Kush. Amanitore restored the Land of the Bow to its greatness following a period of turmoil. Her rule was long and her works lasting.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMANITORE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>At least, that is what historians have pieced together. Two millennia and one dead language later, there is little surviving written record of Amanitore in the form of scrolls or other documents. What remains is carved into the very stone of the buildings she left behind.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMANITORE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The most nebulous aspect of Amanitore's life is who she was before she became queen. Indeed, her personality is a cypher. We can only interpret. One abstract depiction of the kandake shows her mercilessly slaying enemies she has already subjugated. Was it from an actual incident where she ordered the execution of rebels, or propaganda proclaiming her righteous vengeance against those who would be enemies of the state?</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMANITORE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Even then, her actual role as queen is difficult to pin down. Conflicting accounts of her co-ruler Natakamani depict him as either her husband or her son, though thankfully never both. Furthermore, Amanitore succeeded Kandake Amanishakheto, who was either her mother-in-law (if Natakamani was Amanitore's husband), her actual mother (if Natakamani was Amanitore's son), or some other form of relation lost to time.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMANITORE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>The fuzzy details of Amanitore's lineage are less important than the role she held. The title of kandake—or “candace,” as the Romans called it—roughly translates to “queen-mother,” but it did not equate to a regent ruling on behalf of an heir too young to hold power. Instead, the kandakes were independent queens who ruled alone with husband consorts or with kings in a form of co-rulership.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMANITORE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Amanitore's reign took the latter form, with Natakamani as her equal. There is scant information on any aspect of her life before she became queen (around 1 BCE). Still, monuments always depict both co-rulers as adults, so she was likely in her prime when her rule began. In fact, the depictions of Amanitore and Natakamani deliberately present the two as equivalent, particularly in religious buildings, which was uncommon for the time.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMANITORE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>With Egypt a Roman vassal and Rome on amicable terms with Nubia, no regional conflicts threatened Amanitore's reign. The relatively peaceful time and the collaborative autonomy of co-rulership let Amanitore pursue what would become her legacy—an extended period of building that brought great prosperity to the Meroitic kingdom. Among her works were the construction of Nubian pyramids and tombs, restoration of Amun's temple in Meroe, and infrastructure projects, such as the reservoirs built near the capital.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMANITORE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Amanitore also rebuilt the temple of Amun at Napata—the same temple that Roman invaders had destroyed just two decades prior. As Amanitore’s name incorporated the name of the god Amun, it is reasonable to assume its restoration was a point of pride for the busy queen. Indeed, her efforts helped revive Jebel Barkal to at least a fraction of its former glory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMANITORE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Although the queen enjoyed cordial relations with Rome, the decades-earlier reprisal raids into Egyptian (which is to say, "Roman") territory had recovered bronze statues of Augustus Caesar as spoils of war. An apocryphal tale describes Amanitore burying the decapitated head of one such statue beneath temple stairs in Meroe so Nubians would always walk over the Roman emperor responsible for razing Napata. (It was most likely Kandake Amanirenas, her predecessor, who actually did this.) Whether or not she was actually responsible for its burial, the "Meroe head" of Augustus Caesar was recovered in the early 20th Century—found beneath a flight of temple steps.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMANITORE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text> As with the confusion surrounding Amanitore's ascension, we know very little about the end of her reign. Some estimates put the date of her death at roughly 20 CE. Treasure hunters have long since plundered her tomb in Meroe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMANITORE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>Despite the many unknown aspects of Amanitore, the extensive building program she left behind inspired later kandakes to expand upon her work, which in turn led to a flourishing of Meroitic culture and fortunes through the Second Century. Archaeologists continue to uncover examples of her influence, including a set of recently unearthed Nubian pyramids built during her reign.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMANITORE_CHAPTER_CAPSULE_BODY">
			<Text>Nubia is the Land of the Bow, and their civ’s archers are second to none.  Amanitore led the historical Nubians on their greatest building spree; she does the same here with her fascination with city planning and district construction.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMANITORE_CHAPTER_DETAILED_BODY">
			<Text>Nubia will want to scout aggressively for desert tiles while rushing toward Masonry.  With that technology in hand, they can place down their cities, always striving for a cluster of their pyramids in the center.  Districts placed next to these pyramids will provide amplified yields, powering the civ’s development.  Finding mines is also a key priority: historically all the mineral riches enjoyed by Egypt came from Nubia and this civilization can get rich from minerals as well.  And if they need to defend their cities, they have the world's best ranged units who should easily be up to the task.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_BUILDING_JEBEL_BARKAL_QUOTE">
			<Text>“At the south-west corner a large perpendicular mass of sandstone has become separated by a deep fissure from the body of the mountain … it has all the appearance of a colossal statue.”[NEWLINE]– E. A. Wallis Budge</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_JEBEL_BARKAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A lonely mountain rises from the flat Sudanese desert, west of a bend in the Nile. At its base once stood a palace where ancient kingdoms ruled for centuries. Now, there are only ruins.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_JEBEL_BARKAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Easily recognizable from a great distance, the flat-topped mountain of Jebel Barkal was a waypoint for travelers in ancient times. It indicated a point of relatively safe crossing (just downstream of the Nile's Fourth Cataract). After the Fifteenth Century BCE, it also noted the location of Napata, Egypt's southernmost border city that, 500 years later, would become the capital of the Nubian Kingdom of Kush.</Text>
		</Row>		
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_JEBEL_BARKAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Since the 19th Century, archaeologists have excavated a wealth of historical information from Jebel Barkal including temple ruins, stonework carved into the mountain, and ancient inscriptions dating back to the Egyptian occupation of the region. The Nubian pyramids in the shadow of the mountain later served as tombs for Meroitic kings and queens.</Text>
		</Row>		
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_NUBIAN_PITATI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The skill of Nubian archers was long respected and feared along the Nile. These soldiers from the Land of the Bow were a thorn in Egypt’s side for millennia—until the Egyptians solved yet another problem by throwing money at it.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_NUBIAN_PITATI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Thus came about the pítati, Nubian mercenaries paid well to guard the interests of their benefactors, be they Egyptian or Nubian. These highly mobile archers wore little armor and carried bows typical to the region. However, their distinctive thumb rings greatly reduced fatigue, and malachite facepaint applied below their eyes allowed them to loose arrows with accuracy while firing into the sun.</Text>
		</Row>		
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_PYRAMID_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>During their on-again/off-again periods of mutual conflict, Nubia found its culture influenced by the powerful Egyptian dynasties further down the Nile. Nubian burial customs would eventually come to resemble those of Egypt. Nubia’s Kingdom of Kush began burying its kings and queens in pyramids sometime in the First Millennium BCE.</Text>
		</Row>	
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_PYRAMID_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Nubia took a vastly different approach to its pyramids than Egypt. Rather than build immense tomb complexes that bankrupted their state, they opted for a more practical method: smaller pyramids with no more than a 26 ft (8 m) wide base, steep sides that rose at a sharp angle in the air, and an ornate entry chamber that extended from the pyramid tomb. Though treasure hunters plundered most of these pyramids since Nubia's fall, the pyramids remain a powerful testament to Nubia's legacy.</Text>
		</Row>			
	</EnglishText>
</GameData>