<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<BaseGameText>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_INTRO_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
      <Text>In Civilization VI, buildings are no longer trapped in your city center, but may sprawl across your territory as part of districts. The map is more important than ever as you are faced with important strategic placement decisions. Campuses and Holy Site’s alike receive special boosts from placement near Mountains, but only the former also benefits from a nearby source of Rainforest.</Text>
    </Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_CITY_CENTER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The political, cultural, historical, commercial, and geographic heart of a city … at least, that’s the theory. In different areas of the world, as villages grew into towns and towns into cities, different aspects of these symbiotic qualities of civilization became emphasized, usually without forethought. A lot is revealed about a people by wandering around the city center. Rarely do folk actually live in the city center (until the advent of skyscrapers and condos); instead it is the “downtown” where the personality of the city is on display, with its spectacular monuments, grand parks, towering offices, pretentious government buildings, and the like. Often it encompasses the first settled part (the simple homes now leveled by urban renewal) and so is the most historic district of the now sprawling city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_HOLY_SITE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In god-driven civilizations, it is not unknown for religious “districts” to evolve in some cities, where all the shrines, temples, monasteries, altars, churches huddle together. Often, these seem to spring up on a holy site, the place of some miracle, vision, or revelation. The holiest site in Islam, centered on the Kaaba, is one such. Jerusalem is an epicenter for holy sites. Then there’s the Roman Catholic Vatican, a whole holy city built in the midst of Rome. And folk still make pilgrimages to such sites, such as the Hajj to Mecca or the Sikhs’ daily prayer to visit the Golden Temple at Amritsar or the fervent wish to see the Temple Mount by the Chosen People.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_CAMPUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term “campus” is the Latin word for “field,” and was first applied to the grounds of what would become Princeton University founded in 1746 AD; the word has since come to be applied to the usually landscaped setting of any institution of higher learning (and, sometimes, to pretentious corporate office complexes). The tradition of the campus as a special district devoted to learning has its roots in 12th Century European schools where instructors and students lived together in a self-regulating, cloistered settlement. Those early campuses with their collective rights and legal privileges were often guaranteed by charters from princes or prelates, with the land “donated” by the town in which they were located.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_ENCAMPMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When an ancient ruler decided he needed a professional army – rather than a bunch of well-meaning farmers armed with pointed sticks – there needed to be someplace to put it when it wasn’t out dealing death and mayhem. Since it wouldn’t do to have the soldiers mingle with average folk, encampments were established to lodge and train the troops. Often fortified, containing all that was necessary for the well-being of the army – barracks, stables, stores, training grounds, and so forth – these encampments could be quite impressive; at the height of the Roman Empire, a standardized military camp could house and care for an entire legion. Indeed, Roman law and tradition forbade any legion from even entering the city – not a bad idea, until Lucius Sulla marched his legions in and declared himself dictator in 87 BC.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_HARBOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Safe haven, shelter from storms, place to rest and refit, harbor. As soon as men went sailing, the need for harbors became evident. Early civilizations sought out natural harbors, and history has been often defined by where these maritime settlements sat. In time, breakwaters, jetties, seawalls, lighthouses, and drydocks were added, and the seabed was dredged if necessary to keep the harbor open. The harbors were the centers of trade and naval war, the launch point for exploration and end point for immigration. As technology developed, “artificial” harbors could now be built to handle modern merchant ships – such as Long Beach Harbor, created from salt marshes and tidal flats – using concrete, steel, dredge barges, and pumping stations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_AERODROME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>An aerodrome is a place where, well, aeroplanes take off and land. Technically, according to the International Civil Aviation Organization, an “aerodrome” is “a defined area on land or water … intended to be used wholly or in part for the arrival, departure, and surface movement of aircraft.” The first such district to fit that description wholly was located in Viry-Châtillon, a suburb of Paris. In those early days of flight, any open, relatively flat, grassy field would serve … and did. Which meant, unlike the present, that planes could land and take-off in any direction, adjusting for the wind direction and weather conditions, requiring nothing more than a wind-sock or flag. Then someone had the clever idea of adding paved runways, and all that landing and taking-off got far more complicated.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_COMMERCIAL_HUB_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The “commercial hub” of a city usually refers to the downtown business district, where capitalism and greed enliven the city’s finances. Here are the markets, banks and exchanges that make a few folks rich and fuel city growth. In time, evolving from a simple collection of local financiers and corporate offices, a commercial hub might even grow into a “global financial center.” There is even a system for ranking such global centers; until 2013 London held the top spot on the Global Financial Centers Index, when it was supplanted by New York City, both closely followed by Hong Kong, Singapore, and Tokyo. The quest for profit is obviously a universal trait of civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_ENTERTAINMENT_COMPLEX_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The “entertainment” district offers family-friendly distractions from the burden of living in an urban environment. In some cities, the entertainment complex is filled with museums and zoos and other edifying sights; in others it is a district of theaters, pubs, music venues and such; and some are the center of the city’s sport with stadiums and indoor arenas. Whatever the form – be it the Quartier des Spectacles in Montreal, or Te Aro District in Wellington, or even St. Pauli in Hamburg – every civilized city has one to engender happiness and pride in its citizens, imparting a sense of social identity that the countryside can’t.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_THEATER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As the urban middle-class took on aspects of being “cultured” in the late 19th Century, it demanded more refined entertainments than bear-baiting and bare-knuckle boxing. Theater districts were the answer, usually clustering around existing theaters and museums patronized by the upper-class. Thus New York City’s Broadway district saw a number of new music halls and restaurants open immediately after the Metropolitan Opera House relocated to West 39th and Broadway in 1883. In the earlier 1800s, London’s West End theater district expanded outward from the Royal Opera House in Covent Garden. In time, all those that feed off theatrical talent were also found in the theater districts: recording studios, radio studios, agents, producers, and so forth.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_INDUSTRIAL_ZONE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>An industrial zone (sometimes euphemistically termed an industrial “park”) is where the “heavyweight” manufacturing and shipping takes place in modern civilization. Long before the Industrial Revolution, it was common to locate the most noisy, odoriferous, and dangerous workshops – the tanners, smelters, slaughterhouses, etc. – outside the city walls. No one wanted to live near those. Inevitably, heavy transport evolved to carry raw materials in and finished products out of these districts; today industrial zones are nexus for highways, railroads, airports, and seaports. The infrastructure grew with the zones: warehouses, power plants, water towers, pipelines, and communications networks. And the industrial zones kept growing as industry grew; Upgrader Alley outside Edmonton, for instance, covers 318 square kilometers (some 123 square miles).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_NEIGHBORHOOD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mr. Rodgers lived in an idealized one, as do Big Bird and Cookie Monster. In truth, neighborhoods are rarely such functional social networks with friendly values, aspirations, and culture. With the advent of the Industrial Revolution, for the first time more people lived in cities than the countryside; given that transport was limited and slow, overcrowded and unsanitary tenements grew in places like London, New York, and Berlin so the factory workers and office clerks could be near their place of employment. Then came the telephone and automobile; suddenly those middle-class wage slaves could escape the teeming slums and ghettos and move to the suburbs. By the 1880s, London was surrounded by planned “estates” such as Wembley Park and Kingsbury Garden Village … and soon so were most other industrial cities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_AQUEDUCT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The remains of aqueducts – man-made watercourses – have been found scattered about ancient settlements around the world … Egypt, India, Persia, Greece, Azteca, and especially across the once-Roman lands. Over 415 kilometers (about 258 miles) of aqueducts brought fresh water to the metropolis of Rome for drinking and bathing. These Roman aqueducts were marvels of engineering (considering the times) and often roofed, so also serving as bridges where they crossed ravines and waterways. Although there were some health issues involved in the design of aqueducts (notably the sometime use of lead to line them), in general a supply of relatively-clean water was a boon to any town hoping to grow into a city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_SPACEPORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The image of a spaceport (or cosmodrome) as a gateway to the stars is evocative of adventure and discovery, of the next “great frontier” for civilization. The reality is much more prosaic: a place to launch (and maybe eventually land) rockets, much like a seaport for ships or airport for planes. Like those, a spaceport consists of derricks, cranes, administration buildings, control centers, fuel tanks and the working infrastructure. The world’s first permanent facility for orbital, manned launches was Baikonur – which had started as a Soviet military test range – in 1955 AD. Spurred by that the United States soon converted the Air Force Missile Test Center at Cape Canaveral to launch sub-orbital and then orbital rocket test flights … and the space race was on.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_ACROPOLIS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In ancient Greece, acropolis meant, quite literally, “upper city.” And in Athens, Corinth, Argos, Thebes, and elsewhere, that’s exactly what it was – a portion of the town built upon an elevated area, often a hill with steep slopes, that was eminently defensible. Should the outer walls fall to invaders, a final stand could be made in the acropolis. In time, in many places, the old acropolis became the nucleus of a sprawling new city. During the Archaic Period in Greece, as the cities grew and the threat of barbarians lessened, these old upper districts underwent urban renewal, with temples, theaters, forums, palaces, government buildings and the like replacing the humble houses, markets, barracks and squares that once occupied the summit.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_BATH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In old Rome, the thermae were large bath complexes; while many Roman villas and palaces had private, heated baths, the thermae were public, open to all harried, dirty citizens who needed to relax and get clean. Although layout varied greatly from Roman city to Roman city, in general each had an atrium for relaxation and exercise, a caldarium (hot bath), a tepidarium (warm bath), a frigidarium (cool bath), as well as apodyterium (dressing room) and the like. The really nice ones also had a sudatorium (moist steam bath) and laconium (dry steam bath). The women’s baths were almost as elaborate, and more highly decorated with murals and mosaics. After a long day at the Colosseum watching the slaughter, there must have been nothing as luxurious as a visit to the local thermae.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_HANSA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>From the Old French meaning “company of merchants,” the Hanse was a voluntary confederation of merchants and traders organized in a town for the protection and facility of commerce and transport. In the mercantile ports of the Baltic and North Sea these manufacturing and trading guilds became quite powerful and influential in the 13th Century, with their headquarters in complexes also known as the hansa. The largest hansa districts not only housed the administrative offices of competing guilds, but also storerooms, workshops, markets, banks and anything else that could turn a profit. The first such appears to have been built in Lubeck c. 1159 AD to facilitate trade between Western Europe and the resource-rich areas of northern Russia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_LAVRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the Eastern Orthodox tradition, a lavra (such as found at Mount Athos in Greece or Neamț in Romania) is a cloistered monastery of cells for hermits with a central church and/or rectory. Perhaps the most famous is the Alexander Nevsky Lavra (trust the Russians to name a holy place after a warrior) in St. Petersburg where many eminent but dead Russians are buried – besides Nevsky, there’s Euler, Suvarov, Mussorgsky, Tchaikovsky, Dostoevsky and others. Believed to have its origins in the early 4th Century AD, the first lavra seems to have been a settlement of some 600 hermits around Nitria in the Egyptian desert. In the strict Eremitic tradition, these hermit-monks lived a secluded life devoted to prayer, often accompanied by vows of silence, chastity, meditation and/or fasting. Further proof of the lengths to which some of the faithful will resort to be saved.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_MBANZA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mbanza is Kongolese for “city,” or in some cases simply “settlement.” By the time the Portuguese arrived in central Africa, M’banza Kongo was already a large city, rich from trade and craft manufacturing, but most of the population lived in the valleys that surrounded it in residential neighborhoods – perhaps as many as 100 thousand people. While these small towns might have a market and a workshop, the important things – churches, palace, schools, clinics, and tax offices – were located in the hilltop capital. They were linked to M’banza Kongo by several roads up the slopes, and these were quite crowded at times such as feast and tax days. All this in 1648 AD according to the visitor Francesco da Roma. So not only did the Kongolese give civilization suburbia but also “rush hour.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_STREET_CARNIVAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Many cities have street carnivals – especially during the Christian season of Lent – but only Brazilians really know how to cast care to the wind during such festivals. Parades, concerts, performances, masques, and public banquets (along with liberal amounts of alcohol) fuel the celebrations. According to stuffy postmodern sociologists, Carnival as a social institution provides more than just a respite from the seriousness of urban life, it serves as a release for natural impulses that threaten the social order and allows marginalized groups to focus attention on social conflicts by embodying them in “senseless” activities. Whatever the truth of this interpretation, Rio de Janeiro’s is the world’s largest street carnival, hosting upwards of two million participants a day in recent years.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_ROYAL_NAVY_DOCKYARD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Officially designated “HM Royal Dockyards” until the late 1960s, the British Navy maintained a string of facilities around the world where its commissioned ships could be based, overhauled, refitted and repaired (if things afloat went wrong). The first, a shipbuilding yard as well as a dockyard, was designated such at Portsmouth in 1496 AD, just in time to bedevil the Spanish and French for the next couple centuries. The first outside the confines of Great Britain: the Royal Dockyard at English Harbor in Antigua in 1728. Through the Dutch Wars, Napoleonic Wars, colonial wars, and two world wars the Royal Dockyards did (not to mix metaphors overly) yeoman service. But with the reduced role of the Royal Navy and the erosion of the empire, in the latter part of the 20th Century those Royal Dockyards that remain open have been largely converted to accommodation and training of naval personnel.</Text>
		</Row>
	</BaseGameText>
</GameData>