<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<BaseGameText>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_INTRO_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
      <Text>Wonders are the spectacular buildings, inventions, and concepts that have stood the test of time and changed the world forever. Wonders require time, energy, and effort to complete, but once constructed, they provide your civilization with many benefits.</Text>
    </Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_TITLE">
			<Text>Historical Context</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_ALHAMBRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Alhambra began as a small fortress, constructed in 889 AD by the Moors of Granada in Andalusia (Spain); then it was rebuilt and expanded by the emir Mohammed ben Al-Ahmar in the 11th Century and yet again expanded and converted into a royal palace by Sultan Yusuf I in 1333. The al-Hamra (literally, “the red one”), so named for its red clay fortress walls, was lavish – at least by European standards of the time – with all the comforts, including indoor plumbing. It integrated the natural beauty of the spot with structures and gardens designed and outfitted by the finest Muslim, Jewish, and even Christian craftsmen and artisans of the region. Among its most striking aspects, many of the interior walls and columns are inscribed in carved flowing Arabic script with poetry and verses from the Quran. The last sultan of the Nasrid dynasty, Muhammad XII, surrendered Granada to the Spanish in 1492 AD, without the Alhambra being attacked by the crusaders – otherwise it would be just another pile of rubble and memories of elegance.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_BIG_BEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The giant bell, Big Ben, is housed in the Elizabethan Tower – so named to celebrate the Diamond Jubilee of Queen Elizabeth II (being just the “Clock Tower” before that) – at the north end of the Palace of Westminster, where sits the Houses of Parliament. Being rather casual in language, most Brits and flocks of tourists tend to refer to the whole thing as “Big Ben.” The great 16-ton bell was cast in August 1856 at the foundry at Stockton-on-Tees and recast at the Whitechapel Bell Foundry in April 1858 after it cracked while being transported to London. The pendulum clockwork was designed by the Astronomer Royal and crafted by the clockmaker Edward Dent and his stepson Frederick; it was ready in 1854. So fine is the precision, that adding or removing a penny (English, of course) to the pendulum will change the speed by four-tenths of a second each day. But all had to await the completion of the clock tower itself, which wasn’t done until 1859. Despite being silenced during wartime and the occasional breakdown, Big Ben has chimed the hour ever since.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_BOLSHOI_THEATRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Imperial Bolshoi Theatre of Moscow – bolshoi being the Russian for “grand” – is home for the Bolshoi Ballet and Bolshoi Opera companies, among the oldest and largest in the world (the ballet has some 200 dancers). The ballet company was founded in March 1776 by Prince Urusov and Michael Maddox, a British theater manager; after performing in private homes for some years, the company was profitable enough to acquire the Petrovka Theater and opened there for the first time in December 1780. Sadly, the Petrovka burned down in 1805, to be replaced by the New Arbat Theater, which burned down in 1812 during Napoleon’s occupation of the city. The current Bolshoi Theater was built between 1821 and 1824, and it managed not to burn down – although it was renovated in 1843, 1856, 1921, 2002 and 2011. The last renovation included restoring the theater’s acoustics to the original high quality (which had been mucked up by the Soviets) and restoring the original imperial décor (which had been ripped out by those same Soviets). Despite prices ranging up to 5000 rubles, ballet and opera performances continue to be sold out – mostly to tourists.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_BROADWAY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Broadway is a 15-mile long thoroughfare through the heart of Manhattan and the Bronx in New York City, lined with offices, shops and apartments … but no-one thinks of those. Instead, Broadway is best known for the middle section between 42nd and 53rd Streets dubbed the “Great White Way” – the Theater District. Commencing in the mid-1800s a number of theaters opened on Broadway. In 1880 AD a stretch between Madison and Union squares was illuminated with arc lamps, making it one of the first electrically lit streets in the United States (leave it to New Yorkers to light up theaters before homes, hospitals and schools). Spurred by growing American wealth and cultural aspirations, the theaters made it a mecca of popular entertainment. By 1900 some 20 theaters had opened along this stretch, and so bright were their electric billboards that it became the Great White Way. In 1925 at its peak popularity, there were 80 theaters along Broadway, specializing in lavish productions, primarily revues and musicals.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_CHICHEN_ITZA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Mayans decided to build their great city of stone in the Yucatan in the middle of a jungle instead of on some nice beach. Whatever the logic of selecting such a spot, Chichen Itza was a metropolis of homes, temples, palaces, courtyards and ballcourts of extraordinary artistry; some of the ornamented structures date back 1500 years. The ball games were a special time in the city, as the winning captain was beheaded at the end of the play as a sacrifice to the gods (seems like a perfect reason to “throw” the game), possibly at the massive stepped-pyramid Temple of Kukulcan. Chichen Itza was a thriving concern until the 13th Century, when revolt and civil war broke out among the Mayans, at which point the city went into a steep decline from which it never recovered. What war didn’t take care of among the populace, disease and famine did. The center of the city was largely abandoned and in ruins by the time of the Spanish conquest.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_COLOSSEUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Flavian Amphitheater, better known as the “Coliseum” lies in the center of Rome. Construction began during the reign of Emperor Vespasian, c. 72 AD, funded by the spoils from the Jewish Second Temple after the fall of Jerusalem during the First Jewish-Roman War. Built of concrete and stone, it is the largest amphitheater ever built, and one of the great wonders of ancient architecture and engineering. It could hold between 50 and 80 thousand spectators to watch gladiatorial matches, animal hunts, mass executions, and more. By the time medieval Christianity had taken root, it had been repurposed to house low-rent apartments, workshops, quarters for a religious order, a quarry and a Christian shrine. Although knocked about by earthquakes and pillaged by stone-robbers, the Coliseum is still pretty impressive two millennia after the inaugural gladiatorial slaughter.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_COLOSSUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Built from the smelted-down brass and iron of abandoned arms and equipment of a failed invasion, the Colossus of Rhodes was a 98-foot depiction of the Titan Helios erected to celebrate the victory. Construction under the direction of Chares of Lindos began in 292 BC, and by 280 was completed, to the amazement of all. Although the details are a bit hazy – the ancient histories being what they are – the towering statue overlooked the Mandraki harbor entrance set upon a 49-foot high marble pedestal. But it only stood for 56 years before being toppled by an earthquake. Ptolemy III of Egypt offered to pay for its reconstruction, but the Rhodians refused because the Delphi Oracle informed them that the gods were offended by it. Though the gods may have been offended, for nearly 900 years the rusting ruins of the statue were a tourist “must-see.” In 653 AD the forces of the Muslim caliph Muawiyah I overran Rhodes, and the new owners promptly sold it for scrap to Jewish merchants, who used – it is said – 900 camels to haul the mass away. From scrap to scrap.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_CRISTO_REDENTOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The largest art deco statue in the world, Cristo Redentor (“Christ the Redeemer”) stands atop Corcovado Mountain 2300 feet above Rio de Janeiro, keeping a watchful eye on the sinners of that city. With arms spread wide to embrace the city sprawling below in spectacular disorder, this statue of Christ stands 98 feet tall, with the arms measuring 92 feet from fingertip to fingertip. It was sculpted by the Frenchman Paul Landowski, and built of reinforced concrete and soapstone. The idea of putting a giant statue of Christ above the city was first proposed by the Catholic priest Pedro Boss; proposed again in 1920 by the “Catholic Circle” of Rio, the group raised the necessary funds from donations, mostly from devout Brazilian Catholics (of course). Construction began in 1922, and the monument opened to the public in October 1931.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_EIFFEL_TOWER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Named after Alexandre Gustave Eiffel, whose company built the gigantic steel tower to serve as the main entrance for the 1889 Exposition Universelle (world’s fair) in Paris, the Eiffel Tower has come to symbolize the “City of Lights.” (And as garishly illuminated as the tower is at night, this seems fitting.) It was the tallest structure in the world at the time it opened to awestruck crowds, but it was also the subject of considerable controversy and criticism from self-appointed arbitrators of culture. Before it was even built a 300-member committee made up of some of the most prominent French engineers and artists dispatched a petition to the Minister of Works that opened: “We, writers, painters, sculptors, architects and passionate devotees of the hitherto untouched beauty of Paris, protest with all our strength, with all our indignation in the name of slighted French taste, against the erection … of this useless and monstrous Eiffel Tower.” Many were also upset that it was going to cost French taxpayers a million dollars – a not inconsiderable sum at the time. Luckily for the Parisian Tourism Board, the protests were ignored and up the Eiffel Tower went.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_ESTADIO_DO_MARACANA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Officially the Estadio Jornalista Mario Filho – must have been a heck of a sports writer to get a stadium named after him – but better known as the Maracanã, the fútbol stadium is part of a large complex in the heart of Rio de Janeiro. Begun in 1948 AD, after Brazil had won the right to host the FIFA World Cup, it was opened (more-or-less, for construction was not complete) for the first matches in that contest in 1950. Unfortunately, heavily favored Brazil was upset in the final by the team from Uruguay, 2-1, before a crowd of 199,854 rabid fans – making it the world’s largest (and loudest) stadium at the time. Since then the Maracanã has served as host to the Pan-American Games, another World Cup, numerous concerts and cultural events, and thousands of soccer matches. Having been renovated to a smaller capacity (78,838) and more comfortable accommodations (including 292 new toilets), the stadium hosted the Olympics (Summer, obviously) for the first time in 2016.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_FORBIDDEN_CITY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Lying in the center of Beijing, a visit to Gu Gong (the Imperial Palace of China) was forbidden to the common folk without special dispensation from the emperor himself; hence the complex became known across the land as the “Forbidden City” (much like most presidential residences these days). Construction of the walled “city” – liberally sprinkled with ornamental gardens, graceful terraces, restful fountains and lots of utilitarian administrative offices – began in 1408 AD under the guidance of the Yonglu Emperor, third of the Ming dynasty. The complex grew over the centuries, serving as home to 24 emperors of the Ming and Qing. It grew until it encompassed 9,999 rooms spread over 178 square acres, surrounded by a 170-foot wide moat and 32-foot high walls (just to make sure none of those commoners entered unchecked). At its peak, the Forbidden City was home to ten thousand people, all to serve the needs of one emperor. Now only a few hundred inhabit the sumptuous grounds, to serve as guides and janitors.</Text>
		</Row>					
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_GREAT_LIBRARY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>It is generally assumed that the Royal Library of Alexandria was founded at the beginning of the 3rd Century BC during the reign of Ptolemy II after his father had built the Temple of the Muses on the site. The original collection is attributed to Demetrius Phalereus, a student of Aristotle’s (supposedly the famed philosopher’s own scrolls served as the seed); with the patronage of Ptolemy’s successors, the holdings eventually reached between 400 and 700 thousand papyrus scrolls and various vellum codices. Expansion of the collection became an obsession for some of the rulers; by decree of Ptolemy III, all visitors to the city had to surrender any writings in their possession, which were copied for the Library. Sources differ widely on responsibility for the fiery destruction of the Great Library’s collection of texts; usual suspects listed include Julius Caesar’s troops in 48 BC, Roman Emperor Aurelian c. 270 AD, and others. But it does appear that the last vestiges were burned in 391 at the orders of the Patriarch Theophilus to eradicate pagan influences in Egypt – not the last time Christians would burn books.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_GREAT_LIGHTHOUSE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Great Lighthouse of Alexandria (one of the seventeen cities the egotistical young general named after himself), known to the ancients as the Pharos, was reputed to stand between 393 and 450 feet high – making it one of the tallest structures in civilization for many centuries. Begun in 280 BC by Ptolemy Sotor, one of Alexander’s Macedonian generals and successors, on a small island to help guide trade ships into the harbor of the thriving city, the Lighthouse was not completed until 247 at the phenomenal cost of 800 talents. Its light at the top of the massive tower was produced by a furnace reputedly made of solid blocks of limestone, and was visible for one hundred miles. Although badly damaged by three earthquakes between 956 and 1323 AD, it did not topple over – making it the third-longest surviving of the ancient wonders. Finally, the sultan of Egypt quarried the remaining stone (some had fallen into the harbor) to build the Citadel of Qaitbay in 1480 to protect Alexandria against the Ottoman Turks (didn’t work).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_GREAT_ZIMBABWE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to one set of legends, Great Zimbabwe was the palace complex of the Queen of Sheba. According to another set, it was where the laborers of King Solomon’s Mines – which were thought nearby by a generation of deluded treasure hunters – relaxed during their time off. In point of boring fact, it was the capital city, eventually covering some 1700 acres with a peak population of around 18 thousand, of the Kingdom of Zimbabwe which arose in 1220 AD and was gone by 1450 AD. Built entirely of stone (quite a feat in the jungle), Great Zimbabwe was soon afterward abandoned and fell into ruin. The earliest known record of the ruins is by the Portuguese officer Vicente Pegado, written in 1531. He makes mention of great walls, made of chiseled stone fitted without mortar. The ruins lie in three groupings: the Hill Complex, the Valley Complex, and the Great Enclosure, where the majority of the archaeological artifacts have been found: soapstone figurines, gold beads, copper ingots, bronze spearheads, jeweled pendants and bracelets, and much else. So, maybe those treasure hunters weren’t so deluded after all.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_HAGIA_SOPHIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The city of Istanbul (or Constantinople or Byzantium, as one prefers) has been home to many peoples, although best known in its role as capital for the Byzantine and then the Ottoman empires. And it has been home to many faiths, most notably Eastern Orthodox Christianity and Islam respectively. Nothing personifies that personality disorder under one dome so well as the fabulous Hagia Sophia (literally, “holy wisdom”). Built around 532 AD as the Greek Orthodox patriarchal basilica, it has served worshipers for almost 1500 years. In 1453 when Constantinople was captured by the Ottomans and renamed, the Hagia Sophia was converted to a mosque. Ornate and stately, the structure is built of stone and marble, topped by a golden dome measuring 102 feet in diameter, before the Muslim rulers added four minarets. The structure has survived several earthquakes, fires, riots, lootings (such as during the Fourth Crusade), and one massacre (when the elderly and infirm who had taken shelter there were slaughtered by the Ottoman conquerors). Today the Hagia Sophia serves as a museum, and yet remains one of the most striking buildings in civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_HANGING_GARDENS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Hanging Gardens may not have even existed, much less been a “wonder”; no Babylonian source mentions them, and there is no archaeological evidence for them (unlike for other ancient wonders of the world). The primary evidence for the Gardens comes from several Greek and Roman texts – how they were created, why they were created, their size and variety, even how they were watered. According to these, Nebuchadnezzar II constructed the Gardens c. 600 BC for his (obviously spoiled) homesick Median wife Amytis, who missed the green hills of her birth place. The “historical” sources also state that the Gardens were an ascending series of terraces (much like a ziggurat) built of mud bricks and containing all manner of plants. The base was supposedly 400 feet square, and the whole mass rose 75 feet into the very dry air; estimates are that the gardens would have required 8200 gallons of water a day to keep the plants alive in Babylon. If the Gardens did exist, it is assumed these were destroyed sometime during the first century AD.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_HERMITAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The core of what is today the famed Hermitage in St. Petersburg encompasses the monumental Winter Palace, residence of the Tsars since 1764 AD when Catherine the Great completed the palace on a scale to reflect the might and power of Imperial Russia. Catherine declared it her “treasure,” and proceeded to fill it with treasures – Renaissance paintings, jeweled and gilded crafts (the likes of Fabergé eggs, for instance), the crown jewels, and other trinkets. After adding several extensions to the palace and some reorganizing, in 1852 Nicholas I opened it to the public. And the Tsars kept adding to the collection. With the February Revolution of 1917, the building briefly housed the Provisional Government, until the Bolsheviks seized power in October and declared it a gift to the proletariat. Now spread across five buildings, the Hermitage is one of the largest museums in the world, with over three million art and historical items in its collection, including the largest gathering of paintings in the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_MAHABODHI_TEMPLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Mahabodhi Temple (or “Great Awakening” Temple) in Bodh Gaya is one of the four sacred sites of the Lord Buddha’s (Siddhartha Gautama) life, and the very spot where he attained Enlightenment. On the western side of the temple is the sacred Bodhi Tree, the very fig tree under which the Buddha was sitting when he did so. Be all that as it may, the first Mahabodhi Temple (there have been a couple) was built by the Emperor Asoka c. 250 BC. The current temple complex – notably the great tower, one of the first brick structures in India – dates from the 5th and 6th centuries AD. A high wall around the temple grounds was added at a later, undocumented, date; the wall encompasses the Bodhi Tree and six other sacred site of Buddha’s very enlightenment, since he spent seven weeks in seven different spots meditating on his very own revelations, as well as numerous Votive stupas. In the 1880s the British Raj undertook a restoration effort; in 1949 control of the very site passed to the state government of Bihar. Today, Buddhists from the world over make pilgrimage to Bodh Gaya as the holiest place of their very faith.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_MONT_ST_MICHEL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Perched on a rocky islet between Normandy and Brittany in the midst of sandbanks washed over by ocean tides, Mont St. Michel is a Gothic-style Benedictine abbey dedicated to the archangel Micheal built between the 11th and 16th centuries. Besides St. Aubert's skull, the Mont also was repository for bits of St. Petroc and St. Olaf and other holy relics. The place did have a practical purpose; its high walls, turrets and position made it of strategic worth … and many a French king stationed a small garrison (all that was needed) there. At low tide, it was readily accessible to pilgrims eager to give up a coin or two to be blessed; at high tide, the incoming sea would strand or drown any attacking force. The Mont would remain unconquered throughout the Hundred Years War and beyond. Its position also made it ideal to incarcerate unrepentant traitors and other sinners; Louis XI turned the Mont into a prison, a role it served through the rest of the Ancien Régime. Now, alas, it’s just a tourist attraction.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_ORACLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Of all the places in ancient Greece where priestesses uttered prognostications, by far the most famous (and cryptic) was the Oracle at Delphi, a shrine to Apollo located on the slopes of Mount Parnassus. There a priestess known as the “Pythia” would – for suitable compensation – interpret dreams, commune with the gods while in a trance, and read the signs in the entrails of sacrificed animals (chickens for the cheap, or goats for those willing to pay more). The Oracle began operation as early as 1400 BC, and enjoyed a thriving business until Christianity arrived with the Romans. The greatest structure was the stately temple to Apollo (of course), and it stayed standing until pulled down on orders from Theodosius I in 390 AD. The site remained an active “pagan” center throughout the 4th Century, however, and the Pythian Games (a predecessor to the Olympics today) continued to at least 424 AD.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_OXFORD_UNIVERSITY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The oldest university in the English-speaking world (and, thus, of Merry Ol’ England), instruction has been taking place at Oxford University since c. 1096 AD. It grew from a small institution when, in 1148, Henry II granted it a royal charter and then, in 1167, prohibited British students from attending the University of Paris. Although it was a Royalist center during the English Civil War, having survived that error the university has since taken little part in politics. In the mid-1800s the Oxford curriculum was greatly influenced by the reformed model of German higher education which came with the arrival of scholars such as Pusey, Jowett and Muller. The first women’s college (Lady Margaret Hall) at Oxford University was established in 1878. And in 1974, five previously all-male colleges there admitted women for the first time. Things haven’t been the same since.</Text>
		</Row>		
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_PETRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Situated between the Red Sea and the Dead Sea, Petra is a city cut from the red sandstone around Wadi Musa (now part of Jordan) by the Nabataeans – who obviously had a lot of free time – around 400 BC. Mentioned in Egyptian, Greek and Biblical sources, the city would develop into a major caravan center, a vital crossroads between Arabia, Egypt and Syria to the north. Surrounded by mountains riddled with gorges and canyon passages, it was defensible; but it was the ingenious and extensive system of cisterns and reservoirs in the middle of a desert that made it a trade center. At its peak, Petra was home to perhaps 20 thousand inhabitants, and served as the capital of the Nabataean kingdom. That is, until the Romans arrived and annexed it in 106 AD. Struck by a series of earthquakes, as well as Roman taxes, it was essentially abandoned two hundred years after – not to be “discovered” until 1812 by the Swiss explorer Johann Burckhardt.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_POTALA_PALACE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since there wasn’t much level ground in Tibet, with its base set on the southern slope of the Red Hill, the Potala Palace – home to the Dalai Lama (until the fourteenth one fled an uprising in 1959) – sort of grew along the hillside. The palace is named after Mount Potalaka, abode of the eleven-headed bodhisattva Avalokiteśvara. Today, its crimson and white walls and golden roof “shine in glory” … for paying tourists. Lozang Gyatso, the fifth Dalai Lama, began construction of the “modern” palace above Lhasa c. 1645 AD, and moved in four years later. Since then more bits and pieces have been added to the sprawling edifice, notably the Potrang Marpo (“red palace”) and the holy stupa completed in 1694. However, it should be noted that the Potala Palace has only one bathroom, located on the right side of the White Palace Square … although it is said to be the most beautiful restroom on Earth, filled with sunlight and good thoughts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_PYRAMIDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Though pyramids were built from the beginning of the Old Kingdom to the close of the Ptolemaic dynasty, the really big heaps of stone along the Nile were piled up commencing in the late third dynasty and continuing through the sixth (roughly 500 years). The Great Pyramid of Giza that is virtually synonymous with the “glory”  of ancient Egypt went up around 2560 BC to serve as the tomb of Pharaoh Khufu (who is unremarkable for anything else save the length of his reign). It is considered one of the Seven Wonders of the Ancient World. Built by tens of thousands of workers, including skilled masons, and covered with “casing stones” (slabs of polished limestone), the Pyramids of Giza were a testament to Egypt’s power and the natives’ conviction of the afterlife – at least for the elite. To date, some 135 pyramids have been found in what was once the greatest empire in the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_RUHR_VALLEY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since the 1700s, the Ruhrpott (Ruhr Valley) has been dug up – the coal and iron mines there some of the most productive in the world. Initially the ore was easily accessible by strip mining; after that was exhausted, the German miners dug deeper. By 1850, some 300 mines were in operation in and around the Ruhrpott. And, since it was troublesome to ship all this elsewhere, collieries, blast furnaces, rolling mills and the high chimneys of the Industrial Revolution shaped the skyline. Nor was coal and steel the only things pouring out of the Ruhr; by 1820 hundreds of water-powered mills were producing textiles, lumber and iron bars. Urban centers filled with wage slaves sprawled across the land … until today Bochum, Dortmund, Duisburg and Essen form one interconnected metropolis. With the recent decline of the coal and iron industries, the Ruhrpott has undergone a cultural transformation, and such edifices as the Zeche Zollverein coal mine complex and the Gasometer Oberhausen have been reborn as historical landmarks, even listed by UNESCO as World Heritage Sites!</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_STONEHENGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Whatever would motivate a bunch of Neolithic savages to build a circle out of fifty-ton slabs of rock – be it religious fervor, astrological curiosity, royal burial, or just for the fun of it – there’s no denying that Stonehenge is an impressive feat of engineering, given the tools they had to work with. Begun in Southern England some 5000 years ago, Stonehenge was concentric circles of stones surrounded by a moat (or “henge”). After the henge was in place, about a thousand years later an inner ring of “bluestones” were set in place, followed by an outer ring of larger, upright “sarsen” stones some 500 years after that. The 80 bluestones, coming in at about four tons each, were transported from a quarry over 240 miles away; the sarsen stones were cut and transported about 20 miles to the site. However done, for whatever purpose, Stonehenge remains a “wondrous” achievement even after a few millennia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_SYDNEY_OPERA_HOUSE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The construction of an enormous arts center for Sydney on Bennelong Point had been debated since the 1940s; in 1956 AD the government of New South Wales announced an open-ended competition for the design of something grand to show the world that the city really did have some taste. A Danish architect, Jørn Utzon won with his unique expressionist design, a series of precast concrete “shells,” covered with over a million white- or cream-colored tiles with interior glass curtain walls. So unique was the problematic design (Utzon had paid no heed to structural engineering) that it took sixteen years to build at a cost ten times more than estimated. But, once completed and officially dedicated by Queen Elizabeth II in October 1973, it has since become the iconic symbol of the one-time penal colony. From its 2,679-seat grand Concert Hall to the intimate 210-seat Utzon Room, the Opera House brings performances of all sorts down under.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_TERRACOTTA_ARMY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since his efforts at immortality didn’t bear fruit, when it came time for Qin Shi Huang, first emperor of Qin, to be interred, he made sure that it was done with style as befitted his greatness. Never lacking in hubris, the emperor had ordered work to begin on his mausoleum in 246 BC, when he was but 13 years old and just ascended to the throne. According to the Chinese geographer Li Daoyuan, writing six centuries after, Mount Li was selected for the site because of its auspicious geology, with its southern face rich in jade and its northern slopes in gold. In the Records of the Grand Historian (by one Sima Qian), it is claimed some 700 thousand laborers would be employed in digging and outfitting the tomb and filling it with 8000 soldiers, 130 chariots with horses, and 150 mounted cavalry – all made from clay-based ceramic – and armed with functioning weapons. Arranged in military formation. Hence, the “Terracotta Army.” Undisturbed until 1974, when discovered by peasants attempting to dig a well. So much for hubris.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_VENETIAN_ARSENAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Arsenal of Venice, begun about 1104 AD, was eventually a sprawling complex of shipyards, armories, and weapons shops. Built to serve the needs of the Venetian Navy upon which the Republic relied for both its independence and its lucrative sea trade routes, it was termed “the most important example of a large production complex with a centralized structure of the pre-industrial” civilization. Different areas of the Arsenal produced a prefabricated ship part, armaments, rope, sails and everything needed to put together a warship in a single day if necessity demanded. A state-owned forest in the Montello hills provided the timber and tar. The Porto Magna (“great gate”) to the Arsenal was added c. 1460, from a design by the artist Jacopo Bellini, the first Classical Revival structure built in Venice; two stone lions, captured in Greece, were added to the entrance in 1687 to awe visitors. The Arsenal also, when not launching warships to beat down Venice’s challengers in the Mediterranean, produced most of the Venetian merchant ships bringing wealth back to the city-state … to build more ships.</Text>
		</Row>
	</BaseGameText>
</GameData>