<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<BaseGameText>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_INTRO_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
      <Text>A unit that survives combat will gain "experience points" (XPs). Once the unit has acquired enough XPs, you may expend them to acquire "promotions" for that unit. There are a large variety of promotions in Civilization VI. Each gives a unit special advantages in battle.</Text>
    </Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_ADVANCED_ENGINES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Unfortunately, early carriers tended to be slow … too slow to keep up with the battleships and cruisers of the main fleet and fulfill their role of providing air support. Also, if left behind by the main fleet, aircraft carriers were terribly vulnerable; just about anything could sink these lumbering, thin-skinned vessels. Thus, the fleet carriers – made possible by interwar advances in engine design. Although the Washington Naval Treaty of 1922 limited the displacement of carriers to 23,000 tons of water, everyone ignored that. The concept of a fleet carrier was developed in 1931 by American admirals Clark and Yarnell … fast enough to keep up with the fleet and be protected by it. The Essex class of American fleet carriers – driven by Westinghouse geared turbines hooked to eight boilers – became the 20th Century’s most numerous class of capital ship.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_ADVANCED_RANGEFINDING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As artillery became more powerful, and able to hit targets further and further away, better and faster ways of calculating the trajectory and point of impact became necessary. The time of open sights and sticking a finger in the air were over. Thus, stadiametric rangefinders … an advance over the Roman dodecahedron rangefinder as described by Julius Caesar in 'De Bello Gallico.' In effect, the stadiametric approach used a modified telescope to calculate distances quickly, based on the principle that in similar triangles, similar sides are proportional, which comes in handy when trying to hit a distant spot – be that a wall, or a moving ship. In fact, by the mid-1800s stadiametric rangefinders were found in every coastal fortification.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SHRAPNEL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When artillery moved from solid shot to explosive shells, grapeshot was replaced with shrapnel shells, designed to explode above the ground in an airburst and shower those below with lethal little balls; it was invented by Henry Shrapnel around 1780 AD for the British Army. By the Napoleonic Wars it was quite popular among British commanders, although difficult to manufacture and use (the shells had an unfortunate tendency to bury themselves in the ground rather than explode in the air). But by World War I, the kinks had been worked out and both sides used them to great effect.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_CHOKE_POINTS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In military terms, a “choke point” is the tactical use of places where the terrain limits the paths by which the enemy can reach a unit’s position – narrow tracks in the woods, narrow valleys in the hills, bridges or fords at rivers, dry spots in marshland, and so forth. Recognizing the choke points is a skill possessed by great and capable officers. By narrowing the enemy’s approach, an army can dictate the course of battle; military history abounds with examples: Leonidas’s defense of the pass at Thermopylae, Godwinson at the battle of Stamford Bridge, Wallace at Stirling Bridge, and, of course, Agincourt where the French were forced to attack through a narrow gap in the woods.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_AMPHIBIOUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Considered the most complex of operations (now), landing from water into battle didn’t seem to faze the ancient Greeks, Persians, or Vikings. And Alexander the Great’s crossing of the monsoon-swollen Hydaspes to crush King Porus is considered one of the greatest victories ever. Of course, none of them faced coastal artillery, airplanes, and machine guns. But units specifically trained to land from boats and immediately engage the enemy are a relatively modern development. Until Gallipoli, the largest amphibious operation had been the Persian landing at Marathon just prior to the battle. But World War II is marked by far larger conflicts, in Africa and Europe, and across the Pacific.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_AUXILIARY_SHIPS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>While one may have some limited combat (usually defensive) capability, in general auxiliary ships are those that keep the real combat ships functioning at peak efficiency. Without the auxiliaries, no blue-water navy can be efficient, successful, or often afloat. As European navies began to range the oceans during the 1700s and 1800s, those big men-of-war needed support vessels to replenish supplies, make repairs away from ports, and guard those naval bases scattered about the globe. When the age of steam dawned, colliers and later oilers kept the boilers in the destroyers and battleships firing. As navies became ever more diverse, so too did the auxiliary ships; the modern U.S. Navy lists some 86 different types (not counting floating repair docks).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_BATTLECRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The first recorded account of a battle cry is found in the epic Iliad of Homer, but warriors have been screaming into battle since long before. Meant to intimidate the enemy, or perhaps bolster their own courage, many soldiers of civilizations have developed distinctive cries and yells. Among the most famous echoing through history: the 'Alala' of Athens, the several Kipchak shouts, Muslim 'Allahu Akbar,' the Mongol cry to urge their horses to battle, the fearsome Rebel Yell of the South, 'Vive l’Empereur,' and “Remember the Alamo.” War is a noisy business, it seems.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_ARROW_STORM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>It is reported – probably an apocryphal tale – that the Persian envoy trying to convince those stiff-necked Spartans to surrender at Thermopylae said “our arrows will black out the sun,” to which Dienekes replied, “Good, then we will fight in the shade.” Most troops were not quite so complacent about facing an arrow storm, the rapid massed fire of archers onto a particular spot. Whereas most well-trained archers could fire about six arrows a minute, thus creating a pretty dense storm, the English archers armed with longbows were especially proficient at laying down such a rain of death … better even than crossbowmen.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_BOARDING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since – unlike naval ships – sinking an opponent ship brought no profit, pirates and privateers relied on heavily armed and vicious oaring parties to storm the upper decks and so secure the (hopefully) precious cargo. In olden days before the wonder of gunpowder, boarding actions were the primary form of naval combat (far fewer were sunk by ramming) and battles were won on the decks. Boarding parties were armed with a variety of weapons, ever more lethal as time passed: cutlasses and swords, blunderbusses and flintlock pistols, belaying pins and just about anything sharp or blunt. But with the development in the early 16th Century of cannon gunports and deckguns, the use of boarding tactics gradually came to an end.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_BOMBARDMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Shore bombardment came when Edward III of England mounted bombards on some of his ships besieging Calais in 1347 AD. It has become a popular way of assaulting towns and troops ever since. Turning the fleet’s big guns on civilian targets – factories, docks, warehouses, homes, etc. – was generally frowned upon … until World War I. On 16 December 1914, the Imperial German Navy shelled the British towns of Scarborough, Hartlepool, and Whitby, causing 137 fatalities and widespread public outrage (some of that directed at the Royal Navy for allowing the raid to happen). The British themselves bombarded targets in the Dardanelles, Salonika and Belgian coasts. In the next war, blasting civilians was pretty much left to the air forces, the naval guns being reserved for invasions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_ROLLING_BARRAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A rolling barrage is a method to deliver massed firepower across a broad area, as effective by naval ships as for land-based batteries. The fact that the guns are firing from rolling, moving, unsteady platforms just makes it more challenging for the naval gunners. In effect, the guns are aimed at sequential points, typically 20 to 30 yards apart for modern shells, along a path from a few hundred to several thousand yards in length. With multiple ships firing, this can form a box, a rectangle where everything in the path is flattened. Rolling barrages during World War II proved very effective at blasting the enemy out of built-up areas and fortifications. So it was added to the naval repertoire of destruction.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_BREAKTHROUGH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When a commander commits his heavy cavalry – be they horses or tanks – the hope is to break through the enemy’s defensive line, and then rapidly exploit the gap. Much of the battlefield maneuvering is done to mount a breakthrough attempt – focusing a large force on a small portion of the line – or to insure that reserves are available to plug the gap. For both these, the heavy, mobile units proved best. Once the enemy line is broken, the armor can penetrate deep into the rear or attack the exposed flanks of the units on either side of the breach. In either case, the battle’s probably over.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_CAMOUFLAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Whereas the sneaky barbarians had always used camouflage (of a sort, although the dirt and filth hid a lot), honorable soldiers didn’t hide from the enemy. But the advent of the long-range musket and the Baker rifle made concealing oneself a survival necessity. During the French &amp; Indian War the rifle-armed Rogers’ Rangers wore gray and green uniforms, which blended in with the woodlands. During the Napoleonic Wars, the Portuguese Caçadores favored brown-jackets which helped conceal them. By the time of the First World War, all the major nations – save the French – had given up their red, white, and bright blue uniforms which made such lovely targets.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_CHARGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>There is nothing – at least before tanks spoiled everything – more thrilling and effective than a charge by heavy cavalry; unfortunately, they didn’t occur very often. Battles were rarely fought on level, dry, and open ground suitable for such picturesque battle. By the end of the 14th Century, in fact, most knights dismounted to fight, and their prized destriers were led to the rear … except for the French, but look what happened at Crécy, Poitiers, and Agincourt. But if the cavalry charge did reach the enemy, the shock of contact could overwhelm defensive positions, even those sheltered by field works. But the advent of machine guns, barbed wire, and mines put an end to all that glorious charging.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_RUTTER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Before the advent of detailed nautical charts (but after sailors trusted only luck to reach shore safely) a rutter was a mariner’s handbook of sailing directions for navigation – termed a periplus (“sailing around” book) by ancient Mediterranean sailors. These were jealously guarded by navigators and pilots throughout the Middle Ages, for they were the personal record of all one knew about the trade routes they had explored or sailed. During the Renaissance, rutters shared among city merchant-traders made the likes of Pisa, Genoa, and Venice incredibly wealthy. The Age of Discovery brought rutters to even more prominence, as they were the nautical record of how to reach those distant places again. Eventually, all this private knowledge got replaced by nautical charts, and sailing became far less adventurous.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_CLOSE_AIR_SUPPORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In military terms, close air support (CAS) is aerial attacks on enemy ground forces that are in close proximity to friendly forces, demanding coordination with these friendly forces so as not to accidentally bomb and strafe them. There had been some CAS operations during World War I, and the British debuted the first ground attack airplane – modified F.E.2b fighters – in late 1917. After the war, the victorious powers weren’t particularly interested in further research and designs for CAS … but the defeated Germans were. Forbidden strategic bombers by the Treaty of Versailles, the Luftwaffe turned to CAS dive bombers, with the famous Junkers Ju-87 (the Stuka) the first result. Incredibly successful in the Spanish Civil War for the Condor Legion, it proved able to hit enemy positions with near pinpoint accuracy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_COCKPIT_ARMOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Not long after pilot Louis Quénault and observer Joseph Frantz shot down an enemy plane with a machine gun in aerial combat in October 1914, aircraft engineers started considering how to add armor to protect the most vulnerable part of a fighter plane … the pilot. Unfortunately, weight was a concern for those wooden and canvas planes; any extra affected a fighter’s performance. Nevertheless, the Deutsche Luftstreitkräfte and Royal Air Force saw some value in keeping their pilots alive, so a few planes were retrofitted with lightly armored pilot’s seats. By World War II, most fighters had cockpit armor, and shatter-proof canopies, to help deflect all that fire from above and especially below.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_COINCIDENCE_RANGEFINDING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the 1880s, the British Admiralty – recognizing the improvement of naval guns and ammunition – issued a requirement for a new rangefinder accurate to 3% at 3000 yards. In 1888, professors Archibald Barr and William Stroud built the first coincidence rangefinder that did just that; by 1898 their firm had sold over 150 around the world, most fitted to battleships. The device consisted of a long tube with a forward-facing lens at each end, two prism wedges inside, and an eyepiece in the center; The operator can rotate the prisms until the two images align; the degree of rotation of each will then give the range to a distant target by simple triangulation. Coincidence rangefinders became the naval standard … until replaced by modern laser rangefinders.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_COMMANDO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Commandos, those soldiers trained in the more esoteric aspects of war – infiltration, climbing, and rappelling, close combat, amphibious operations, and such – are today’s elite troops, from the American Green Berets to the Israeli Shaldag Unit. Although several nations had units trained in unconventional attacks on “high-value targets,” the term “commando” was first used in relation to the Boer bands of militia which raised havoc with the British at the beginning of the 1900s.  So impressed were the British, that in 1941 their Imperial General Staff adopted the name for their volunteer units raised to raid the German-occupied continent. Other militaries soon followed suit with these “special forces.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_CONVOY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Naval convoys have been around since at least since the 12th Century, when classes of warships became distinct and different sorts had different, coordinated roles to play in an engagement. During the age of colonization, Spain and Portugal sent military escorts with their lumbering treasure ships to ward off pirates and privateers. Convoy tactics figured prominently during the Napoleonic War, as Britain sought to interdict French grain fleets; several battles – Ushant, Dogger Bank and the Glorious First of June – swirled around convoys. During World War I, a convoy system was instituted by the British Admiralty to counter the threat of German submarines, a policy carried over to the far deadlier Battle of the Atlantic in the next great war.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_CREEPING_ATTACK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>During the early stage of the anti-submarine war, during the final run of a convoy escort to drop stern-mounted depth charges on a skulking U-boat contact was lost by the active sound detection system (ASDIC) … giving the German sub the chance to change depth or direction at the last minute. To counter this, the Royal Navy’s 36 Escort Group devised the “Creeping Attack.” Using two ships, one stationary to maintain contact and one to close on the target, the latter releasing its depth charges on a signal from the first. Although the tactic required patience, and took extra time and ships, it proved effective. The arrival of more sophisticated ASDIC, along with forward-throwing Hedgehog and Squid depth charges, made the tactic obsolete – although the British continued to use it to war’s end.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_DEBATER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Through most of the Middle Ages and Renaissance, religious “disputations” (formal debates) offered the avowed method of establishing truth in theology. Based on the hoary old traditions of Platonic philosophy, these debates were judged based on the debaters’ citation of “accepted” written works and the usual rhetorical skills of spokesmen. Disputations between Catholic and Jewish theologians (such as that in Paris in 1240) were quite polite; those between Protestants and Catholics (for instance, Regensburg in 1541) somewhat less so. Meanwhile, to the East the Mughal emperor Akbar the Great was hosting disputations between Muslim, Hindu, Jain, Zoroastrian, and Catholic Jesuit holy men as a show of his religious tolerance.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_DECK_CREWS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In 1922, with the launch of the USS Langley, it became obvious that dedicated aircraft carriers would need dedicated flight deck (and later, hangar deck) crews for efficient launch and recovery operations, and maintenance of all the temperamental aeroplanes. By the time World War II got started, well-trained deck crews could land, service, and launch a squadron of planes as though their lives depended on it … as they did. The crews became highly organized, with a hierarchy of tasks under the supervision of the likes of the air officer, catapult officer, aircraft directors, signal officers, and dozens of others. Refueling, rearming, and repairs were handled on the flight deck in combat, sometimes even as the carrier was trying to avoid being sunk.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SPIKING_THE_GUNS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Light cavalry in the 1700s and 1800s – especially the flamboyant types like hussars and lancers – were generally used for scouting, skirmishing, and raiding. In general, their use on the battlefield was limited until after the fighting, when they were unleashed to run down the fleeing enemy. But upon occasion the light cavalry was used to charge enemy artillery, usually suffering daunting casualties before nearing the guns. Whereupon the gunners would run to the nearest friendly infantry, and the horsemen would dismount to spike the guns, driving a barbed steel spike into the touch-hole and rendering the guns useless. A popular tactic for many decades; indeed, Count Friedrich von Bismarck recommended that every cavalryman should carry spikes. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_DOGFIGHTING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>At first, military aviation was fairly placid, most reconnaissance, artillery spotting, and the occasional bombing of footsloggers; even in the opening months of World War I, this was the case. Then, a few pilots started taking shots at enemy pilots with pistols. Before anyone knew it, planes were equipped with machine guns (after Fokker solved that problem of shooting through a spinning propeller), and dogfighting began. Adventurous pilots invented maneuvers – such as the Immelmann and Low Yo-Yo – to give themselves an advantage in battle. Victory in a dogfight – unlike knightly jousts, it’s more of a composite of fear and flames – quickly became a matter of technology and technique.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_ECHELON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The use of echelon – in effect, units in the infantry line are arranged diagonally, so as to refuse the flank (for instance, in a right echelon, each is placed to the right and slightly behind the adjacent unit on its left) – dates back to antiquity. The earliest recorded use is when the Thebans attacked the Spartans at the battle of Leuctra with their left wing while they use an echelon formation to refuse their weak right flank; they won … one of the few defeats the Spartans ever suffered. The use of echelon did not pass away with the arrival of gunpowder; the famed Jomini wrote extensively about it in his works on linear tactics, influential on European and American officers for decades after.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_ELITE_GUARD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Many a king, emperor, and general had an elite guard, hand-picked and highly trained soldiers that accompanied him (or her) when he (or she) went on campaign. Although the primary duty of these “imperial” guards was the continued breathing of their commander, they were also the best shock troops available in a battle: better armed, better disciplined, and willing to fight to the death (supposedly). History recounts the stirring exploits of many of these – Persian Immortals, Ottoman Janissaries, the Tang Dynasty’s Forbidden Troops, Napoleon’s Old Guard, and Britain’s Household Division. So these units were much more than just pretty uniforms.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_EMBOLON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The embolon (Greek for “wedge”) was one of the earliest formations used by ancient warriors, first on land and then on sea. In open sea, the Greek triremes usually sailed in single line, led by the commander’s ship. However, upon sight of the enemy warships, the Greek fleet would deploy into a triangular or trapezoid formation, with the courageous commander’s ship at the tip. This formation meant the enemy had a limited front to fire missiles at, and gave the superior Greek seamen the chance to use their rams to best effect while shielding the sides of the ship ahead – any enemy turning to ram would be instead rammed by the next ship in the wedge. So effective was the embolon that it remained in use, until cannon made it a liability.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_EMPLACEMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If a siege progressed past a few days, the attackers would build earthworks to protect themselves from those angry fellows on the walls defending the town. This was especially useful for keeping the crews manning the siege artillery – be these catapult or cannon – alive, for they tended to draw attention as they sought to batter down the walls. The introduction of gunpowder made this even more essential, as cannon mounted on walls could lob shells quite a distance. Temporary redoubts and emplacements meant the guns could keep firing on the walls until these were breached; in 1453 AD, for example, Mehmed II’s 62 cannon – protected by earthen ramparts – hammered away at the walls of Constantinople for six weeks.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_ESCORT_MOBILITY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Light cavalry proved excellent serving as escort to vulnerable bits of the army: commanders and headquarters, supply and medical units, artillery, communications and engineering troops, and such. Upon occasion, they were also assigned to provide security to civilians, notably to settlers and work parties; indeed, during the settling of the American west, South Africa, and Australia, light cavalry accompanied wagon trains, railroad work crews, freight caravans, and even stagecoaches (if somebody or something important was aboard) across territories full of hostile natives. The military escort, generally unhappy with such babysitting duty, tended to hurry these folk along at a brisk pace. Thus, making everyone happier when their destination was reached.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_EVASIVE_MANEUVERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Bombers – especially four-engine ones – aren’t very maneuverable, and tended to trust to the formation’s massed firepower when attacked by enemy interceptors. So, usually straight and steady was the best defense, and it gave the plane’s gunners at least some chance of hitting their targets. But, upon (desperate) occasion they would engage in aerial hijinks. Lone bombers would try air-braking or the corkscrew (a series of steep diving and climbing turns) when attacked. Against ground fire, these might work, but most bomber pilots preferred to jink to throw off the aim of the AA gunners below. In general, however, none of these worked very well; bombers were still big, lumbering targets.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_EXPERT_CREW_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As the battlefield became more fluid in the 1700s in Europe, various nations created horse artillery – light, fast-moving, and fast-firing artillery that could provide mobile support, sort of a hybrid of cavalry and cannons. Introduced by the Swedes during the Thirty Years War, horse artillery became a staple for all the “modern” armies, and the guns themselves became larger and yet lighter. Thus, battlefield cannon evolved … unfortunately, that meant that the crews needed to be better trained. But it wasn’t until 1915, when Britain established the School of Instruction for Royal Horse and Field Artillery (the world’s first) at Larkhill that such training was available, making its graduates “experts” in fire-and-move artillery tactics.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_EXPERT_MARKSMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>With catapults, onagers, ballistae, and the like, eyeballing a target worked well enough, given their range and the size of their targets. But as artillery passed into the gunpowder era, with longer ranges and often smaller targets, that wasn’t as effective. Thus, a number of devices were invented to help with the ballistic calculations for cannon. The first recorded device to measure elevation angles was the gunner’s quadrant, c. 1545 AD. In 1742 the ballistic pendulum invented by Benjamin Robins revolutionized artillery fire. And in 1892, the firm of Barr &amp; Stroud were awarded a contract by the British Army for six rangefinders, the very first ones. All these turned gun laying into a science, rather than an art.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_GUERRILLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Typically, guerrilla operations entail some sort of “fight and flee” tactic, whereby a small, lightly-armed, fast-moving unit attacks a bigger one, and then gallantly runs away. Using every advantage of cover, camouflage, stealth, and ambush, guerrilla units seek to wear down the enemy’s advantages in numbers and munitions, while simultaneously negatively impacting its will to pursue. But, the main point is to avoid a “stand-up” fight; otherwise the guerrilla force is annihilated.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_INCENDIARIES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Throwing lit torches on spears worked pretty well, but firing incendiary arrows worked even better. Built-up areas throughout history have tended to burn nicely, making defenders decidedly uncomfortable, and so ancient generals quickly found that attacks on cities and districts were more successful when a rain of fiery missiles could be laid down. Flaming projectiles fired from bows, catapults, and cannons have been used ever since the first recorded instances of the Assyrians and the Judeans did so. When gunpowder made its appearance, so did the carcass, a hollow iron projectile filled with a highly flammable mixture to lob over the walls, first used by the French in 1672 AD.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_FLIGHT_DECK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The first flight decks were inclined wooden ramps built on the forecastle of a few warships … just in case this “aeroplane thing” proved useful. The first plane to launch from a warship (USS Birmingham) occurred in November 1910; two months later, the first plane to land on a warship platform (USS Pennsylvania) was piloted by Eugene Fly. The first aircraft carrier that actually had a “modern” flight deck was the converted liner HMS Argus, whose upper works had been cut away and a large wooden platform laid over the hull. It was used to experiment with possibilities, including the construction of a starboard “island” to serve as bridge and chartrooms and briefing room and control tower. The flight deck also proved the primary – actually only – place to park the aeroplanes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_HANGAR_DECK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>It proved unhandy to keep a carrier’s planes all tied down on the flight deck; the aircraft were subject to weather, rough seas, and enemy attentions. By the time of World War II, Japanese and American fleet carriers often carried two or more fighter squadrons, a couple of torpedo-bomber squadrons, at least one dive bomber squadron, and several scout planes. There was not nearly enough room up top for these 80 to 100 planes on a typical carrier. Thus, between the wars naval designers incorporated a “hangar deck” – a carrier’s garage – on the latest. Located two decks below the flight deck, the hangar deck on the USS Eisenhower for instance is 110 feet wide, 25 feet high and 685 feet long … plenty of room for 60 planes, as well as fuel tanks and heavy repair equipment.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_FOLDING_WINGS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Even with hangar decks, things got crowded, especially when dive bombers were added to the aviation complement of the carriers in the 1930s. Since adding another hangar deck was impractical, naval “thinkers” turned to more radical solutions for packing more planes onto fleet carriers … and so folding wings were incorporated into new carrier plane designs. Despite the misgivings of some pilots (who weren’t real keen on the possibility of their wings folding up while aloft), aircraft such as the British Supermarine Spitfire and Fairy Gannet were soon aboard British carriers; by the late 1930s virtually all American carrier planes had been converted to folding wings. The Japanese ones too. Folding wings did mean more hydraulic and electrical maintenance chores, but the added planes seemed worth the trouble.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_FORWARD_OBSERVERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A forward observer, or “spotter,” is the one (or ones) set up far in advance of the battery so artillery or mortar fire can be called down on the enemy like the wrath of God … accurately. Because these are indirect fire weapons, so long as a battery commander knew where the target was, impediments to line of sight such as hills, trees, buildings, and such were no problem. Although there had been some use of forward observers since the Crimean War, World War I made them indispensable. Using binoculars and rangefinders, and the terrain for concealment, communicating with the battery commander via field phone or radio, a spotter could change the course of a modern battle with one well-placed and unexpected barrage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_GARRISON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>From the French verb 'garner' (“to equip”), a garrison is put in place in a town to protect it, intimidate the residents, rest or train the troops, or simply as policy. The Romans, beset by barbarians on all sides, would often settle retiring veterans in frontier towns, a ready-made garrison of experienced soldiers should necessity demand. For garrisons, fighting from behind walls and well-motivated (since there was no place to retreat to), proved the best defense against attackers. Often the garrison troops had their families with them … also a motivation to defend the place to the death. The ability of garrisons to stave off assaults is the primary reason there are so many sieges in history.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_GRAPE_SHOT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>First used during the Hussite Wars in cannon and “hand-cannon” (clumsy pistols), grapeshot proved very effective against enemy infantry. In effect, grapeshot is a mass of small metal (or even stone) bits packed tightly in the barrel; when fired, the metal bits spread out like buckshot, although with far deadlier results. It was something new in warfare, for ancient artillery simply weren’t capable of such a shotgun approach. At sea, grapeshot was used to clear the decks of enemy ships, although less effective than firing on a dense formation of soft targets in the open. In time, rather than just being shoveled in, the small bits were packed into special shells – canister shot – that broke open when fired.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_GROUND_CREWS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Aeroplanes are complex and fragile machines, especially when they are getting shot at. From the beginning, as early as the American Civil War, military balloons had a dedicated ground crew, those who could fix the craft and keep it flying (well, floating). In World War I, every airbase had its contingent of ground crewmen working to repair, maintain, arm, and service the airplanes. Of course, the fact that they and their facilities were indispensable to the operation made them prime targets for the enemy, so strafing and bombing airfields was conducted on a regular basis. As warplanes became ever more sophisticated, so too did the ground crews … to the point that specialized training now takes months.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_HEATHEN_CONVERSION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>For quite some time, it was tough on organized religion, what with all those other faiths vying for the “hearts and minds” of the people. Buddhists in Japan, Christians in Rome, Hindus in Indonesia … all struggled to bring holy writ to the heathens they faced. Although the Christian conversion of the Roman Empire proceeded by fits and starts, it wasn’t long before the Church had missionaries all over Europe. And then Africa, Asia and the Americas, converting heathens everywhere – by the sword if necessary.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SHELLS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mortars have been pounding defensive walls for centuries during sieges; the high, arcing trajectory of their bombs and shells are also handy for lobbing explosives over things, thus rendering walls, trenches, bastions, and the like somewhat useless. Most historians consider the Turks’ siege of Constantinople the first use of mortars, which they used to even better effect in the siege of Belgrade in 1456 AD. European mortars were virtually too heavy to move, until Menno van Coehoorn devised lighter ones, using explosive shells to blast walls apart at the siege of Grave. Mortars fell out of favor during the wars of maneuver in the 1800s, but underwent a resurgence in popularity when World War I saw hundreds of miles of trenches dug.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_HELMSMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Steering a ship isn’t as easy as it appears; it’s far more than just turning the tiller. Once sails went up, the value of a skilled helmsman escalated considerably, demanding both skill and strength. In Greek triremes, for instance, steering was achieved through two steering oars on either side of the stern controlled by a single kybernetes (“helmsman”), who usually had the Trierarch (“captain”) next to him shouting advice. A good helmsman had a keen sense of how his ship would react to different conditions (wind, swells, currents, and storms) and was able to anticipate the delay between changing the helm and when the ship would respond to the rudder. The same is as true today as then.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SENTRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The importance of holding the high ground has been recognized since Sun Tzu advised that any general hoping for victory should seize it – or at least make sure the enemy didn’t. It was hard to charge uphill, or throw rocks, javelins, and the like uphill. Conversely, it was easier to charge or throw things downhill. Holding the high ground also provides longer lines of sight than mucking about in valleys. General Ji Ling of the Eastern Han dynasty sent lookouts to positions of high ground to provide early warning of encroaching barbarians. He wasn’t the first, or last, to post sentries on hilltops.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_HOLD_THE_LINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>On 25 October, 1854 AD, the British 93rd Highland (Sutherland) Regiment was in position, along with a small force of Royal Marines and some Turkish infantrymen, near the British headquarters during the battle of Balaklava. Deployed in line two deep, when the massed Russian cavalry charged, the Highlanders didn’t form square but instead stood their ground. Firing rapidly into the oncoming charge. The Russians broke, the first time that infantry in line had routed an oncoming cavalry charge. Their stand hearted the units to either side, and saved the day. The event was immortalized by William H. Russell, a London 'Times' correspondent, and his description of the “thin red streak tipped with a line of steel” would become “the thin red line” … used ever since to represent courageous composure in the face of onrushing danger.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_CAPARISON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mankind has used animals in conflict for thousands of years, and soon enough sought to protect these valuable additions to war. What is probably the first man-made “armor” for animals appeared c. 2600 BC in Ur, where the onagers that pulled Sumerian battle carts seem to have worn padded leather chest protectors; the earliest evidence for European horse armor dates to the 8th Century BC when cloth and leather caparisons were worn by Greek warhorses, a practice likely introduced from the East. Although padded caparison would evolve to be more decorative than defensive during the Middle Ages, it remains in use for ceremonial occasions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_INDULGENCE_VENDOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>An indulgence, according to the Catholic Church, was a way to reduce punishment for ones sins … for a price. Originally, the penance might be a pilgrimage, or doing charitable works. But by the early Renaissance, indulgences were sold for money. Quaestores – professional “pardoners” – practiced the unrestricted sale of indulgences, and one of Gutenberg’s earliest commissions as a printer was wholesale production of indulgences for the German cardinal Nicolaus Cusanus. So bad were the abuses that the practice became a centerpiece for the Protestant Reformation that tore the Church apart.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_INTERCEPTOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Towards the end of World War I, as long-range bombing raids became more fearsome and frequent, several designers began building fighter planes specifically to prevent these; they termed them “interceptor aircraft.” Between the wars, as it became obvious that everyone was going to bomb targets in each other’s homelands (following the Italian Giulio Douhet’s theories), there was a push to design interceptors; these designs took two forms: relatively lightweight and speedy fighters to hit the bombers aloof, and heavier and long-range fighters to operate in adverse weather and at night. During the Cold War, both the United States and Soviet Russia maintained entire wings of interceptors (not that they’d have done much good when the nukes were unleashed).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_LINE_OF_BATTLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Those thrilling images of towering ships-of-the-line in line of battle discharging broadsides at each other as they sail majestically along being battered to pieces are actually fairly accurate … unlike some other film representations of history. The tactic in which a fleet of warships form a line stern to bow was devised at some point before 1555 AD, when the Portuguese writer Fernão de Oliveira recommended it as the ideal combat formation. Compared to other formations, each ship could fire its broadsides without fear of hitting a friendly ship, all of which were running either parallel or in opposite direction of the enemy ships. During World War I, line of battle was still being used by the battleships and cruisers of the Great Powers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_LONG_RANGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>By the end of 1943, it had become obvious that the United States needed a very long-range, high-flying strategic bomber to carry the war to the Japanese home islands and the heart of Japanese industry. The Americans developed the Boeing B-29 Superfortress with an operational range of 3250 miles (5230 km) and the British their Avro Lancaster with range of 2530 miles (4073 km). The long-range raids on Japan culminated in the bombs dropped by B-29s on Hiroshima and Nagasaki in August 1945. In the ensuing Cold War, both Soviet Russia and the United States developed ever longer ranged bombers, so as to drop nuclear bombs on the other’s heartland.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_DROP_TANKS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Drop tanks were first used during the Spanish Civil War to allow fighter escorts to accompany bombers on long-range missions. When World War II opened, the Luftwaffe used 80-gallon drop tanks to extend the range of the long-range version of the infamous Stukas for ground attack. Throughout the war, every air force made use of these external fuel tanks for every sort of fighter mission, from air patrols to recon flights. Because these tanks made the fighter less aerodynamic, when engaging the enemy, the tanks were usually jettisoned (i.e., dropped on some hapless place below). The postwar introduction of jet fighters only made the problem of range more immediate, as such were notorious for fuel consumption.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_LOOT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since the fabled Sea Peoples sailed the Aegean around the 14th Century BC, raiders have plundered coastal towns. In classical antiquity the Illyrians and Tyrrhenians were known as pirates, and as early as 258 AD Herulic raiders ravaged towns on the coasts of the Black Sea and the Sea of Marmara. Since a pirate fleet couldn’t just sail up to the docks and loot the port (that’s what forts with cannons were for), shore parties were necessary to help take the town and then plunder it. It was during the “Golden Age of Piracy” that shore parties of raiders led by the likes of l’Ollonnais (Maracaibo), Morgan (Panama City), and Drake (Santo Domingo and Cartagena) enjoyed great success … and profit.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_MARTYR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Every religion seems to have its (long) list of martyrs, those willing to suffer torture and death for their beliefs. Most of them – though not all – had profound effects on their faith, often engendering all sorts to follow their lead in dying for god or gods. Most of them – though not all – are considered “holy” only by those of their faith. After their death, all sorts of their belongings – sandals, nails, bones, cups, and other odd bits – are also considered holy. And all these relics get housed in temples, churches, and monasteries where the faithful can make pilgrimage to see them.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_CHAPLAIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Every faith has its healers. In antiquity, priests were often also physicians, keeping the faithful healthy in body as well as spirit. A number of early Christian healers are revered as saints by the Catholic Church, and in the Middle Ages several religious orders were founded which maintained hospitals, leper colonies, infirmaries, hospices, and rudimentary medical care for the poor … some still do. The Catholics weren’t alone. Buddha declared, “Bodhisattvas should learn the art of healing in order to help others and to liberate them from suffering”; and Islamic scholars kept the knowledge of the ancient physicians alive through the dark ages of Europe. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_ALPINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>While some early tribes were adept at trudging across the hills and mountains of Europe and Asia (in fact, many primitives had strong superstitions concerning the “high places” and tended to avoid these), in general it wasn’t until the Renaissance that military units were formed in Switzerland, Austria, Italy, Germany, and even India with the skills to operate in hilly terrain. Since warfare began, holding the high ground has been important for victory; these alpine formations – usually small – not only scouted the lay of the land but looked to insure it was held by their side.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_OBSERVATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Germany sent out two waves of surface merchant raiders during World War II, mostly converted refrigerator ships which tended to be faster and have more reinforcement than ordinary merchant ships. Armed with naval guns and a few torpedoes and mines, it was planned they would raise havoc in the Pacific among Allied shipping there … but their greatest advantage may have been that some were equipped with naval radar, able to spot prey over the horizon. In fact, radar served the Kormoran when it surprised and sank the Australian cruiser Sydney in one of the more infamous episodes. Submarines, both Axis and Allied, had to rely on sonar for the purpose of locating distant ships since radar didn’t work so well underwater.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_ORATOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Whether quietly teaching the “Word” or loudly pounding the pulpit, the primary method of bringing newcomers into a faith is public speaking, with all the techniques of oratory to draw upon. Indeed, in the Roman Catholic Church, an “oratory” is a place set aside for ecclesiastical public prayer. In the beginning, religious oratory carried only as far as a prophet’s voice, but the mass media age gave it evangelical wings on radio (Billy Sunday, for example) and television (Billy Graham).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_DOUBLE_ENVELOPMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A double envelopment is one of the most devastating maneuvers in warfare, a simultaneous attack on both flanks of an enemy formation, usually carried out by highly mobile elements like light cavalry. Sun Tzu contemplated the art of the “pincer” maneuver, but advised against it since an enemy would likely run before it could be completed; if actually trapped by horsemen, he felt the enemy soldiers would fight all the more ferociously since they were doomed anyway. Nevertheless, the double envelopment was used successfully by the likes of Miltiades at Marathon, Alexander at Hydaspes, and Hannibal at Cannae. And Genghis Khan used a rudimentary sort known as the Mongol “horns.” Eventually the Germans perfected it for armored warfare – the blitzkrieg.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_PILGRIM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As Nelson DeMille put it, “We’re all pilgrims … but some pilgrims have better road maps.” A pilgrim is a traveler with a purpose, to reach a holy place – thus a physical and spiritual journey to some special place in some specific belief system. This might be a holy city (Rome, Mecca, and the like), a natural wonder imbued with significance (Mount Sinai, Naj Tunich, the Ganges River, etc.), or something much smaller but just as significant. Inevitably, some of the pilgrims to such places come back having “seen the light,” and insist on sharing their enlightenment.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_PREPARATORY_FIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Naval gunfire support (a type of shore bombardment known as NGFS) is the use of naval guns – from primitive mortars to modern rockets – to provide artillery support for ground troops operating near the shore. Modern NGFS is often part of the preparatory fire (“softening up”) for amphibious assaults. During the 17th Century, bomb vessels had two or more mortars mounted to fire explosive shells onto enemy troops on or near the shore. During the American Civil War and the Crimean War, armored monitors made an appearance, along with “floating batteries.” But by World War I, the big guns of battleships, cruisers, and destroyers served better for NGFS. A practice used extensively during the many amphibious operations of the next two major wars.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_PROSELYTIZER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Proselytizing seeks to convert others to one's faith, or at least convince them it has some redeeming points. In the process, proselytizers also seek to eradicate or limit the influence of other religions. Most faiths have those who seek to attract new believers; in the Baha’i faith it is strongly emphasized, and every faithful Mormon goes on a mission proselytizing door-to-door. For many, however, such activity is considered disrespectful, insulting, or annoying. In some countries, in fact, such proselytizing is illegal, and in most it is not condoned in schools, government buildings, and workplaces.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_RANGER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Despite Tolkien’s fancies, real rangers do not talk to the birds and beasts … but they can slip silently through the woods with ease and are deadly marksmen. While a number of elite units in various civilizations had these abilities in the past, the first units to be named such were the colonial ranger units formed by Benjamin Church and by Robert Rogers during the French &amp; Indian War. In 1775 the Continental Congress authorized the formation of eight ranger companies to bedevil the Redcoats during the American rebellion; most European nations soon followed suit.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_REACTIVE_ARMOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As weapons improved, an “arms race” evolved between armor and armor-piercing technologies, one as old as war itself. In the late Middle Ages, inventors tried using padding on the inside and outside of the plate armor in hopes of ameliorating the effects of crossbow bolts and pikes (nothing worked very well). In the World wars, the answer was simply to add more layers of armor; again, it didn’t work very well. After World War II, various types of “reactive armor” were invented. The concept of explosive reactive armor was first proposed by the Russian Bogdan Voitsekhovsky in 1949, with the first production models appearing in the 1960s. Most main battle tanks now carry some form of reactive armor.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_REDEPLOY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Column, line, and square. The basic infantry formations until modern weapons like machine guns and rapid-firing artillery made bunching together butchery. Each formation had its benefits and its non-benefits. The ability to rapidly change from one to another was often the difference between victory and defeat for an infantry unit, and the subject of much training. Thus, redeploying from a mobile column into a line formation, capable of bringing all the muskets or pikes to bear on the battle, was a necessity; and woe to the line that couldn’t form a square quickly when the cuirassiers – “big men on big horses” – charged. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_REINFORCED_HULL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The widespread use of rams lead, inevitably, to efforts to reinforce the hulls that they smashed so frequently. The Greeks experimented with reinforcing the hulls with extra timbers as bracing, and even built a few very large ships around 200 BC with double hulls, one nested inside the outer: ships such as the Tessarakonteres, Thalamegos, Syracusia, and Leontophoros. Sadly, most of these were so unwieldy and heavy that they maneuvered poorly and tended to sink abruptly. Carthage not only reinforced their hulls with braces, but also their prows so they could smash enemy ships to pieces without self-inflicted damage. When steam came to war, reinforced hulls meant ever thicker steel plating.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_CREW_WEAPONS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Artillery crews – those manning the catapults and cannons – tended to be killed quickly if enemy troops reached them. The crew’s specialty was long distances, not hand-to-hand combat. But, most artillerists were lightly armed in the eventuality of things going horribly wrong; Roman artillery crew, for instance, had pilum to defend against enemy foot-soldiers that reached them, hopefully holding them off until other legionnaires could arrive. With the arrival of gunpowder, and advances in tactics (where cavalry were seen as the primary counter to field artillery), artillery crews were armed with pistols and short swords, and could of course use their tools (ramrods, spikes, shovels, and such) to fend off the unwanted attentions of enemy soldiers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_ARMOR_PIERCING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>From the time armored cavalry made their appearance on the battlefield, other armored cavalry was used to try and dissuade them from running over all the rest of the army. During the High Middle Ages, this took the form of opposing bodies of knights armed with jousting lances, tipped with pointy iron or steel socketed heads that could penetrate plate armor (knights usually also carried a sword or dagger to fight when unhorsed). Armored vehicles on the battlefield brought a new batch of armor-piercing weapons: armor-piercing high explosive (APHE), high-explosive incendiary (HEI), high-explosive anti-tank (HEAT), armor-piercing discarding sabot (APDS), and many other shells.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SCHILTRON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>During their wars of independence, the Scots devised the schiltron formation to counter the English advantages in numbers and weapons, using their 6- to 8-foot pikes to deter both infantry and cavalry, as when William Wallace drew up his schiltrons in a circle at Falkirk in 1298 AD. Schiltrons could be circular, or more commonly rectangular, the latter formations capable of both offensive as well as defensive actions, quite good at pushing back masses of English swordsmen. The first use of the schiltron offensively is credited to Robert the Bruce at Bannockburn, a glorious victory for the Scots. Thereafter, rectilinear schiltrons figured in a number of victories (and defeats as well), and the formation was adopted by the Welsh and Flemings as well.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_DEPREDATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Light cavalry were famed for depredation – not pillage or plunder, which entails carrying stuff off. Among most primitive tribes, this was the most common and effective form of warfare since they generally couldn’t face a civilized army in a stand-up fight. These depredations could lay waste to whole regions, the chevauchée (literally, “horse charge”) popular during the Hundred Years War, such as that carried out by the Black Prince in southern France in 1355 AD. The Prophet Muhammed preached the use of depredation during Islam’s initial expansions, a strategy perfectly suited to the Arab forces. As a policy, depredation lasted into the Napoleonic and American Civil wars, after which it fell out of favor. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SCOUT_PLANES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Reconnaissance was one of the first tasks when balloons and aeroplanes entered military affairs, and it was even more important on the vast, open oceans. It could prove quite embarrassing for an enemy fleet to sneak into range. Naval scout planes made their first appearance during World War I, usually one-seater craft launched from seaplane tenders or from battleships that had a short flight deck laid atop some of the gun turrets (unfortunately, these could not land, so the pilots had to ditch their planes in the water beside the ship and wait to be rescued). Between the wars, a search for better solutions lead to catapults and arresting gear, and true aircraft carriers made their appearance, each with its compliment of long-range scout planes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SILENT_RUNNING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once surface warships – especially the destroyers, corvettes, and frigates – got sonar, things were not nearly as easy for submarine crews. Sonar was developed towards the end of World War I, too late to take a hand in defeating the U-boat “scourge.” But with unusual foresight, by the next big war many of the smaller escort ships had passive sonar and were listening to the depths for sound of a lurking sub so they could drop depth charges and eliminate it. The only way to counter all that pinging for the submarine was to engage in “silent running,” silencing all superfluous noises. Engines were cut, ventilation minimized, and the crew kept quiet … usually silently praying and hoping the enemy above would pass over them unaware. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_AMBUSH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Anthropologists and archaeologists have suggested that prehistoric men used ambush on dangerous prey, and later on each other. So the art of taking advantage of concealment and stealth to surprise the enemy, get in a couple of blows, and then run away has been a staple of warfare for a long time. Ambush is intended to hit the stronger enemy hard, cause disproportionate casualties through the element of surprise, and then fade away into the brush rather than stand and fight. It has been the favored tactic of barbarians for millennia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_PURSUIT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>One of the greatest advantages of light cavalry in comparison with heavy was that the light were significantly faster, and therefore ideal for pursuing and taking down defeated enemy troops, stragglers, and camp followers. Indeed, their mobility and speed meant that light cavalry were still being used at the opening of World War I, whereas the heavier types had been disbanded. With the development of armored warfare, the distinction returned, with main battle tanks considered “heavy cavalry” and the armored cars and light tanks, still significantly faster than their lumbering brethren, the “light.” And, when necessary, the mechanized light cavalry can still run over the defeated without slowing down.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SPYGLASS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>No one is quite sure who devised the first spyglass, a single optical tube fitted with a ground lens for magnifying objects at a distance; it was likely some nameless Chinese or Arabic tinkerer, for it was known that spyglasses were in use in both empires by 1608 AD when the Dutchman Jacob Metius began producing his commercially. Metius’s apparatus had a 15mm lens at one end and a double concave eyepiece that gave a magnification of about 3x. Not only was it popular with sailors, but soon every general just had to have one … as did their reconnaissance scouts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SPY_ACE_DRIVER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Occasionally spies have to escape, and the popular image – fostered by far too many action movies – is as the object of a high-speed chase by the nefarious villains or authorities. (In point of fact, if it comes to this pass, the agent will more reasonably try to blend in and slip away by public transport.) But during World War II and the Cold War, several agencies had evasive driving courses for their operatives, teaching them such maneuvers as the J-turn, powerslide, fishtailing, and PIT (“precision immobilization technique”). Historical instances of a spy outracing capture in a vehicle are non-existent, but why spoil a good story?</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SPY_CAT_BURGLAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Like the infamous (albeit fictional) Arthur J. Raffles or (real) Bill Mason, cat burglars steal valuables. Spies too are occasionally called upon to pilfer things – plans, designs, codes … and artwork. The latter either to embarrass a foreign government, or to reclaim their national cultural artifacts that have been looted or stolen previously. The ability to slip in and out undetected, leaving the authorities baffled, is a skill that has brought more than one master thief to employment in an intelligence service. The most successful heists are never, of course, announced or admitted by either the victims or the agents.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SPY_CON_ARTIST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The art of the great con according to some successful confidence men –Victor Lustig (who sold the Eiffel Tower … twice), Charles Ponzi (whose “get-rich-quick” scam was named after him), and Ferdinand Demara (known as “the Great Imposter”) – is to “read the mark,” and then cater to his/her greatest weakness(es). Whether seeking to empty a bank account or destabilize an entire economy (such as the German “Operation Bernhard” during World War II), the tricks of con artists and spies often overlap. Both, for instance, use the cackle-bladder regularly, fooling some hapless sap into believing someone has been killed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SPY_DEMOLITIONS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Sabotage, by spies or members of a resistance movement, is hard to prevent and quite effective.  Pervasive “simple sabotage” (such as slashing tires, contaminating fuel, ruining machine parts, cutting electrical wires, and the like) can be conducted by almost anyone; for really big things – like the Black Tom explosion in Jersey City which destroyed warehouses and ships full of munitions and fuel in July 1916 – it takes training. During World War II, the American OSS (later renamed the CIA) taught hundreds of Allied saboteurs the tricks of identifying key components in machinery… and how to blow them up.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SPY_DISGUISE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Any old thing – wig, glasses, cotton stuck in the cheeks, padding over the belly, or even just a change of clothes – is a disguise, so long as it alters a person’s appearance. Disguise is the stock in trade of actors, criminals, and spies. Generally, disguises in espionage are used briefly to slip in and out of places, usually as someone who ostensibly belongs there; occasionally, as for deep-cover agents, the disguise is somewhat more permanent, and may even entail surgery. So long as the fake appearance matches the forged identity papers, all is well.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SPY_GUERILLA_LEADER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Romantic, historic, drenched in blood: Massoud, Che, Mao, Fidel, l’Ouverture, Avraham Stern, Michael Collins, and hundreds more. For centuries intelligence services have been supporting, financially or materially, guerrilla leaders fighting wars of revolution or resistance. In some cases, this backing is overt, and in others covert. But the goal is the same, to discomfort the power on the other side of the conflict. While these leaders are not (usually) the agents of a spy ring, their irregular warfare nevertheless benefits the sponsor. And brings ever more partisans to their chaotic standard.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SPY_LINGUIST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>For both espionage and counterespionage, being fluent in several languages is a boon. It helps in all sorts of missions, from surveillance to infiltration. While early spies were often recruited solely because of their facility with a language, by the opening salvos of World War II, most intelligence agencies had their own schools to train agents in the language(s) of the enemy. And linguistic complexities made it difficult for some nations to be spied upon, as with the Japanese and Chinese. During the Cold War, both the CIA and the KGB even established institutes to study linguistics seeking to overcome such challenges.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SPY_QUARTERMASTER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Who can resist nifty little gadgets? Certainly not those in the field of espionage. Since the first spies used “invisible” ink and hidden weapons, the quartermasters of the world’s intelligence agencies have had an ever expanding inventory of inventions to help in the craft of stealing or protecting secrets. While the list of devices may not be as long as in the James Bond series, the British Secret Intelligence Service – better known as MI6 – supposedly maintains an extensive (and deadly) collection at its headquarters at 85 Vauxhall Cross. But, of course, no one is quite sure what these might be.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SPY_ROCKET_SCIENTIST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Operation Paperclip” was a long-running (1949-1990) OSS/CIA program to bring scientists, engineers, and technicians from Nazi Germany and other countries to work in America on (primarily) rocket and nuclear projects. By the time of its suspension, over 1500 “rocket scientists” had been recruited, blackmailed, or lured to work in and for the United States. As much as American progress, the purpose of the operation was to deny these folk to the Soviet Union, which had its own “Operation Osoaviakhim” doing the same thing. Among the more notable brought to America: Werner von Braun, Kurt Debus, Hubertus Strughold, and Arthur Rudolph.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SPY_SEDUCTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Seduction, as an espionage tactic, is as old as sin (so they say); in a classic honeypot mission, an illicit liaison would lead to blackmail, by which the patsy would be forced to reveal classified information or perform other chores – in other words, to act as an agent for the seducer. During the height of the Cold War, the Soviet KGB and East German Stasi actively trained agents (termed “swallows” if female or “ravens” if male) to entrap foreigners … the most notorious case being that of the Marine Clayton Lonetree.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SPY_TECHNOLOGIST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>While espionage has been practiced since the days of Francis Walsingham (“spymaster” to Elizabeth I), the advent of modern warfare made acquisition of information on technology a priority. Such skullduggery reached its peak during World War II and the subsequent Cold War. American operations such as “LUSTY” (to uncover and evaluate German aeronautical technology) and the Technical Air Intelligence Units (to retrieve and analyze Japanese aircraft) characterize this sort of espionage. Later, Soviet and American moles dug about to see what secrets they could steal in research institutions, ministries, and factories - work now done by government-funded hackers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SQUARE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>An infantry square is a formation whereby the infantry close ranks, facing outward on all sides, to deter cavalry attack. The Romans, faced with battling horse barbarians numerous times, devised it according to Plutarch; the legions at the battle of Carrhae, for instance, used the square successfully to neutralize the Parthians. The mounted infantry of the Han dynasty dismounted and formed squares in their many battles against the fearsome Xiongnu. The square formation, which fell out of favor during the Middle Ages, was revived in the 14th Century, and would figure prominently during the Napoleonic Wars. Unfortunately, densely packed infantrymen – as in a square – tended to be susceptible to artillery. But they remained the best deterrent to cavalry charges.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_STRAFE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Soon after machine guns were fitted to biplane fighters, pilots with unused ammunition returning from a mission amused themselves diving and firing upon ground targets … usually the poor infantry and supply convoys stuck below in the mud of the Western Front. In short order, generals saw the value in doing so, and so strafing became a part of aerial tactics (it was less dangerous than dogfights). Aviation designers even began building planes dedicated to ground attack, such as the Junkers J.1 with two downwards facing machine guns. Come World War II most of the combatants had warplanes devoted to strafing, most mounting multiple machine guns and some small rockets.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SUPERFORTRESS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Carpet bombing – also known as area bombing, saturation bombing, and the descriptive obliteration bombing – is a wave of bombers dropping large amounts of untargeted explosives to inflict maximum damage on every part of a selected area of land. This indiscriminate bombing of an entire area is quite effective, if expensive in terms of munitions, in leveling fields and farms, industrial areas, neighborhoods, and everything else. The first instance of carpet bombing was that by the Condor Legion during the Spanish Civil War against enemy forces scattered on the rocky slopes during the battle of El Mazuco. Throughout World War II, all the major combatants resorted to carpet bombing techniques. Eventually, of course, such bombing against areas containing a “concentration of civilians” was outlawed by the 1977 Protocol I of the Geneva Convention.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SUPER_CARRIER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The first ship to be described by journalists as a “supercarrier” was the HMS Ark Royal in 1938, 685 feet long and capable of carrying 72 aircraft (though it didn’t do her much good when torpedoed in 1941). Next, the Americans declared their 45-thousand ton Midway-class of carriers as “super” in 1943; three were completed. But it was the Cold War nuclear-powered carriers of the United States and Russia that might legitimately be called supercarriers. Virtually floating cities, the American Nimitz-class carriers have unlimited range for 20-25 years, driven by two nuclear reactors, carry over 5000 ship and flight crew, have between 85-90 planes and helicopters, and have a displacement between 100-104 thousand tons. And that doesn’t even count the missiles aboard.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SUPPLY_FLEET_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Ships in the age of coal, fuel oil, and diesel used a lot of fuel and munitions during war. A ship tender – or as the Royal Navy termed these, depot ship – was the answer to not having warships shuttle back and forth to port. In effect, these were mobile maintenance bases, able to resupply or repair the ships that did the dirty work. Often these were dedicated to a specific type of ship, as with the British destroyer tenders of the world wars. Almost anything with a large cargo capacity could serve as a tender … and did. In fact, during World War II the Germans used modified Type XIV submarines (nicknamed 'Milchkuh') to resupply U-boats at sea with fuel, motor oil, torpedoes and food.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SUPPRESSION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to NATO, suppression is “the application of fire, direct or indirect, to destroy, neutralize or suppress the enemy’s movement.” Before NATO so nicely defined the term, the Royal Army defined it as “fire delivered to render a target temporarily ineffective.” In other words, firing at someone tends to slow them down … a brilliant insight that military commanders had been aware of long before NATO. But suppression fire requires a lot of ammunition fired rapidly, so it wasn’t used often until the advent of industrial age warfare, when it became a common tactic.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_COURSERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As war evolved, and cavalry evolved into “light” and “heavy,” different types of horses were bred with differing abilities. By the Middle Ages, the destrier – the massive, slow but powerful mount for the knights and nobility – was highly prized; but far more common was the courser, strong and swift. Usually ridden by men-at-arms and squires, these were battle-trained, lightly-armored, and used to operate on the flanks of the battle, riding down archers, artillerymen, and others.  (Meanwhile, of course, the heavy knights on their destriers were duking it out for God, king, and glory in the center.) Valuable, but far less expensive than a destrier, the courser was the workhorse of the medieval army.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_SWIFT_KEEL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As time passed in the salt sea after construction, the hull of a ship became fouled with marine life (notably, barnacles and shipworms) and suffered rot and corrosion. All of which slowed it considerably, and the hull became less streamlined and sturdy. Although various remedies had been tried over the centuries, it was not until the use of copper sheathing was pioneered and developed by the Royal Navy in the mid-18th Century that a “cure” was found (although the American Revolution slowed the refitting). It proved a boon to naval raiders, who found it challenging to find a place to scrape and clean their hull. Thus, British-built raiders such as the copper-sheathed CSS Alabama, Florida and Shenandoah were both fast and able to remain at sea for long-periods.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_TACTICAL_MAINTENANCE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Englishman Conrad Hal Waddington had been educated as a biologist, and would subsequently be an influential geneticist and philosopher who laid the foundations for “systems biology.” But, with the outbreak of World War II, he answered the call and was promptly assigned to operational research for Coastal Command. The command’s B-24 Liberator bombers were spending an inordinate amount of time grounded for maintenance; Waddington’s team gathered data and concluded that too much time was being spent on preventive maintenance as opposed to repairs necessary to keep the bombers at combat readiness. These findings lead to his concept of "force readiness"; although foregoing regular maintenance might lead to problems with some planes, far fewer were out of action at any given time. In fact, effective flying hours for Coastal Command’s bombers increased by around 60%.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_TANK_BUSTER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The last battles of World War I featured the first appearance of tanks, and generals soon sought a way to destroy these; attacking them from the air seemed a logical approach. But, given that most fighters of the day were unarmored and their weapons could rarely penetrate the tank armor, they weren’t very effective … in fact, the RAF suffered losses approaching 30% among ground-attack aircraft in 1918. But when Europe went at it again in 1939, fighter-bombers devoted to attacking tanks were common, such as the German Stuka, British Hurricane Mk IID, and Russian Sturmovik. As the war progressed, even standard fighters were up-armed with cannons and rockets to make them “tank busters.” </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_THRUST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Spears – both those for throwing and those for thrusting – have been used since prehistoric times for the hunt and for war. The ones meant for thrusting tend to be heavier, sturdier, and used with one or two hands. By the Bronze Age, spears with socketed metal heads were the most common weapon; and around the 7th Century BC the Greeks created the phalanx, a close-order formation to utilize thrusting spears up to nine feet long in dense ranks. The unwieldly Greek spear eventually gave way to various pole weapons, which combined the thrust of the spear with the cutting edge of the axe: the halberd, glaive, bill, and pike … the latter the dominate weapon in the 1500s and 1600s. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_BOX_FORMATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>During World War I, primitive bombers operated in ones, twos, and threes; so the formation they adopted wasn’t really significant, although having overlapping fields of fire to the rear was beneficial. But, the mass bomber raids of World War II were another matter; formations helped defend against enemy fighters, deliver the most bombs on target, and kept the bombers from running into each other. With losses among the first USAAF daylight missions over occupied Europe reaching staggering numbers, Colonel Curtis LeMay developed the combat box formation in August 1942. By December 1942, while losses were still high, these had dropped substantially. In short order, the “Javelin Down” combat box formation was adopted by both the Americans and British for all bombing operations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_BARDING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As history turned from the Dark Ages to the Middle Ages in Europe, the padded armor of caparison was replaced with the barding of plate armor for the noble steeds of the knights. Caparisons didn’t stand up to the increased effectiveness of crossbows, longbows, and pikes, and the horses became primary targets (rather than the well-armored riders). Barding from chest protectors to the full harness of plate armor, developed first in the armories of Lombardy. Complete barding consisted of five main pieces: chanfron (face), crinière (neck), croupier (hind quarters), flanchard (flanks) and peytral (chest). Destriers, thus accoutered, would dominate European warfare for three centuries.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_TORPEDO_BOMBER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In June 1914, Arthur Longmore dropped the first aerial torpedo at the Royal Navy Air Station at Calshot. While aerial torpedoes weren’t used much during World War I (their warheads tended to explode when hitting the water), several nations thought there was potential in them – notably Britain, America, and Japan. During the inter-war years, all three devoted significant efforts to developing more reliable torpedoes and designing special aircraft to deliver these. Torpedo bombers, both land-based and carrier-launched, would prove pretty effective during the upcoming war, as at Taranto and at Pearl Harbor. Although aerial torpedoes are generally obsolete now, naval warfare changed forever under the shadow of the torpedo bombers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_TORTOISE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Romans, bedeviled by barbarians who insisted on shooting at them, devised the testudo – or “tortoise” – formation to counter that foolishness. In effect, the outer ranks of a packed formation aligned their shields to form an all-round wall, while those within raised theirs to cover the top. So long as the tortoise held, they were covered from shin to skull. Once the enemy stopped throwing things, the legionnaires could quickly break the formation and get on with slaughtering the savages. Plutarch was the first to describe the testudo, used by Mark Anthony during his invasion of Parthia in 25 BC.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_TRANSLATOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Whether a priest, missionary, or even a prophet, it helps to speak the language of one’s flock. Training missionaries in the local tongue (as for instance, the Catholic Church did with missionaries to the Norsemen) and converting holy texts so the locals could read the holy texts themselves has had an enormous impact on the success of all that preaching. Indeed, there is even a patron saint of translation (there are saints for just about everything), one Jerome of Stridon who translated the Hebrew Bible into Latin. But, as the Buddhist monks who translated Indian sutras into Chinese did, sometimes the holy word got adjusted to take account of cultural sensibilities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_MARAUDING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Heavy cavalry wasn’t much good in urban combat, and the mounted soldiers usually dismounted to join in the looting, despoiling, and such after a city had fallen. Breaching the walls and actually capturing the city was left to the poor infantry and artillery. However, cavalry was very good at terrorizing un-walled neighborhoods, marauding through the streets and riding down civilians and soldiers alike that didn’t get out of their way. Things haven’t changed much between antiquity and modern times; tanks still aren’t very good in street fighting, but are superb at blitzing through the suburbs … Stalingrad, Berlin, Manila, etc.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_URBAN_WARFARE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Some 5500 years ago, before writing was invented to record it, the people of the city of Hamoukar, near rich copper mines, were subjected to the first known instance of urban warfare when an army from the city of Uruk attacked and fought their way through the streets, killing most everyone. Fighting in built-up areas is a tactical nightmare, but by the Middle Ages some military units came to specialize in it. When a town’s walls were breached, these foot soldiers would pour through the gap to end the resistance in hand-to-hand combat (since neither mounted nor missile troops were much use in the narrow confines), as at Jerusalem and Constantinople during the Crusades.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_VOLLEY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Volley fire, which saved those Redcoats more than once, dates back long before muskets; it was used by formations of archers in ancient civilizations to fire a bunch of arrows simultaneously on command, making up for the inaccuracy, slow rate of fire, and limited range of primitive bows. After the first release, usually fire was either done by ranks – as at Agincourt where English longbowmen slaughtered the French knights – or “at will.” Given that most of the militia armies until the 1600s were untrained peasants, the tactic worked fairly well against equally untrained charging militia. When the musket appeared on the European battlefield, the tactic was adopted, likely first by Maurice of Nassau in 1594.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_ROUT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Heavy cavalry comes into its own when it can ride down a defeated enemy, especially those in a chaotic and disorderly rout. An orderly retreat can quickly turn into a rout when heavy cavalry attack units that have already suffered significant casualties; the result: a state of “every man for himself,” ideal for those fast-moving cavalry men with their lances and sabers. In fact, in general more soldiers have been killed in the rout than in the battle. And tanks work just as well as heavy cavalry in turning retreat into rout, as the Germans proved repeatedly during their blitzkrieg across Europe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_PROXIMITY_FUSES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Some 2800 kamikaze planes sank 34 Allied warships and damaged 368 others during the final, desperate days of the Pacific war … thus about 14 percent of kamikaze pilots got through to score a hit. Given this, little wonder that naval gunners developed their own methods of dealing with diving kamikazes. While light, rapid-fire AA guns such as the Bofors and Oerlikon autocannons could, and did, throw up a lot of metal in the path of the oncoming plane, it was fire of the heavier AA (such as the 38-caliber) that had the punch to knock one out of the sky if they could hit it. But in early 1945, radio frequency proximity fuses – seven times more effective than previous ones – finally became available and turned the tide.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_HOMING_TORPEDOES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Following the development of a prototype self-propelled naval torpedo by the Austro-Hungarians in 1864, and its subsequent manufacture by the British engineer Robert Whitehead, naval warfare evolved yet again. The Germans had a deep interest in torpedo technology, and as the convoy system made things more difficult for the U-boats in World War II, German scientists devised the programmable pattern-running torpedoes. These would follow a pre-set pattern until they ran out of fuel or hit something, perfect against formations of ships. Next came “homing” torpedoes, which used acoustics to pick up the sounds of a wake and follow it to an enemy ship. These two “fire-and-forget” weapon systems made things grim for the Allied convoys for the rest of the war.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_WOLFPACK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Admiral Karl Donitz coined the term Rudeltaktik (or “tactics of a pack”) to describe his strategy of U-boat warfare in the Atlantic; it was the Allies that used “wolfpack” to refer to the mass-attack of gathered subs against convoys – less accurate, but more metaphoric. As the war progressed, rather than simply wandering about until a target was found for their torpedoes, U-boats patrolled separately but strung out along coordinated lines across convoy lanes. When a U-boat captain spotted a convoy, he signaled the others of the “pack” to gather and launch a series of attacks on the merchants while bypassing their overstretched escorts. It was highly effective, until advances in detection gear and anti-sub weaponry won the Battle of the Atlantic in late 1944.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITPROMOTIONS_PAGE_PROMOTION_ZWEIHANDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The 'Zweihänder' (also known as the 'Beidhänder') is a type of two-handed longsword, common during the 16th Century AD and much favored by the German and Swiss Landsknechte. Eventually, so deadly were they against spear and pike-armed units that the Swiss outlawed them, although the Germans kept on until muskets became common. Heavy, long and double-edged, the Zweihänder could chop through spears and pikes with relative ease, and had the reach to do so before the swordsman could be impaled … such as at the battle of Fornovo in 1495. Hardly honorable, but quite effective.</Text>
		</Row>
	</BaseGameText>
</GameData>