<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<BaseGameText>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_INTRO_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
      <Text>Improvements can increase the [ICON_Production] Production, [ICON_Gold] Gold, and [ICON_Food] Food output of your tiles. They also provide access to special bonuses provided by certain resources. If you do not improve your land, your civilization will almost certainly be overwhelmed by more established civilizations.</Text>
    </Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_AIRSTRIP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When early aeronauts needed a place to land in a hurry, any field that was fairly level and without things sticking up would serve … much to the surprise of many a farmer. In time, some of these became well-known and often used, thus an “airstrip.” In remote locations around the world, these extended air travel to everywhere. Most consisted of a grassy runway and perhaps some fueling storage tanks and pumps. Not many amenities, but these weren’t intended for tourists and the casual traveler. Unlike aerodromes and airports – although some airstrips did mature into these – airstrips were more for unplanned stops than not, or as a means to land near some backwater settlement. Oil fields, lumber camps, sheep stations, cattle ranches and the like often boosted an airstrip. Some still do.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_BARBARIAN_CAMP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Historically, barbarians came in two types: those who wandered about and those that settled down. The latter became “civilized” and built cities, empires and such. The former plagued the latter, raiding the borders and upsetting the empire’s citizens. Generally organized along tribal lines, these barbarians – far from the “noble savage” stereotype, most of them really were brutal, cruel and warlike – were nomads, establishing temporary outposts from which to attack civilization and each other as well. When the fun of all that rampaging wore off, or when an organized army showed up and thrashed them, the surviving barbarians would pack up and move on, to establish another outpost sometime later somewhere else. Since it was generally a good idea – if one were a barbarian – not to be easily found by the civilized, the outposts over time were located in more inaccessible (and defensible) places … until, of course, there were no such places left.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_BEACH_RESORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Seaside resorts have been around since the Roman Empire, the first where folk – rich folk – had the time to spend lying about; the Roman town of Baiae on the Gulf of Naples, the island of Capri and the doomed town of Pompeii were all favored by the elite of the empire. But it wasn’t until the mid-18th Century that the wealthy took to the waters at seaside resorts in droves as part of their conspicuous consumption; the first to cater to the indolent rich was Scarborough in 1720 AD. In 1793 Heiligendamm opened, bringing Europe’s aristocracy to the shores of the Baltic. With the coming of the Industrial Revolution, the nouveau riche joined them in splashing about in warm waters. Then, as working hours declined and disposable income increased, even the working classes could join them at Brighton, Nice and Coney Island … forcing the filthy rich to go to places like Monte Carlo and Acapulco for their sun and fun.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_CAMP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once upon a time, a camp was vital to survival … whether it was a temporary shelter thrown up by wandering barbarians or a semi-permanent hunting camp supplying game, fish or fowl to the growing population. Until mankind learned to domesticate and pen livestock for a more dependable source of meat, hunting camps kept civilization going. In time, camps took on new roles, such as supplying furs, firewood, or trading opportunities with the nearby natives. Today, more often than not, a “camp” – temporary or permanent – is simply a recreational site where the city slickers can “get back to nature.” And now civilized folk hunt game, fish, and fowl for sport rather than survival.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_CHATEAU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If one must ask, one cannot afford it. A château is a manor house or country home of landed gentry, usually without fortifications. In the Middle Ages, a château was largely self-sufficient, being supported by the lord's demesne (hereditary lands). In the 1600s, the wealthy and aristocratic French lords dotted the countryside with elegant, luxuriant, architecturally refined mansions such as the Château de Maisons. But many of these stately homes were burned during peasant revolts and populist revolutions. But a few remain as tourist attractions. Today, the term château is loosely used; for instance, it is common for any winery or inn, no matter how humble, to prefix its name with "Château.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_FARM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once people figured out that it was a lot easier to stay in one place and grow crops, rather than wander about gathering whatever happened to be growing, “civilization” broke out. Around 12,000 years ago, this was the “Neolithic Revolution.” Farming meant that permanent settlements could be self-sustaining, and that the more food that could be harvested, the bigger settlements could grow. Ever since, advances in technology have been making agriculture more efficient: irrigation, machinery, fertilizers, pesticides, GMOs and so forth. Yields skyrocketed. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_FISHING_BOATS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Behold, I am going to send for many fishermen,” declared the Lord, “and they will fish for them.” (Jeremiah 16:16) And so it has been since men first cast hooks and nets into the waters, whether from the sea shore or the river bank. Eventually, those fisher folk built boats to pursue the fish into deeper waters. A number of civilizations – from the Polynesians of the Pacific to the Norse along the North Sea – depended upon fishing for food, oil, raw materials, and trade goods. Even where agriculture was viable, fishing boats supplied essentials unavailable by any other means. From small dinghies to large commercial vessels, fishing boats operate out of every port; as of 2004 AD, there were some four million registered fishing boats. Trawlers, seiners, longliners and whalers have prowled the seas for centuries. And some folk even think of fishing as a sport...</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_COLOSSAL_HEAD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The colossal “Olmec Heads,” 17 stone sculptures dating to before 900 BC, are the best known remnants (at least, by tourists) of the once flourishing MesoAmerican Olmec civilization. Carved from a single boulder and then transported many miles, each depicts the head and face of a mature man, likely that of a powerful Olmec ruler, or as some theories would have it,  famous ball players (if so, not much has changed). The massive heads weigh between six (the smallest) and 50 tons (the largest, but unfinished), made from basalt from quarries in the Sierra de los Tuxtlas range near Veracruz. Given that the Olmec had no metal tools, the effort to scatter these sculptures across the countryside was immense … yet another instance of mankind’s desire to leave their mark on the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_FORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since the first ego-maniacal chieftain threw up a wall of dirt and proclaimed everything behind it his, soldiers have been building fortifications. Whether to pacify new territory, protect the borders, or insure that the ruled didn’t get uppity, the military-minded have dug ditches and moats, planted stakes and spikes, and put up walls of all sorts. Some made such military engineering an art form, such as the Roman legions, which could march through the day and have a fortified camp in place by nightfall. In time, the appearance of gunpowder led to innovations in fortifications; those wooden and stone walls were simply no longer adequate. So, rather than build up, fortifications went down – trenches and bunkers, pillboxes and minefields, barbed wire and “defense in depth.” But the intent remains the same, to protect the troops and keep the civilization safe from both without and within.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_ROMAN_FORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>{LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_FORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_GOODY_HUT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Tribal villages were where the unwashed, uncivilized lived. Out beyond the pale. When explorers from “civilized” places arrived in these villages, the natives often greeted them with open arms, gifts, information, awe and respect. Tribal villages were distinguished from civilized settlements by a number of factors – their faiths tended to be experiential, their government local, their economies barter-based, their laws commonsensical, their organizations cooperative (rather than competitive), their social structures straightforward, their families extended, and their culture practical. In fact, some of these tribal villages evolved into cities, where none of that primitivism survived.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_GREAT_WALL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A fortified border took on new meaning when some civilizations attempted to make sure the uncivilized stayed out. A number of empires built “great walls” – the Roman Hadrian’s Wall, the Chola-Pandya Madukkarai Wall, the Sassanid Great Wall of Gorgan, the French Maginot Line, and, of course, the Great Wall of China. Most were built of earth and stone, most incorporated natural terrain features (hills, rivers, and the like), and most had fortresses or garrisons scattered along their length. They were built in stages, sometimes over a long period of time. In terms of intent, none of these worked very well, for the outsiders managed time and again to “cross” the frontier walls, no matter how great. On the other hand, these great walls did provide a psychological sop to the empire’s citizens, and did deter the less barbaric barbarians from raiding the frontier settlements. With history having passed them by, most of the great walls have fallen into disrepair and obscurity … or become tourist traps.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_KURGAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>For some reason, some of civilization’s greatest feats of engineering and construction are mausoleums and tombs, and, for some reason, these great piles are usually reserved for military and political leaders. For the Scythians these piles were great mounds of dirt, now called kurgans, from the Turkish word for “mound.” It appears that a number of the barbarian nomads of the steppes of Central Asia began interring their leaders in these mounds sometime around the 4th Century BC. By the Early Iron Age, the kurgans of the Scythians and other tribes were truly impressive mounds, some as much as 500 meters (1600 feet) across at the base, and might stand as high as 27 meters (89 feet). So, these tended to stand out on the rolling open terrain of the steppes. And then the Scythians decorated the tumuli with the bodies of slaves and horses, just to insure it got everyone’s attention that here lie a great man (or perhaps woman).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_LUMBER_MILL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>For centuries the purpose of a lumber mill has not changed: logs go in one end, and cut beams, boards, posts, and shingles come out the other. The earliest known sawmill that can be reliably dated is a Roman water-powered mill uncovered at Hierapolis dating to the 3rd Century AD. Small, water-powered mills were common throughout Europe and the Middle East where trees were plentiful, and the designs later went with European colonists so they could start chopping down the virgin forests everywhere else as well. The Industrial Revolution speeded the whole process, as steam railroads could transport the logs to steam lumber mills, and then haul the “finished” (in more ways than one) wood products to market in the booming cities. In time, even the byproducts of the trimming and cutting were used – for paper, fuel, and packing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_MINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The extraction of valuable (or sometimes not so valuable) minerals is as much part of civilization as farming or making war. Even in “pre-historic” times, the Neolithic hunter-gatherers dug flint out of seams, creating mines such as those at Grimes Graves (c. 4000 BC). The Egyptians mined malachite, the Greeks silver, the Romans tin and lead, and every civilization since has found something in the earth they needed or wanted. Most of the work until the Industrial Revolution was done by hand, whether the mining was an open pit or underground tunnel, by slaves or wage-slaves using picks and shovels and hammers. Some of civilization's first great corporations were mining concerns, and prospectors pushed the frontiers ever outward. Today, machines do all the hard work – the prospecting and mining and refining. So efficient are they at stripping out everything valuable and moving on that there are currently upwards of 560 thousand abandoned mines in the United States alone.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_MISSILE_SILO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Like everything else rocketry, the Germans pioneered the underground missile silo – building the first such complex near Saint-Omer in 1944. It was intended to store and launch V2s on England, but never entered service due to heavy Allied bombing. The British toyed with the idea of underground launch facilities in the 1950s for their missiles, and even built one, before opting for using submarines to launch their ICBMs. It was the Americans and Russians, however, who really took to the idea of planting nuclear missiles underground – as though that would help in the event of World War III. The primary purpose of the silos was to insure the rapid launch of Soviet UR-100 or American Titan II missiles to insure mutual destruction. Since the Cold War, the Russians have moved most of their ICBMs to submarines, the Americans have about 450 silos still in operation, and China has built a few silos but still favors mobile ICBM launchers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_MISSION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to the Catholic Church, missions are religious communities devoted to teaching, tending, and helping the local populace, thus supporting Christ’s ideals. Of course, the Spanish, Portuguese and French missions were also devoted to converting the locals and then “civilizing” them through cultural assimilation. The Spanish missions serve as the traditional template, self-supporting enclaves with churches, dormitories, fields and pastures, gardens, barns, workrooms, hospitals and schools. In places these were even fortified, ready to defend themselves from opposition. Most of the missions in the Americas, Asia, and Africa were administered by religious orders such as the Franciscans, Jesuits, Dominicans, and Augustinians rather than the Church itself, but the effects were the same. Nonetheless, the missions often served as a nucleus around which European colonizing efforts could coalesce.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_OFFSHORE_OIL_RIG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>At one time, long ago, an offshore platform was used by primitives for fishing, harvesting kelp, or gathering shells. But once civilization discovered all the uses for oil, offshore platforms became massive constructs anchored in deep waters to squeeze out the oil below the seabed. The first underwater oil drilling was on platforms on pilings in the fresh water Ohio lake St. Mary’s in 1891 AD. The first true offshore rig went up in 1896 at the Summerland field off the California coast near Santa Barbara. Soon enough, offshore platforms were sprouting off the Texas and Louisiana coastline in the 1910s, in the Caspian Sea near Azerbaijan in the 1920s, the Persian Gulf, the North Sea, the Campos and Santos basins off Brazil, and every place else the oil companies set their sights on. Submarine pipelines finally solved the problem of getting the oil ashore cheaply. Although oil rigs are expensive, and occasionally one sinks or leaks, the profits outweigh the costs … at least in the short term.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_OIL_WELL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As J. Paul Getty put it, “Formula for success: rise early, work hard, strike oil.” Ever since the first oil wells were drilled in China around 340 AD, using metal bits attached to bamboo poles, men have been trying to do just that. Throughout the millennium and a half since then, the technology has advanced, spurred by civilization finding new ways to use all the things that come from petroleum: gasoline, lubricants, asphalt, petrochemicals, tar, plastics, fertilizer, pesticides, and a thousand other things. The first “modern” commercial oil well in North America came online in Oil Springs, Ontario, in 1858. Then came the development of the automobile, and humanity’s thirst for oil became insatiable. Since then, wars have been fought for it, regimes toppled because of it, and unchecked pollution has resulted from it. But then too, unbelievable fortunes have been made from it – as Getty could attest.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_PASTURE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since it is a lot easier to keep track of livestock if they aren’t running loose across the countryside, it wasn’t long after grazing animals were domesticated that a lazy shepherd devised a fence for keeping them in a pasture. Even those pastoralists who practiced transhumance had crude pastures at each end of their seasonal journeys. Pastures (not to be confused with meadows) are typically grazed throughout the summer, and may be purposely planted or simply fenced-off rangeland. The fences can be made of almost anything that will keep the livestock in and the local predators (animal or human) out: rock and stone, posts and rails, thorny brush, barbed wire, or electric wire. In most places, land ownership was tied to fenced pasturage, as in feudal societies or those progressive ranchers in the American West. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_PLANTATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Not just a fancy sort of farm (although some of them have really nice houses), a plantation is a large agrarian enterprise generally devoted to a single valuable “cash” crop – cotton, tobacco, tea, sugar cane, rubber, coffee and such – tended by resident laborers. The crops are usually, but not always, indigenous to the region, and most of the plantations in history were in tropical or semi-tropical climes. The crops did well with all the rain and heat, and it meant the plantation owner didn’t have to waste money keeping the workers warm. As Europeans spread their empires around the globe, they took the plantation formula with them to the Americas, India and Africa. The produce was not meant for local consumption, but was shipped out to the markets of Europe where the civilized folk could appreciate this rich bounty.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_QUARRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once people started building structures out of stone rather than sticks and mud, the need for stone and rock increased. Those came from quarries, an open pit where picks and hammers and chisels (and later dynamite and bulldozers) were used to hack out chunks of marble, limestone, granite, slate, sandstone, or whatever else was useful. As the tools became more sophisticated, slabs could be cut away, and then polished on the site. The oldest known quarries have been located in the Aswan region of Egypt, and the lands of the once Roman Empire are dotted with marble quarries (they needed a lot for all those grand buildings). Whereas the Egyptians and Romans and other civilized ancients mostly used slaves and condemned criminals (life expectancy in quarries not being long), on Easter Island the entire community chipped moai out of quarries. Today, quarry miners are considered skilled professionals.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_SPHINX_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In contrast to the Greek version, the Egyptian sphinx has a human head on a lion’s body, is benevolent, and is the guardian of temples and tombs. Perhaps the first Egyptian sphinx constructed was during the Fourth Dynasty (c. 2500 BC) that depicted the face of Queen Hetepheres II, daughter of famed Khufu. But the sphinx was a common motif among those eternity-obsessed pharaohs; other famous ones include that depicting Hatshepsut and the “alabaster sphinx” of Memphis. Then there is that “Great Sphinx” at Giza that bears the likeness of the pharaoh Khafra (who is otherwise historically insignificant). Smaller ones lined the approaches to tombs and temples, and any number were put at the top of stairways in palaces and public places. By the 18th Dynasty, one could hardly swing a cat in Egypt without hitting a sphinx.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_STEPWELL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A “stepwell” is a well or pool that can be reached by a set of steps. Although found in other regions, stepwells (known by a variety of names) are prevalent in India and Southeast Asia. The first rock-cut stepwells in India date from around 200 BC, and by 600 AD they were common throughout the Gujarat region; scholars believe that “cylindrical brick-lined wells” were a product of the early Bronze Age Indus Valley civilization. Many of the ancient Indian settlements had stepwells, and the elaborate ornamentation – some as detailed as those of any Hindu temple – show they were highly thought of by the citizenry. Not surprising, given the scarcity of clean water in the area. Alas, the British overseers of the Raj found the hygiene of the wells less than desirable, and so installed pumps and pipes to replace the stepwells in their holdings. Far less picturesque, but certainly more efficient.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_ZIGGURAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When the Egyptians were building pyramids along the Nile, the Akkadians, Sumerians, Elamites, Babylonians and Assyrians were building ziggurats all over Mesopotamia. These were terraced pyramids, sometimes truncated so a temple could be placed on top. The earliest date from the Early Dynastic Period, roughly 2900 to 2400 BC, and the newest found date to c. 600 BC. Sun-baked bricks made up the center, and were faced with fire-glazed bricks that were more durable. Unlike the Egyptian pyramids, the ziggurats were generally solid, with shrines and temples on the summit, occasionally more than one (since one didn’t want to offend any god). Sadly none of the shrines or temples have survived – thanks to war, earthquakes and religious fervor – although the great piles of brick have. There were a number of “great” ziggurats, including the one in Babylon dedicated to the god Marduk which may have inspired the fable of the Tower of Babel.</Text>
		</Row>
	</BaseGameText>
</GameData>