<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<BaseGameText>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_INTRO_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
      <Text>Advancing technology makes a civilization stronger, bigger, smarter, and a formidable opponent. It is critically important for a civilization to keep up technologically with its neighbors. While it is possible for a unenlightened civilization to overcome their more advanced neighbor, there are only a few examples of such events occurring in history –so too is this the case in Civilization VI.</Text>
    </Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ADVANCED_BALLISTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once humans started shooting off rockets, the need for a new understanding of ballistics became clear. The flight of rockets, jets, missiles, spacecraft and such simply couldn’t be covered by the current knowledge of internal, transition, external and terminal ballistics that had been accumulated by engineers to that time. When Goddard and von Braun began lighting up the heavens, something more than a gyroscope was required to get the missile to impact where desired. And issues such as escape velocity and orbital reentry began to be of some importance, especially to future cosmonauts and astronauts. Meanwhile, jet aircraft capable of flying at Mach at altitudes of 10-15,000 meters (33-49,000 feet) changed the dynamics of flight into that of ballistics.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ADVANCED_BALLISTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Although Newtonian mechanics still applied, ballistics for rockets and missiles became so complex that mathematicians had to derive second-order differential equations to calculate the plot, compute the drag, and estimate the arrival on target. Even gravity had to be taken into account. Then add in launching missiles and rockets from fast-moving aircraft in aft-crossing trajectory and only computers could possibly make sense of it all.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ADVANCED_BALLISTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Those looking to fire things into orbit and beyond were forced to create a whole new field: astrodynamics, a combination of ballistics and celestial mechanics. If one wanted to land a man on the Moon (and bring him back to Earth alive), mere ballistics wasn’t good enough. Trying to get two moving objects together safely was so complex that NASA’s Apollo Guidance Computer was developed, an on-board microcomputer with which the astronauts could communicate via the DSKY keypad for near-instantaneous ballistic calculations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ADVANCED_BALLISTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>The application of ballistics has become so advanced that mere men can no longer deal with it.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ADVANCED_FLIGHT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As the Second World War progressed, a new form of aircraft made its appearance, pioneered by the Germans but with the Americans and British not far behind. From the very beginning of powered flight, various forward thinkers proposed a jet propulsion system; in 1910 AD, the Romanian Henri Coandă even patented a crude one. Meanwhile, the Germans were experimenting with rockets strapped to airplanes, and in 1929 the first purpose-built rocket plane flew. As the war loomed, various inventors and engineers scrambled to create a true, and affordable, jet fighter.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ADVANCED_FLIGHT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The first flight of a jet aircraft was made by the Italian Caproni Campini N.1 prototype in August 1940. The Germans had kept their own work, the Messerschmitt Me-262, under wraps. Although successfully test flown as early as 1941, mass production didn’t start until mid-1944 when several Luftwaffe jet squadrons took to the skies against the Allied bombers. The first jet fighter to see combat, its appearance was too late to affect the war significantly, but Me-262s did shot down 542 enemy planes. And the reconstituted Czech air force kept them in service until 1951.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ADVANCED_FLIGHT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Meanwhile about the same time in 1944 the British rolled out their turbojet Gloster Meteor, the only operational Allied jet aircraft of the war, to combat the scourge of the V-1 flying bombs. After the war, it was America that took the lead in advanced flight, pioneering swept-wing fighters such as the F-86 Sabre, F-4 Phantom and the Grumman F-14A Tomcat (made a Hollywood star in “Top Gun”). The U.S. Air Force brought the B-45 Tornado, the world’s first jet bomber, into service in 1948. Soon both superpowers had lots of bomb-laden jets on standby as the Cold War occasionally warmed up.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ADVANCED_FLIGHT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>But those who looked to make a killing in post-war airline travel were not idle either. BOAC opened the first commercial jet service – London to Johannesburg – in 1952. But a series of crashes involving the de Havilland Comet jetliner gave Boeing the time to roll out its 707, which entered service in 1958 and soon dominated the market for commercial jets. Thus was born the “jet set.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ANIMAL_HUSBANDRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The domestication of animals and the selective breeding of some to accentuate certain traits (husbandry) appears to have occurred around the same time as the development of agriculture. The dog is thought to be the earliest domesticated animal, probably to assist in hunting game and protect the camp. (They also improved sanitation by eating all the scraps being tossed around the fire pit.) Evidence suggests that dogs were first tamed and bred in China – in fact, geneticists believe that about 95% of the breeds today are descended from just a few common Chinese ancestors.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ANIMAL_HUSBANDRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Meanwhile, goats and sheep were domesticated in the Middle East by about 10,000 BC. Next, men domesticated cattle, probably in the Middle East also according to geneticists. Then, around 4000 BC, horses on the Eurasian steppes. And then followed many of the rest of earth's creatures. In time, most of the domesticated animals became so tame that they could not survive on their own in the wild. Those that couldn’t be domesticated got hunted, by men on horseback … with dogs.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ANIMAL_HUSBANDRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>To be successfully domesticated, according to Charles Darwin, a type of animal must fit certain criteria. It should be able to consume food that is less attractive to humans (grass or vermin or leftovers). It should mature rapidly, so that it becomes useful quickly and so that it can be husbanded through repeated generations of breeding. The animal should have a pleasant disposition (doesn’t bite the hand that feeds it). It shouldn’t panic easily … or if it does, it should tend to stay together with others of its kind, making it possible for humans or dogs to protect the herd. Finally, it is useful if the animal can be trained or tricked to think of a human as its pack or herd leader.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ARCHERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Archery is the method by which a person uses the spring power stored in a bent stick to shoot a slender pointed projectile a great distance at rapid speed. A very useful technology, whether employed against game animals or against other human beings. Now it’s considered just recreation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ARCHERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The earliest use of the bow is lost in the mists of time, but dates from the Paleolithic era (which ended around ten thousand BC), although archaeologists have found stone points in Africa dating 60,000 years ago that may have been arrowheads. Virtually every early civilization employed bows and arrows. It is known that the bow was used in warfare in pre-dynastic Egypt; several successful Classical civilizations – Assyrians, Persians, Parthians, Indians, Koreans, Chinese and Japanese – fielded large contingents of archers in their armies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ARCHERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The technology of archery continued to advance. The composite bow, a laminate of wood and horn, spread outward from Asia to Arabia, North Africa and even Europe. The English longbow, so useful for poaching the King’s deer, proved itself in battle first at Sluys and Crécy, before eventually slaughtering the flower of French chivalry at Agincourt. Shortly thereafter the recurve bow, with its slightly outward bend at the end of the arms, provided greater power and range without increasing the draw weight. The complicated compound bow added wheels and pulleys to heighten the power even more. And then there was the crossbow – so simple and undemanding any peasant could use it effectively – developed by the Chinese during their Warring States period and in a few centuries adopted across Europe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ARCHERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>The coming of the crossbow, and even more so firearms, saw the decline of archery, both in hunting and especially in war. Why spend years training an archer to be deadly, when it takes just a few weeks to teach someone to use a musket effectively?</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ASTROLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Now considered a “pseudoscience,” astrology is based on the premise that there is some sort of relationship between celestial objects and phenomena and events on this small ball of earth. Constellations, the moon, comets, the sun and planets (those that could be seen from Earth) were associated with gods, and it was believed that these thus had an impact on the physical universe. A certain planet or cluster of stars might appear each year around harvest time, and eventually men decided that that planet governed the harvest. Perhaps if one sacrificed a goat on the day that the planet first appeared, it would bless the upcoming harvest.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ASTROLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Most primitive civilizations attached great significance to this nonsense, and that spurred a number of advances. The Indians, Chinese and Mayans developed elaborate calendars to track celestial events. The standing stones of Stonehenge may have been erected for astrological purposes. The mixing of Hellenic astrology with Babylonian astronomy gave rise to many mathematical principles. Chinese astrology flourished during the Han dynasty, and gave birth to several traditional cultural markers: the yin-yang dichotomy, the five elements, Confucian philosophy, Chinese theories of medicine.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ASTROLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>During the so-called Scientific Revolution astrology shed much of its religious and mystical trappings, morphing into astronomy. In 1543 AD Nicolai Copernicus published 'De Revolutionibus orbium coelestium,' which postulated that the sun was the center of the universe, not the Earth, and that the planets orbited the sun, and the moon orbited the Earth. If all these heavenly bodies didn’t circle our planet, why should they affect our lives? During the Enlightenment, the last vestiges of support for astrology fell away, with leading thinkers declaring it to be puerile and infantile. Leaving only the old ladies casting horoscopes and the occasional New Age resurgence to keep astrology afloat in modern times.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ASTRONOMY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If one stares into the night sky long enough, one discovers astronomy (or if none too bright, astrology – but that’s another topic). Up to the Renaissance, astronomy as the study of objects in space was neither a science nor particularly studious; until, that is, Nicholas Copernicus published his heliocentric theory of the solar system in 1543 AD. His work was defended, corrected and expanded by Galileo Galilei using that new wonder, the telescope. A key figure in the “Scientific Revolution,” Johannes Kepler next devised a mathematical system that detailed the motions of the planets; a few decades later, Newton worked out the mechanics with his development of celestial dynamics and the laws of gravitation, using the reflecting telescope he invented.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ASTRONOMY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Significant advances in astronomy have usually come with the introduction of new technology; it helps to be able to see things larger, farther away or in other spectrums when studying infinity. Better and better telescopes allowed William Herschel to create a detailed catalogue of nebulas and clusters, and to “discover” the planet Uranus in 1781. The German Friedrich Bessel managed to measure the distance to a star (61 Cygni) in 1838 for the first time. The spectroscope and photography thrust astronomical knowledge ahead, notably when scientists realized that other stars were similar to the sun in composition – just with a wide range of masses, temperatures and sizes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ASTRONOMY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>But it wasn’t until the early 20th Century that astronomers finally realized that our system was part of a galaxy, the “Milky Way,” and that there were lots of other galaxies floating about. And in between these galaxies were all sorts of exotic things – quasars, pulsars, blazers, radio galaxies, black holes, neutron stars, and such – discovered with esoteric types of telescopes, and even some that orbit the Earth in space where all that man-made pollution doesn’t interfere with studiously observing the night sky.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_BALLISTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The mechanics of throwing things have been known for quite awhile; primitive cultures are quite adept at throwing things. The science of those mechanics is known as “ballistics.” The first ballistic weapons were sticks, stones and spears. Then bows get invented around 10 thousand years ago; then gunpowder and the study of the mechanics of launching things gets rather complicated. The motion, behavior and effects of bullets, shells, bombs, rockets and the like became of great interest to military and law enforcement forces throughout civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_BALLISTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As cannon became common in warfare, military engineers began to study the combination of factors (ranging from elevation to windage) that might affect the path of a cannon ball on its way to flatten a wall or a human being. They soon divided that study into four subfields: internal ballistics concerned with the initial acceleration, transition ballistics for the shift to unpowered flight, external ballistics which focused on trajectory, and terminal ballistics for the effects when the flight ends (hopefully as planned). Their findings and the advances that resulted helped the military improve not only its weapons, but understanding all sorts of other aspects of warfare (such as the study of “military wound ballistics”). Better bullets, better bombs, better shells.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_BALLISTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The study of military wound ballistics soon crept into the civilian realm. Colonel Calvin Hooker Goddard – army officer, physician, researcher, and forensic scientist – is generally credited with founding the field of forensic ballistics in the 1920s. He pioneered the use of the comparison microscope to study bullets from crime scenes. He established, not without opposition, the world’s first Bureau of Forensic Ballistics in New York City; so successful was it in solving crimes and prosecuting criminals that Hoover encouraged his FBI offices to take up the practice. These days, that’s all the average person ensconced in front of the television knows about ballistics.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_BANKING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Although there had been “banks” before – Hammurabi even set down laws governing banking in his famous Code – mostly these were private individuals that made loans, with various unsavory methods to insure repayment. With the fall of Rome in the West and the fall of money lending, Banks did not reappear in Europe until the Middle Ages, rediscovered by rulers looking for ways to fund their bloody and expensive Crusades. Benches were used by Jewish Florentine money-lenders as temporary exchange tables, and hence the term “bank.” Until laws were passed against usury, such as that of Edward I of England in 1275 AD (who used it as an excuse to seize the wealth of hundreds of executed Jews), it was not unknown for such loans to carry 24% or even 48% interest.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_BANKING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>During the 14th Century, avaricious and clever individuals in families such as the Bardi, de Medici, Peruzzi, Gondi and others established permanent banks in their home cities of Florence, Genoa, Venice, Siena, Rome and elsewhere across Italy. The oldest bank still open is the Monte dei Paschi in Siena, operating continuously since 1472. Soon enough the ruling princes got into the act; in 1407 the first state-chartered bank, the Bank of St. George, was founded by the Doge of Genoa (it ceased operations in 1805 after Napoleon’s invasion).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_BANKING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Meanwhile, by the time of the Song dynasty in China the two types of traditional financial institutions – the piaohao (nationwide) and the qianzhuang (local) – were in operation, facilitated by the creation of China’s first paper money in 1024 AD by the state of Sichuan. Although Chinese banks tended to focus on commercial banking based on personal relationships, all the major banking functions found in Europe had arisen independently there as well: deposits, loans, issuing notes, currency exchange, and money transfers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_BANKING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>The arrival of the telegraph and electricity allowed international banking on a grand scale, pioneered by the Rothschilds. Today, banks generally perform the same functions that they did during the Renaissance. And still make a comfortable profit (not to use the term “usury”) doing so.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_BRONZE_WORKING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The English word “bronze” was liberated from the French term bronze, which had been borrowed from the Italian bronzo, evolved from the Medieval Latin bronzium, adapted from either the Greek brontesion or Persian biranj. Whatever one calls it, bronze is a simple alloy of copper and usually tin, occasionally with traces of other metals for strength, luster, or ductility. Bronze “working” allowed men to create all sorts of useful things (like pans and swords) that were both durable and decorative.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_BRONZE_WORKING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The earliest bronze artifacts – actually, arsenic bronze, alloys of metallic arsenic rather than tin – found by archaeologists in Iranian tombs date back to the fifth millennium BC. Tin-bronze was eventually found to be superior to arsenic-bronze … and the fumes of the alloying process didn’t kill the bronze worker, so that was a plus. The oldest (c. 4500 BC) tin-bronze items have been found in a Vinca site in Serbia, and other early examples include odd bits found in China and Mesopotamia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_BRONZE_WORKING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Deposits of copper and tin rarely occur near each other, and thus the export of tin from readily accessible surface mines became a major economic factor in some places; in Europe tin from ore deposits in Cornwall have been found as far afield as Phoenicia in the eastern Mediterranean. Besides being useful, bronze was also considered valuable, enough to give its moniker to an entire age of civilization. In Europe, extensive hordes of bronze tools have been found buried near ruins of treasuries, and in China ritual bronzes dating from 1650 BC have been found as grave goods in the tombs of royalty and nobility.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_BRONZE_WORKING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Although bronze is harder and can hold a sharp edge longer than iron, it is also harder to find and pound into something useful. Thus, the Bronze Age gave way to the Iron Age.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CARTOGRAPHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>There is a fair amount of scholarly debate about how long the “science” of making maps has been around, since there’s a fair amount of debate about what constitutes a map. The oldest “map” to have been discovered is a depiction of what may be local terrain features about Catal Huyuk in Anatolia, dated to the 7th millennium BC. But the first ink splatters that are definitely a map is the “House of the Admiral” wall painting dating to the Minoan civilization c. 1600 BC. Around the 4th Century BC, the Greeks and the Romans were making somewhat more portable maps. And Ptolemy produced his famous treatise on cartography, 'Geographia,' in the 2nd Century AD.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CARTOGRAPHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In ancient China, maps have been found dating back to the Qin dynasty, while cartography in ancient India seems to have been limited mostly to star charts of more use to priests than to travelers. During the Dark Ages, most Europeans barely knew what was around the next bend in the river, much less over the horizon. But the Arabs were producing marvelous atlases such as Muhammed al-Idrisi’s Tabula Rogeriana in 1154 showing what was known of Africa, the Middle East, the Mediterranean, the Indian Ocean and even the Far East. His work remained the most accurate and far-reaching map collection for three centuries.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CARTOGRAPHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Until the Age of Exploration kicked off in the 1400s, Portuguese, Spanish, English, Dutch and French explorers and adventurers brought back crude sketches of coastlines and islands, and European cartographers started making innovative maps for those looking to plunder distant shores. In 1492 the German Martin Behaim made the first known globe of the earth; in 1527 the Portuguese map-maker Diego Ribero made one with an equator. And where they didn’t know what was there, these artists filled the empty spaces with sea monsters, mermaids, and all sorts of mythical and mythological creatures. So, if not as accurate, at least the maps were a lot more entertaining than those staid computer-generated ones created from satellite imaging, remote sensing and aerial photography these days.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CASTLES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Great piles of stone – some still intact (more or less) – dominate the varied landscapes of Europe, castles dating back to the early 10th Century AD when feudal lords sought to insure their power and influence. Some were little more than cold, dirty square stone boxes; others were fairy structures with tall towers, crenelated parapets and flying buttresses. But rather than the romantic visions of noble knights, damsels in distress, great feasts and throwing the barbarians back from the moat, castles served the ultimate utilitarian role in feudal society – imposing the lord’s will on the land.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CASTLES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>According to archeologists, the accumulation of surplus wealth and resources led to the need for defensive structures, and the earliest fortifications evolved in the Fertile Crescent, Indus Valley, Egypt and China to keep the barbarians out of the larder. Europe was rather slower to develop such fortresses, and it was not until the Bronze Age that hill forts began to be built. Soon after the collapse of the Pax Romana, Germanic tribes began to construct heavy stone fortifications. The incursions of the Magyars, Vikings and Muslims brought more castle-building, and the breakdown of the Carolingian Empire led to the privatization of local government as local lords assumed the “privilege” of protecting the people. The success of William the Conqueror set off a lengthy period of warfare and conquest by contending kings, dominated by castle building throughout western civilization … until gunpowder and cannon showed up in the 1600s.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CASTLES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Just as the thick- and high-walled castles fell out of vogue in Europe, Japan entered its own castle age. Evolving from the wooden stockades of the early daimyo, the first castles were constructed of stone with wooden upper structures. Thus, they tended to burn a lot – especially during the Sengoku (“Warring States”) period. Unlike in Europe, the introduction of gunpowder spurred the building of Japanese castles, and the 16th Century saw a boom in castle-building on a grander scale than ever until the Meiji Restoration and the end of feudalism there.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CELESTIAL_NAVIGATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Celestial navigation (or astronavigation, which sounds more scientific than artistic) is the practice of taking angular measurements between a celestial body (sun, moon, planet or star) and a point on the horizon to determine one’s position on the globe. A very useful skill for early sailors venturing out of sight of land. The altitude of the sun above the horizon at noon when compared with the altitude of other bodies gave, for instance, the latitude of the ship. Similarly, an angular measurement to the star Polaris and a similar measurement to a star near the western or eastern horizon could give a fairly accurate longitudinal position.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CELESTIAL_NAVIGATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Polynesian navigation is probably the best known – not to mention earliest – form of celestial navigation; their “wayfarers” memorized the positions of the heavens at all seasons and could cross thousands of miles of open ocean with little error. In Medieval Europe, celestial navigation was considered one of the seven mechanical arts, and the first mariner’s astrolabe was used in the Mediterranean by Muslim merchants. (Perhaps by design, the astrolabe also allowed Muslim travelers to locate the Qibla and calculate the times for the Salat.) Meanwhile, the use of the magnetic compass spread from China across civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CELESTIAL_NAVIGATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Since navigation by “dead reckoning” could have unfortunate results (like running aground and drowning or getting lost and starving), crossing the open seas using the astrolabe and the compass together reached its peak during the “Age of Discovery.” The first circumnavigation of the Earth utilized these tools, along with Magellan’s innate sense of direction (every great admiral of the period had one).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CELESTIAL_NAVIGATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Eventually, of course, the invention of radio, radar and satellite mapping made the entire process much easier and far safer. But even today, sailors rely on the heavens to keep them on course and off the rocks.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CHEMISTRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As astronomy evolved from astrology, chemistry evolved from another pseudoscience: alchemy. Alchemy spans four millennia and three continents; never underestimate mankind’s ability to believe in the irrational. The roots of Western alchemy can be traced to Hellenic Egypt, where Zosimos of Panopolis claimed that the ancient priests had discovered a way to transmute metals from one to another (such as lead to gold, the “Holy Grail” for alchemists). However, the method and the mix of elements that could bring this about had been lost. Whatever the hair-brained basis, this led hundreds of “scientists” over the centuries to investigate and record the chemical properties of various metals, liquids and compounds.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CHEMISTRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But by the Renaissance, scholars had decided that transmutation – at least in this manner – was a pipe-dream, and began to organize what knowledge the alchemists had stumbled across. The posthumously-published work of Jan van Helmont in 1648 AD was the principle bridge between alchemy and chemistry, and enormously influential on Robert Boyle, an English scientist who published The Skeptical Chymist in 1661, the cornerstone of modern chemistry. Chemistry achieved its dignified status in 1789, when Antoine Lavoisier published a paper describing the law of conservation of mass. In “Elements of Chemistry,” Lavoisier revealed the composition of air and water, coining the term “oxygen.” If Boyle is the godfather, Lavoisier is considered the father of chemistry.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CHEMISTRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>As new equipment became available in the following two centuries, chemistry became an experimental science, with its own theoretical base. In 1803 John Dalton was the first to propose the atomic theory. The “gas laws” soon followed, along with Dmitri Mendeleev’s periodic table and Willard Gibbs’ laws of thermodynamics. In the 1890s the Curies pioneered the study of radioactivity in elements. By the turn of the new century, chemists were inventing all sorts of things – plastic, synthetic fibers, new drugs (some with medicinal properties), improved poisons, better explosives, and much more. Or, as the chemical firm DuPont would have it, “Better living through chemistry.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_COMBINED_ARMS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since the earliest age, able military commanders had integrated formations of infantry, archers and whatever passed for cavalry in battle with more or less success. But it wasn’t until the campaigns of Gustavus Adolphus who fielded 3-pounder cannon in his infantry regiments and attached teams of musketeers to his cavalry units that the concept showed its true worth. As the century progressed, several European nations combined musketeers, light infantry, dragoon and horse artillery into unified brigades. Napoleon revolutionized tactics by employing fast-moving advance detachments composed of light cavalry, light infantry and horse artillery in his Grande Armée.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_COMBINED_ARMS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Despite the descent into trench warfare on the Western Front, the First World War brought two new weapons to the forefront – the tank and the airplane. In the following years before the next big brouhaha, various military thinkers proposed new combined-arms systems for the "all-arms battles” they envisioned. These would include such as close artillery support, air support and tanks and infantry in mutual support during an attack. One of those whose ideas drew some attention was a German officer named Erwin Rommel, whose book 'Gefechts-Aufgaben für Zug and Kompanie' was published in 1934. The successful blitzkrieg in the West and East was carried out with fast-moving armored formations, supported by motorized infantry, self-propelled guns and specialized ground-support aircraft.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_COMBINED_ARMS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>After the successes against the Germans, the superpowers adopted the combined-arms approach as doctrine (never mind the nuclear missiles poised to rain down). The U.S. Marine Corps, for instance, formalized the concept of the independent Marine Air-Ground Task Force in 1963. The Vietnam War and the Soviet-Afghan War brought air-mobile forces and “special forces” to the field, allowing for quick-strike offensives in a range of terrain not suited to conventional combined-arms operations. The Gulf Wars finally gave the world a chance to see the new combined-arms theories put into practice, with impressive results.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_COMBUSTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Although there were internal combustion engines described by engineers before the 19th Century – for instance, a piston-and-cylinder gas-fired engine by Jean Joseph Étienne Lenoir in 1860 AD – until industrial-level drilling for petroleum and methods for refining it into gasoline, they really weren’t much more than a curiosity. And a smelly and noisy one to boot. Even when Siegfried Marcus put a mobile gas-driven engine on a handcart in 1870 Vienna, the potential went unrecognized.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_COMBUSTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But things picked up as designers in various countries began experimenting and developing modifications to the basic internal combustion engine. In 1879 Karl Benz was granted a patent for a two-stroke gas engine; a few years later, he devised a four-stroke engine which he put in his “automobiles,” which he then put into production in 1886. By 1884, English tinkerer Edward Butler had invented the spark plug, ignition magneto, coil ignition and jet carburetor (and coined the term “petrol” to confuse motorists for generations). In 1885, Gottlieb Daimler devised the supercharger so his autos would be faster than Benz’s. A few years later, Rudolf Diesel developed his Carnot heat engine type, better known as the “diesel engine.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_COMBUSTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Meanwhile, some daredevil types were fitting small gas-powered engines onto bicycle frames and tearing about the countryside in Europe. In 1894, the firm Hildebrand &amp; Wolfmüller became the first to begin production of a motorrad (i.e., motorcycle). For true aficionados, Harley-Davidson began production of its bikes in 1903. That same year the Wright brothers put one on a glider and flew. Then Henry Ford figured out how to mass produce internal combustion engines and stick them in cheaply-made, assembly-line Model-Ts, founding the Ford Motor Company in 1908 … and launching a love-affair with excessive speed civilization has yet to outgrow.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_COMPOSITES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A composite is any material made from two or more materials with significantly differing physical or chemical properties; composites are distinct from alloys or chemical compounds (in which the components do not retain their original properties).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_COMPOSITES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The earliest examples of Composites were likely Egyptian bricks, made from straw and mud, which were both durable and cheap. The Romans invented concrete, another composite used in construction. Around 3400 BC the Mesopotamians invented plywood, thin sheets of various woods glued together giving added strength and durability. Barbarians were using composite bows made of wood, bone, horn, and silk to slaughter the civilized; Mongolian composite bows carried their rule across much of the known world in the 14th Century AD. Papier-mâché, a composite of glue and paper, has been used for centuries by artists and other children. More recently, fiberglass was invented in the 1930s.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_COMPOSITES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Modern composites are produced only in laboratories or specialized industrial plants. In 1961, carbon fiber was spun and within a few years the first carbon fiber composites were commercially available. The 1970s and 1980s saw a series of breakthroughs in producing ultra-high molecular weight composites, exceedingly sturdy and resistant to corrosion, soon used in the production of aircraft, boats, automobiles and a lot of household gadgets. By the mid-1990s, the production of composite materials dominated materials manufacturing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_COMPOSITES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>The latest advances in composites include research into hybrid materials and nanocomposites, the creation of new materials on the molecular scale. Hybrid materials are a mix of organic and inorganic components; the intent is to mimic nature’s processes for a variety of benefits – weight, strength, durability, environmental-friendliness, and even healing. (Just imagine when cars can repair themselves.) Research into nanocomposites has just begun, but the potential (at least according to researchers) is great.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_COMPUTERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If one thinks of a computer as a device simply to aid computation, then these have been around for millennia. An abacus, used as early as 2400 BC, is just such as device. (For that matter, so is counting using fingers, but that’s far too simple for modern civilization.) A mechanical astrolabe with a calendar calculator was devised by Abi Bakr in Persia in 1235 AD. The slide rule was invented around 1620. The “differential analyzer,” a mechanical analog calculator, was first proposed by Lord Kelvin in 1876, and by the 1920s Vannevar Bush and others had built such contraptions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_COMPUTERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But most people think of a computer as a device that is programmable to perform and display a wide variety of tasks, something more than a souped-up calculator. The primogenitor of such was built in 1833 – about a century ahead of its time – by the “father of the computer,” the Englishman Charles Babbage. His programmable “mechanical computer” incorporated punched cards, a printer, an arithmetic logic unit, conditional branching and even an integrated memory (of sorts) … all recognizable to any present-day computer geek.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_COMPUTERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>It was the arrival of electricity that spawned the “Computer Age.” The principles of pioneer “computer scientist” (actually, he was a mathematician) Alan Turing were first set out in his 1936 paper “On Computable Numbers.” During the Second World War, various battling nations set about turning his insights into reality, for everything from breaking enemy codes to shooting down enemy aircraft. Most of the engineers used electricity and vacuum tubes rather than mechanical switches, and gave their monstrous machines names such as “ABC,” “Colossus” (the first digital programmable computer), and ENIAC (capable of 5000 additions or subtractions a second) in 1946, the first “Turning-complete” machine.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_COMPUTERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Since then, thanks to the invention of bipolar transistors and integrated circuits and semiconductors, and the efforts of a lot of tinkerers, computers have become ever faster, more compact and oozed into all sorts of human pursuits from research to manufacturing to warfare to entertainment. Thus, HAL 9000 and Skynet.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CONSTRUCTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When the architects and engineers get done mucking about, the contractors take over. Once there was agriculture and a reason to stay in one place, the first huts were constructed by the people who would live in them. As cities grew during the Bronze Age, professional construction workers – just bricklayers and carpenters at first – arose. This new class of skilled workers, including lots of slaves, literally laid the foundations for civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CONSTRUCTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The history of construction is the history of advances in tools, materials and energy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CONSTRUCTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The ancient civilizations built in wood occasionally, but mostly in mud brick and in stone. Although remarkably durable, stone and brick are also quite heavy and inflexible. It's impossible to construct very tall structures out of these materials – unless the structure in question is solid stone or brick and is pyramid-shaped. Otherwise they tend to topple over when given a shake, as with the Pharos of Alexandria. The Greeks built the little things out of brick, but employed marble for the big things like the Parthenon.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CONSTRUCTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>While the Romans didn’t develop any new building materials – if you discount their invention of concrete – they did revolutionize construction in terms of designs and of tools. The arch, the waterwheel, the sawmill, and a host of hand tools come from the Romans, who not only were constructing aqueducts, roads and walls but also some really nice villas and colosseums. Meanwhile, the Chinese and Japanese were working in wood, devising the likes of post and lintel construction and mortise and tenon joints to build their pagodas and palaces.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CONSTRUCTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>The Industrial Revolution brought steel to construction. Strong and durable. Using steel, contractors could create soaring bridges, deep tunnels, towering skyscrapers, and elevated roadways. And new energy sources – electricity, gas-powered engines, arc welding, etc. – made construction a lot easier.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CURRENCY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Currency, where something relatively worthless in itself represents some amount of actual value, has been the bane of civilization since around 2000 BC, when a form of receipt was used to show ownership of stored grain in temples in Sumer. The Egyptians soon adopted the practice for their own grain warehouses, so that individuals could claim a portion they had “banked” therein. Then small bits of rare metals, a lot easier to keep track of than written receipts (especially since these were on clay tablets), came to represent certain amounts of various commodities, able to be exchanged … or hoarded. Thus, wealth was determined by how many of these bits a person had.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CURRENCY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But the collapse of the Mesopotamian and Mediterranean trading economy around 1100 BC revealed a flaw in this concept of circulating currency – it was only as good as the guarantees of worth that backed it. It was only with the recovery of Phoenician trade across the Mediterranean that coinage made a reappearance, this time being backed by rulers of the city-states of Phoenicia and Greece. Most of the major economies of the time were soon minting coins, usually out of gold or silver or copper. Trade flourished, taxes could be paid, banking evolved, and now people could even go into debt (a whole new concept).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_CURRENCY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>It was left to the Chinese to “invent” paper currency, initially in the form of promissory notes from wholesaler’s shops backed by the merchant, but these were only useful in the local region. The Song dynasty began issuing a more universal paper currency based on the state monopoly of salt production. It took until the 13th Century for this paper money to finally become standardized and acceptable across the kingdom. Around the same time, the Islamic nations adopted the practice and established a stable, high-value currency (the dinar). A vibrant and vigorous monetary economy resulted; the Muslims thus were the first to have credit, cheques, savings accounts, trusts, exchange rates, and all the other wonders of a “modern” economy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ECONOMICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Economics is the understanding of “the production, distribution and consumption of goods and services.” This understanding was a lot easier in olden times when things were distributed via barter (“I have a daughter and you have some goats; let’s trade."), but even in the early stages of coinage and mercantile trade notions of production and profits was pretty straightforward. Ancient writers such as Fan Li of China c. 517 BC, Chanakya of India c. 350 BC, and Aristotle of Greece c. 350 BC laid down the precepts of supply-and-demand, monopolies, loans and debts, and state economic policies. During the Middle Ages, Thomas Aquinas and Duns Scotus debated the philosophy of a “fair price” and, until Adam Smith, the Muslim scholar Ibn Khaldun was considered to offer the most insight into economic theory, including “supply-side” economics, the specialization of labor, and the financial life-cycle of civilizations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ECONOMICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But no one save a few befuddled historians remembers those writings. Instead Adam Smith’s studies – notably his monumental The Wealth of Nations (1776) – are considered the foundation of modern economics. In his book, Smith contends that a free market is the most efficient means of assigning worth to and for distributing goods and services. Moreover, when a person pursues his own financial self-interests (i.e., unbounded greed) he automatically is promoting the good of society in general through economic growth and investment. In other words, unbridled capitalism is the best economic basis for civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ECONOMICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>As might be imagined, Smith’s pronouncements were not without critics. David Ricardo argued in 1817 that there was an inherent conflict between the economic interests of landowners on one hand and labor on the other, and was the first to prove the principle of comparative advantage in international trade. The philosopher John Stuart Mill stated that governments would have to intervene in economic affairs because the market’s two roles – allocation of resources and distribution of income – could not otherwise be balanced. But it was Karl Marx with the publication of 'Das Kapital: Kritik der politischen Ökonomie' who really kicked over the proverbial apple cart when he proposed the labor theory of value. Capitalists and communists have been fighting over who is right ever since.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_EDUCATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Humans learn things, and civilization results. Obviously education has been around as long as mankind has. Through most of history, it was an informal affair, parents teaching their children the skills they needed to know to survive and be productive (household chores and hunting expeditions and dodging barbarians and so forth). As a tribe expanded and grew more prosperous, village elders and priests might educate the children while the healthy adults gathered food, built stuff and made war. Eventually a wealthy society might have formal classes for the more important children.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_EDUCATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As the thinkers of a nation-state extended its knowledge beyond the merely practical, into realms where learning by imitation wasn’t possible, schools were established. By the time of the Middle Kingdom, the priesthood in Egypt had established schools to teach reading and writing, mathematics, history, the sciences, medicine, astrology and, of course, religion. In Greece, private academies arose to teach the privileged, such as that established by Plato in Athens, the first institution of “higher” education in Europe. Further east, China’s Confucius began a program of establishing schools to teach his philosophies, as well as some basic skills such as reading and mathematics and music.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_EDUCATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Mostly, the dominant religion took on the task of education. In the cultures of Mesoamerica, teaching was in the hands of the priests, the “educated” class who served as advisors and judges as well as educators; their self-serving coursework in divination and writing and astrology and arithmetic was aimed at creating yet more priests. With the fall of Rome, the Catholic Church became the sole purveyor of “approved learning” across Western Europe. Elsewhere, Islamic schools produced the finest scholars of the age, being somewhat more tolerant of differing views of the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_EDUCATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Soon enough other civilizations too realized the importance of education. The Renaissance saw an explosion of schools and universities, both private and state-sponsored in a new age of discovery and enlightenment. Then came the thought that everyone deserved an education, and now one can get a degree even in basket-weaving or psychology.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ELECTRICITY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mankind has known electricity existed since the first bunch of Neanderthals got blasted by a lightning bolt; in fact, for millennia afterwards, electricity in this form was associated with angry gods. Egyptian texts dating from c. 2750 BC record people getting shocks from electric eels. Around 600 BC Thales of Miletus observed that static electricity could be generated by rubbing rods of amber with cat’s fur (but didn’t investigate what the cats thought of this). Greek, Roman, and Arabic physicians attested to the numbing effects of electric shocks delivered by various animals. Electricity, however, remained nothing more than a scientific curiosity through the 17th Century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ELECTRICITY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In 1600 the British dilettante William Gilbert made a comparative study of magnetism and this little-understood force, for which he coined the term electricus (from the Greek electron meaning “amber,” from which he was generating the static sort), hence “electricity.” The work of others – von Guericke, Boyle, Gray, and du Fay – led history’s ultimate dilettante Benjamin Franklin to “discover” electricity while flying a kite with a key attached in a thunderstorm (don’t try this at home). Franklin never did anything with his discovery, but it set others off searching for more sources of electricity. Luigi Galvani discovered bioelectricity, whereby messages are passed between nerve and muscle cells. Alessandro Volta invented the battery, a more reliable source of electricity than rubbing cats. Ampere discovered electromagnetism; and Michael Faraday built the first electric motor in 1821.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ELECTRICITY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Advances in electricity in the second half of the 19th Century by tinkerers like Nikola Tesla, Thomas Edison, George Westinghouse, Alexander Graham Bell, and Lord Kelvin revolutionized life around the world. The telegraph and telephone made the world smaller. The electric light opened home and workplace to night activity, and the phonograph, radio, and movies were certainly entertaining. Adding electricity to a chair was thought a more humane method of executing miscreants. The creation of power plants that pushed energy in the form of electricity into people’s homes changed civilization beyond comprehension.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ENGINEERING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Engineering is the science (or perhaps “art,” if engineers themselves are involved in the discussion) of using science to design things: buildings, roads and bridges, machines, and other materially useful things. The term is somewhat vague – consider for example, software “engineering.” Originally the term referred only to creating “engines” of war; the Romans applied it to all sorts of public works, since their legions were building roads, bridges and walls all over the empire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ENGINEERING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Soon the term was being attached to the design and construction of all sorts of monumental monuments and wondrous works. And designing machines, such as water screws, pumps, differential gearing, and such. By the time of the Industrial Revolution, engineers were everywhere underfoot, creating steam engines (James Watt) and electrical gadgets (Thomas Edison), and building canals, railroads, bridges, tunnels, dams and skyscrapers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ENGINEERING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Around this time colleges and universities began offering degrees in engineering, such as that awarded by the Rensselaer Institute in the United States in 1835 AD; soon enough there was “higher” education in mechanical, civil, electrical, architectural, military, agricultural, structural, and all sorts of other practical engineering. The first doctorate in engineering was awarded by Yale University to one Josiah Gibbs in 1863 (it was only the second PhD awarded in the young United States at this time.)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ENGINEERING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>So respected did the term “engineering” become among the masses that other pursuits started appropriating it, so that now there’s chemical engineering, software engineering, bioengineering, materials engineering, environmental engineering, aerospace engineering and the like. But it is the harnessing of mathematics and physics to design buildings and machines that remains the true essence of engineering. As some have noted, engineering is applied problem solving (as opposed to pure science), and has brought or dragged) civilization – for good or bad – into the 21st Century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_FLIGHT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since the Renaissance, mankind has learned how to fly … and how to crash too. Leonardo da Vinci's visions of flight are well-known, of course, but he certainly wasn’t the first. From the earliest times there have been legends (some maybe even true) of men strapping on wings or other devices and attempting to fly, usually by jumping off something tall (most ended badly). In the Middle Ages, for instance, Armen Firman strapped wings with vulture feathers to himself and jumped off a tower in Cordoba during 852 AD. In China, man-carrying kites were the method of choice. But it wasn’t until 1783 when the Montgolfier brothers launched a manned hot-air balloon that man finally took off – and landed safely. Ballooning became all the rage across Europe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_FLIGHT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In 1804 Englishman George Cayley flew a fixed-wing glider model, and in 1853 he created a full-scale model which carried his (reluctant) coachman in the first manned glider flight. Fifty years later two American brothers constructed their own glider with an advanced wing shape onto which they were going to stick a gasoline engine with a “propeller.” Unable to find anyone to construct a light gasoline-powered engine to their specifications, they built their own. On December 17, the Wright flyer flew four times, at distances up to 852 feet. The years following the Wright brothers’ breakthrough saw rapid improvements in the technology of powered flight. In 1908 American Glenn Hammond Curtiss flew over one kilometer, and in 1909 Frenchman Louis Bleriot flew across the English Channel.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_FLIGHT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>World War I saw significant advances in flight technology, especially in the militarization of the air, with the creation of fighters and bombers. By the 1920s pilots were regularly flying across the continents (and crashing into them), and in 1927 Charles Lindberg completed the first nonstop solo flight across the Atlantic Ocean. Seems flying was here to stay.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_FUTURE_TECH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Anything worth saying about “future tech” has already been said by science-fiction authors. There are a few broad things that all of them seem to agree upon. Sooner or later, medical breakthroughs will cure cancer and other diseases, dramatically increase the human lifespan, and hook the human brain up to machines. Cheap, clean forms of energy will be discovered. Computers will get faster and smaller; robots will take over the daily grind. Games will get more immersive and realistic. Nasty weapons will be invented … but not used. Extinct species wiped out by man (or asteroids) will be reborn. Ecologists will end pollution and recover lost ecosystems. Mankind will move beyond the heavens to other worlds. Civilization will be saved.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_FUTURE_TECH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Or, perhaps not …</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_GUIDANCE_SYSTEMS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>With the advent of rocketry, it became rather important not to get lost when launching a nuclear-tipped missile at the enemy or shooting a man into space. A compass and a sextant just wouldn’t serve any longer, not if you wanted to hit your target. So, if going ballistic, a guidance system was needed. And since the computations were too complicated for mere mortals, getting something to arrive where and when intended was turned over to machines.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_GUIDANCE_SYSTEMS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Guidance systems demand three sub-systems: input, processing, and output. Input devices include sensors, course data from radio and satellite links, radar, visual cameras and such. Processing is generally done with both onboard and ground-based central processing units, which determines such things as course, trajectory, velocity, etc. Output is the adjustments made to speed (via fuel pumps, engine operation, cooling systems) and course (ailerons, rudders, weight distribution). Since, in general, the rocket isn’t coming back, these systems can be fairly cheap and simple (save, perhaps for the onboard CPUs).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_GUIDANCE_SYSTEMS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The American Robert Goddard and, separately, the German team developing the V-2 rocket both experimented with simple gyroscopic guidance systems … which sort of worked. After the war, with its collection of some 500 German aerospace scientists led by von Braun, American research on self-contained guidance systems was concentrated at Caltech, MIT and the NASA Jet Propulsion Lab. Their combined efforts led to the unreliable “Delta” system, which assessed the difference in position constantly from a reference trajectory; the problems were overcome with the “Q-system” in 1956 AD. So successful was it for nuclear missiles that the Q-system was classified throughout the 1960s, and is still used for many military weapons.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_GUIDANCE_SYSTEMS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>However, it was the “space race” that brought guidance systems to true efficiency. In August 1961 NASA awarded MIT a contract for the design of a guidance and navigation system for the Apollo program. The result was the ancestor to the PEG4 (“powered explicit guidance”) system used for the American shuttle program and most other space launches. Meanwhile, the global positioning system was being developed in tandem by the U.S. military so they could keep their shiny ICBMs on target. GPS was eventually commercialized, and now helps keep Dad from getting lost on the way to the mall.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_GUNPOWDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The invention of gunpowder is usually attributed to Chinese alchemists during the Tang dynasty, one of the “Four Great Inventions of China.” The earliest written record of it – a formula composed of sulfur, charcoal and potassium nitrate dating to the later Song dynasty – was supposed to be an elixir for immortality … it was anything but. But the Chinese did discover that it burned explosively and the resultant gases expanded rapidly when exposed to heat; so it was useful for making fireworks. The Chinese found a more practical use for gunpowder in crude bombs and rockets which they used against the Mongols … until the Mongols overran China and then used the new weapon against everyone else on their path westward.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_GUNPOWDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>While the Mongols were using gunpowder to intimidate the Europeans they encountered, the Arabs sometime between 1240 and 1280 AD developed better recipes, purer niter, and more deadly weapons – notably cannon and a primitive arquebus. Some historical texts state that the Mamluks used the first cannon in history against the Mongols during the battle at Ain Jalut in 1260, but this is open to debate. The earliest description of a “portable hand cannon,” however, does appear in an Arabic manuscript from the 14th Century. Once they’d turned back the Mongols, the Arabs put these to use elsewhere.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_GUNPOWDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>But it was the Europeans who really took to gunpowder as a means of wholesale slaughter. Not only did they improve the formula and add touches such as “corning” – using liquid to increase granularity and hence stability – and “smokeless” powder, but they created all sorts of toys that used it to hurl small and large bits of lead and iron at people. From the days of the Renaissance, military history in Europe was shaped by gunpowder, as it came to dominate the battlefield like no technology before.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_HORSEBACK_RIDING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>There is archaeological evidence that around 4000 BC humans had used bits on their horses in the basins of the Dnieper and Don rivers; skeletons of horses found in the region shows signs that the horses chomped on bits. Thus, horseback riding. It is thought that the Scythians of the steppes may well have been the first to develop the stirrup and the saddle, although the historical argument is as yet unconvincing. (And ancient Greek historians also claim that the Scythians were the first to geld stallions, hence making them more docile and controllable … but that’s another story.)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_HORSEBACK_RIDING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>However, horses in the Bronze Age were relatively small by modern standards, some argue too small to be ridden comfortably or for any distance and more likely to have pulled wagons or chariots. On the other hand, Fell ponies – descended from Roman cavalry mounts – can easily carry a full-grown adult, and so it is likely that there was cavalry around long before the Greeks and Romans took to the battlefield (although this light cavalry was hardly a dominate factor in victory, mostly being used to slaughter the defeated foot soldiers trying to flee).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_HORSEBACK_RIDING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>By the Middle Ages, however, heavily-armored mounted knights dominated warfare in Europe. And in the Far East, Japanese samurai fought from horseback for centuries, although mostly as archers. Indeed, horseback riding archers were the most common type of cavalry in Central Asia for a millennium. The Arabians, astride their magnificent stallions, spread Islam across the Middle East, North Africa, and into India and Europe. Horseback riding quite literally shaped history.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_HORSEBACK_RIDING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Save in the Americas, where the native horse breeds had died out. Horseback riding was brought back to North America by European explorers and conquistadors, commencing with Columbus’s 1493 voyage. Soon enough, the Plains Indians would be combating the white settlers from horseback.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_INDUSTRIALIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Not many “technologies” (or, in this case a convergence of several technologies) give a label to a revolution and to an era. Industrialization is viewed by scholars as the transition from an agrarian society to an industrial one, which was historically accompanied by widespread social and economic upheaval. It is driven by the invention of new machinery and discovery of new power sources. The Industrial Revolution, beginning in Europe during the 18th century, brought about unforeseen changes in the way people lived their daily lives, both beneficial and detrimental.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_INDUSTRIALIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>With increasingly complex machinery and tools available, trades that were once left to talented craftsmen became obsolete with the advent of assembly lines operated by masses of unskilled factory laborers. New professions evolved. People moved to the cities, where factories and transportation were concentrated.  The process involved the reorganization of the world’s economy from self-sufficiency to one of manufacturing and consumerism. As the wages of workers rose, markets for services and goods expanded, demanding ever more production, resulting in higher prices and wages, and so forth in a tornadic cycle.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_INDUSTRIALIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Industrialization is also marked by urbanization, exploitation (over 40% of the world’s employees are considered to be “working poor” by the United Nations), institutional complexity, rampant consumerism, capitalism and communism, unprecedented population growth, and complex change in every social structure, even the nuclear family. The accumulation of capital permits increased investment in scientific research and new technologies, speeding the process of industrialization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_INDUSTRIALIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Some argue that there was a Second Industrial Revolution, the period during the late 1800s in which the internal combustion engine, electricity, telephony, and innovative factory machines launched a new cycle of urbanization, consumerism and social alienation. There are even some who believe that civilization has entered yet another “Industrial Revolution” – just look at the changes over the past quarter-century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_IRON_WORKING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>While the use of iron has been dated back to 4000 BC, the Hittites were the first to extract the ore, smelt it and fashion weapons – thus setting off the Iron Age around 1200 BC. In Asia, iron working developed at about the same time; iron Chinese artifacts have been unearthed dating back to around 600 BC. From those two places, using iron for weapons and tools spread quickly across the globe, except in the Americas where the natives continued to hit each other with rocks.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_IRON_WORKING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>There were two types of iron working, one producing wrought iron and the other cast iron. Wrought iron is a semi-fused alloy, tough, malleable, corrosion-resistant and able to be welded. It could be beaten into all sorts of shapes, and it was used extensively across Europe during the Middle Ages. Besides armor and weapons and tools, iron work was used to protect doors and windows with grills and bars, and even used as decoration for Canterbury Cathedral, Winchester Cathedral and Notre Dame de Paris. The French even made it into balconies and stair railings.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_IRON_WORKING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>By contrast, cast iron is made by melting the iron ore and pouring it into molds; the Chinese were the first to use it, primarily to make beams and rods to support their elaborate pagodas and other tall buildings. Cast iron also made pretty good arrowheads and cannon shot, as the Chinese soon discovered.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_IRON_WORKING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>In the West, cast iron working did not take hold until around the 15th Century AD, the technique apparently moving along the Silk Road from Asia to Europe. The Europeans too found cast iron perfect for making cannon barrels and cannon balls, musket barrels and musket balls. During the Industrial Revolution structural engineers found some more creative uses for cast iron, using it to construct cast-iron bridges and as framing for ever taller buildings.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_IRRIGATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Irrigation has been a central feature of agriculture for over 5000 years, and forms the basis for the economy and culture of many civilizations throughout history. Perennial irrigation was first practiced in Mesopotamia with water flowing through small channels connecting to a river or a small lake. In Egypt, several pharaohs during the Twelfth Dynasty used oases to store water for irrigation during the dry season. Ancient Nubians devised a waterwheel device to bring water to their fields around the second millennium BC. Terrace irrigation evolved in pre-Columbian America, in Syria, China and India.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_IRRIGATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The first hydraulic engineers recorded in history were Sunshu Ao (6th Century BC) and Ximen Bao (5th Century BC) of China who both worked on extensive irrigation projects for the emperor (whoever that happened to be at the time) in the Sichuan region; with waters from the “four circuits of rivers” lifted into and moved through channels by chain pumps powered by humans or oxen, it was a marvel of ancient engineering.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_IRRIGATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Although it is not known precisely how the famed Hanging Gardens were irrigated, they may well have used the noria, invented around this time. The noria is a wheel with buckets or pots along its circumference. As the wheel rotated – driven by flowing water – the upper buckets emptied by gravity into a trough or channel. The wheel, turning, returned the empty buckets to be refilled. Pretty clever, since it didn’t depend on muscle power.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_IRRIGATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>It would be a thousand years before the next advance in irrigation: the windmill, designed to pump water upward into pipes or ditches to water the fields; the technology spread across Europe, allowing for population growth not seen before. That led to more irrigation. It is estimated that there are approximately 600 million acres being irrigated worldwide now.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_LASERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term “laser” is an acronym for “light amplification by stimulated emission of radiation,” which pretty much describes what it happens to be. The theory dates back to a paper by Albert Einstein in 1917 which offered a derivation of Planck’s Law concerning stimulated emission of electromagnetic radiation. In 1928, the atomic physicist Rudolf Ladenburg confirmed the phenomena of stimulated emission and negative absorption.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_LASERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>By the time of the first true laser, American and Soviet Russian scientists had built masers, amplifying microwave radiation rather than light radiation. So it wasn’t long before various others were attempting to build “optical masers,” as commonly termed (“laser” was coined in 1959). The first functional laser was demonstrated in May 1960 when the Hughes Research Laboratories introduced laser technology capable of storing data on optical devices. Later that same year, the Iranian Ali Javan headed an international team that produced the first gas laser, utilizing helium and neon, capable of continuous operation in the infrared spectrum.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_LASERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Since this early laser research many kinds of specialized lasers have been developed, ones optimized for different maximum firing ranges, output power, or utilizing different wavelengths. Chemical lasers, excimer lasers, dry lasers, solid state and fiber lasers, semiconductor lasers and free-electron lasers. So many kinds, with so many different purposes. Lasers have found their way into thousands of uses, from consumer electronics and entertainment to law enforcement and military use.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_LASERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Perhaps the most advanced uses of lasers are in the fields of medicine and the military. In the former lasers offer “bloodless” surgery, removal of tumors and diseased organs, diagnostic tools unknown a decade ago, and photobiomodulation (i.e., laser therapy). And for the military nothing beats a laser for targeting and weapons guidance, although its potential as a directed-energy weapon has yet to be realized (despite research in the billions of dollars thus far). Industrial and home use (the oft-touted holography isn’t quite here yet) is expanding continuously. Just don’t look directly into the light from one.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MACHINERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When humans began to develop tasks that they or their animals could not (or would not) do, they invented machines. From those first simple machines – the lever, pulley and screw – that Archimedes went on about, a machine civilization has evolved on Earth. Later Greek thinkers added the wedge and the wheel/axle to the list of the five simple machines (these form the basis for every other machine that aids physical work). Heron of Alexandria in his work Mechanica (c. 50 AD) described their fabrication and uses. But the Greeks, while they understood statics and friction, had no understanding of dynamics.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MACHINERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Thus, during the supposedly “Dark” Ages, men in various parts of the world began to devise machinery in which a tradeoff between distance and force was the principle behind producing mechanical energy. The complete dynamic theory of simple machines (the above plus some later ones) was worked out by Galileo Galilei and published in his Le Meccaniche in 1600; his was the first – or the first to publish anyway – insight that machines did not create useful energy but merely transformed it from one type to another.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MACHINERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The Renaissance witnessed tinkers on the order of da Vinci, di Giorgio Martini and Gutenberg invent everything from pile drivers to centrifugal pumps, from cranes to the printing press. It was an explosion of machines, to be followed a couple hundred years later by another explosion of machines during the Industrial Age. Machines invaded the mills and factories, but it was one revolutionary device – the steam engine – that profoundly altered civilization’s notion of what a machine was and what it could do.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MACHINERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>From that new type of machine sprang a thousand more, including the internal combustion engine, the electric generator, and the diesel motor. Now the world even has “machines” without moving parts … witness, the computer.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MASONRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Masonry: the “art” of construction of something, sometimes utilitarian (houses) or not (temples and palaces), from blocks of stone, brick or even concrete usually held together with mortar (if not, it’s termed “dry set” masonry).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MASONRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The ancient Egyptians mastered the art of masonry as early as the fourth millennium BC, constructing temples, palaces, pyramids and other edifices from limestone, sandstone, granite and basalt found in the hills of the Nile River. The Assyrians of the Fertile Crescent lacked easy access to stone but possessed rich deposits of clay, which they sun-dried into bricks. The Babylonians too used brick, held together with mortar made of lime and pitch. The Harappa city in now-Pakistan was built around 2600 BC with bricks and gypsum mortar (now called “plaster of Paris”).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MASONRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The Romans invented concrete, a superior mortar for all that stone and marble building they did … and which could be used as a construction material itself. This “concrete revolution” allowed them to build monumental structures that were impossible using more primitive materials. From 300 BC to the fall of Rome, concrete paved roads, lined aqueducts, and held the Colosseum together (among other things). But the masonry skills were lost during the Dark Ages (as was so much else) until the 1300s, when Europeans again began using concrete as mortar for their castles.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MASONRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>So endemic did the use of concrete become, the term “mason” evolved to include those who worked with concrete (along with the secretive members of a fraternal organization). To distinguish themselves as artisans, those who work with “real” stone took to calling themselves “stonemasons.” Although they occasionally labor on the building of modern monuments and memorials in capitals around the world, mostly they just carve tombstones these days.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MASS_PRODUCTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Until the Industrial Revolution, the idea of “mass production” was limited to pottery (molds), Chinese crossbows with interchangeable parts, and assembly line production of books. But in the Renaissance, Venice began mass producing ships to maintain their grip on the Mediterranean in their famed Arsenal, using prefabricated parts and assembly lines that would not be matched for output for three centuries. At its peak of efficiency, the Arsenal could produce a sea-worthy ship in a day and employed some ten thousand workers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MASS_PRODUCTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Meanwhile, the printing press gave rise to another kind of mass production, standardized texts produced cheaply for the masses. Although the products of movable type printing were not as elegant nor as durable as hand-copied tomes, they were inexpensive and firmly established the idea of uniform quality (whatever the level) in the midst of quantity. Meanwhile, molds were being used to create ceramic and metal products in large numbers that were identical, and mills staffed by hundreds of spinners and weavers were churning out standardized woolen garments in England and France.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MASS_PRODUCTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The Industrial Revolution brought mass production to just about everything, even things that hadn’t been invented when it started in the early 1800s.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MASS_PRODUCTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>In 1914 AD Henry Ford realized that by making a conveyor line on which automobiles moved and giving each worker on the line a series of specialized tasks they alone would do, he could make cars cheaply and more efficiently. The time it took to turn out a Model T in the factory went from 728 minutes to 98 minutes; this time was eventually to drop to one Model T every 24 minutes. Where once folks were thrilled to pay extra for mass-produced goods of uniform quality, now hand-crafted things are more highly valued. That’s progress …</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MATHEMATICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term “mathematics” is derived from the Greek mathema, meaning “knowledge, study, or learning.” Appropriate, given that it is the science of science, focused on quantity, measurement, structure, logic and change. Mathematics, according to some, is also the art of art, focused on space, shape, relationship, perspective, and fractals. Not to mention mathematics relationship to music.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MATHEMATICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Whether art or science, virtually everything today is based or derived from mathematics. Mathematics has been around since some relatively intelligent human ancestor figured out that having four bananas was better than having two bananas – and clubbed his neighbor to get them. The Sumerians had a complex arithmetic (the manipulation of numbers), which was both “base-ten” (the modern system) and “base-sixty” as well. The remnants of that base-60 system survived in time-keeping: 60 second in a minute, sixty minutes in an hour.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MATHEMATICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The Egyptians, needing to keep track of all the taxes and trade, not to mention designing massive pyramids and monuments, developed a written system of numerals during the Middle Kingdom period. Between 600 and 300 BC, the Greeks began a systematic study of mathematics, dividing it into two spheres: arithmetic and geometry (the understanding of shapes and area). More importantly, they divorced mathematics from reality and began the study of it in the abstract, evolving the concepts of proofs and theorems, leading to the likes of the Pythagorean Theorem and irrational numbers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MATHEMATICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Mathematics continued to evolve to bedevil students over the following centuries. Muslim mathematicians developed algebra. In India, the Kerala School of astronomy and mathematics discovered infinite series and trigonometric functions. And the Indians invented “zero,” not just to fill an empty space in the calculations as the Egyptians did, but as an actual value around 600 AD. From that point mathematics as a discipline has grown (as one might say) geometrically ever since …</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_METAL_CASTING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Metal casting is the process by which a craftsman can make multiple, identical metal objects by pouring molten metal into a mold. The oldest such yet found is a copper frog cast in Mesopotamia around 3200 BC. The first production of cast iron was in China between 800 and 700 BC; using sand mold casting, the Chinese were making cast iron plowshares by 233 BC. Cast iron was also handy for making a lot of arrowheads, spearheads and cannon balls, as the Chinese soon discovered. But mostly the ancients used metal casting to make jewelry.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_METAL_CASTING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>One of the oldest methods of making a mold is the “lost wax” procedure, which dates back at least to the third millennium BC. In this process, the craftsman creates a wax duplicate of the object around which is built the mold, usually of clay (one needs something that the hot metal won’t melt); the wax is then melted and flows out of the mold and is replaced by molten metal. Historically, sand and clay have been popular materials from which to construct molds. In modern times molds have been constructed out of plastics and latex-like substances.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_METAL_CASTING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In the West, cast iron did not take hold until around the 15th Century AD, the technique apparently moving along the Silk Road from Asia to Europe. In 1455 the Germans are using cast iron pipe to carry water in the Dillenburg Castle, and around 1500 the Italian Vannoccio Biringuccio builds the first cast iron foundry.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_METAL_CASTING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>In 1799s England metal casting – especially with iron and later steel – became common. In 1709 Abraham Darby established a foundry using sand-and-loam molds to produce high quality pig iron. Fifty years later, another Englishman, Benjamin Huntsman, reinvented the process to cast crucible steel. Fifty years after that A.G. Eckhardt of Soho developed centrifugal casting to make thin-walled metal cylinders. Engineers kept coming up with new metal casting methods, until now just everything is made of metal – what isn’t made out of plastic, that is.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_APPRENTICESHIP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Traditionally, an apprenticeship is some method of instructing a new generation of “masters” in a craft, art, or trade … using hands-on training, leavened with lots of beatings. (The latter, not so much anymore.) During this period of training, the apprentice studies with an employer in exchange for his/her labor for an agreed time – typically, three to six years – until he/she has achieved a level of measurable competence. All this under the auspices of a guild or trade union. Those who complete their apprenticeship successfully become journeymen, and if diligent, masters themselves so they can instruct a new generation of apprentices. Thus, the trade or craft develops a self-sustaining core of practitioners.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_APPRENTICESHIP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The whole system evolved during the late Middle Ages, when a master craftsman was given the right in many town and city charters to employ young people in exchange for lodging, food, a little spending money, and formal training. In effect, the apprentice was bound body and soul to the master for the length of the apprenticeship. But it was better than most other choices for poor and illiterate youngsters looking to get ahead. In most of Europe, once an apprentice became a journeyman (if he/she did), they were considered a freeman with all the rights of any citizen. If they became masters, they were respected and respectable members of society.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_APPRENTICESHIP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Most apprentices during the medieval and renaissance periods were male, but female apprentices could be found in a few places learning to be seamstresses, tailors, cordwainers, or stationers. Civilization is built upon a constantly renewed skilled labor force, of course; whereas through much of history these skills were passed down in families, the population and technological explosion that began in the 1400s demanded an expanding force. And the guild-apprentice system worked very well. In time government regulations disbanded the guilds and the rise of vocational schools gave young workers other options; nevertheless, vestiges of the apprenticeship system remain, especially in the building trades.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MILITARY_ENGINEERING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Loosely defined as “the art and practice of designing and building military works and maintaining lines of military transport and communications,” military engineering dates back to the Roman legions, which each had a small, specialized corps devoted to overseeing the building of fortifications and roads. They were also the ones to build the catapults, battering rams and siege towers when needed to stamp out some unruly town. But for over five centuries after the fall of Rome in the west military engineering barely progressed; it wasn’t until late in the Middle Ages that the need for siege warfare again spurred the advance of military engineering.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MILITARY_ENGINEERING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>With the development of gunpowder, military engineers became vital, both in designing fortifications to withstand cannon (one of the first innovations: earthen walls worked better than stone ones, since the cannonballs just went thunk and sank into the dirt) and devising ways to get the cannon close enough to the fortifications to be effective. Military engineers became specialized. Sappers, for instance, first appeared in the French army; their task was to excavate zig-zag trenches towards the enemy walls to protect infantry and artillery, all while under musket and cannon fire. In the British army, miners tunneled under enemy walls to place explosive charges … not a long-term career.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MILITARY_ENGINEERING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Meanwhile Renaissance engineers were devising new types of forts and weapons; even da Vinci got into the act with his flights of military fancy. More practical engineers, such as French Marshal Sébastien Le Prestre de Vauban (1633-1707), developed new types of forts and new tactics to use against them during the wars of Louis XIV. During the brief times of peace, military engineers turned their attentions to fortifying the borders and building and maintaining roads and bridges to facilitate the movement of troops. With the coming of the telegraph in the 1800s, they also got stuck with maintaining the lines of communication and command. By the time of the First World War, military engineers were indispensable in modern warfare.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MILITARY_SCIENCE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Military Science is the study of the theory and application of “organized coercive force,” both friendly and enemy. Until the end of the Second World War, when the arrival of atomic weapons made a lot of its assumptions baseless, the term was always written starting with capital letters in English and was considered an academic discipline on par with physics, philosophy and political science. However, as Clausewitz observed, “unlike in any other science or art, in war the object reacts.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MILITARY_SCIENCE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Although there had been earlier generals and writers such as Sun Tzu, Aeneas Tacticus, Miyamoto Musashi, Niccolò Machiavelli, and others who had focused on using military power to efficiently achieve a civilization’s political goals – whether that be defending the homeland or beating up one’s neighbors – it was Carl von Clausewitz, Ardant du Picq, Alfred Thayer Mahan and Helmuth von Moltke (the Elder) who gave theories of warfare the patina of science in the latter half of the 1800s. With the evolution of weapons, tactics and technology that resulted from the American Civil War and the Franco-Prussian War, military science needed to go beyond mere considerations of the battlefield. Von Moltke, for instance, wrote extensively on exploiting the railroad and the telegraph to insure victory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MILITARY_SCIENCE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In the process, military science came to consider all aspects of war. Ardant du Picq looked at the manner in which a soldier’s fighting performance was rooted in the individual’s personal and group psychology while Hans Delbrück formulated the theory of a “strategy of exhaustion.” Other soldier-academics focused on logistics, economics, national morale, military intelligence and even more esoteric parts of war. The Great War was the chance for the generals to put these new theories of military science to the test, a sort of empirical experiment in slaughter.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MILITARY_SCIENCE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>The Cold War with its strategies of mutual destruction, state-sponsored terrorism and military-industrial complex, took military science from the merely theoretical to something far more terrifying and immediate for most civilians. Military Science has not been as simple since.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MILITARY_TACTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Until the Middle Ages, “tactics” was limited to mostly running at the enemy in a frontal assault, leavened by the occasional maneuver to turn the flank of the enemy line or the decision of when to commit the cavalry to take care of the survivors. Which is not to say that some civilizations were not quite adept at all this: the Akkadians, the Assyrians, the Macedonians, the Romans, the Guptas, and the Han Dynasty. Thus evolved the “Seven Classical Maneuvers” of tactics: penetration of the center, attack from a defensive position, single envelopment, double envelopment, attack in oblique order, feigned retreat, and the indirect approach.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MILITARY_TACTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In the late 4th Century AD Publius Flavius Vegetius Renatus wrote De re Militari, described by some historians as "the bible of warfare throughout the Middle Ages." One of the five major sections of this work focused on field tactics, and stressed the role of infantry and archers, because they were cheaper than cavalry and could operate across any terrain. Some 200 versions of the work appeared, translated into every European language. But European tactics were forced to evolve when the Arabs, Mongols and Turks didn’t pay much attention to Vegetius’ pronouncements on cavalry.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MILITARY_TACTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tactics underwent another paradigm shift when gunpowder appeared on the battlefield. Black-powder warfare reached its apex in the Napoleonic Wars, which laid down the principles of tactics that would dominate war until the invention of machine-guns, barbed wire, poison gas, tanks and airplanes made them all moot come the First World War. Napoleonic tactics focused on formations and the maneuver of lines, columns and squares, as well as upon the melding of infantry, cavalry and artillery into supporting and integrated branches. It was all rather elegant.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MILITARY_TACTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>But the First World War and even more the Second changed everything. The Germans developed the blitzkrieg, the British commando operations, the Americans airborne attacks, while the Soviets just bludgeoned their way forward. On the mobile battlefield the old accepted tactics were forced to give way to the feuerkampf (fire fight) between squads and platoons.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MILITARY_TACTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>And all this doesn’t even touch on the history of naval tactics, as triremes gave way to ships-of-the-line to dreadnaughts to battleships …</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MINING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If it can’t be found laying about, dig it up. That’s the basic premise behind mining, one of civilization’s earliest and most pragmatic technologies. The Neolithics mined flint in England and France about 4000 BC; the ancient Egyptians mined malachite at Maadi between 2600 and 2500 BC, using the hard stone for ornamentation and pottery. These were generally open pit mines, or shallow shafts (less than 100 feet deep) such as the Athenian silver mines at Laurium, where over 20 thousand slaves labored.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MINING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>It was Roman engineers who developed large and efficient mining methods; among their other advances in the technology, building aqueducts to bring water to the mine site, where it was used to remove debris (a sort of early hydraulic mining) and separate ore from crushed rock. Romans also developed the process of thermal cracking to shatter rock, building fires against the rock face and heating the stone until it shattered when a stream of water was directed onto it. Their mining methods spread around the world, as men dug for copper, iron, gems, gold, silver, and just about every other mineral and crystal.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MINING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In Asia and the Americas, mining tech remained fairly primitive until the Europeans arrived to begin carting off the wealth of those lands. During the late Middle Ages, as the rich veins easily reached were exhausted, deep mining evolved, using hand tools to drive shafts further down and shoring the walls and ceilings up with timber. Then the great silver crisis of 1465 AD came when the mines reached such depths that groundwater filled the shafts. It took a hundred years for that obstacle to be overcome, and in the meantime gunpowder blasting replaced the picks and shovels (mostly). Then came the Industrial Revolution, with its thirst for coal, and mining became mechanized and ever more rapacious.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_NANOTECHNOLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Tiny machines inside animals and humans snipping, slicing, splicing, melding or mutating cells. Tiny machines creating new materials on the molecular level. Or tiny machines making more tiny machines. Whatever use it may be put to, nanotechnology is just beyond the edge of science fiction.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_NANOTECHNOLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The theoretical foundations of nanotech date back to December 29, 1959 AD, when the American physicist Richard Feynman introduced it in a Physical Science conference at CalTech. Norio Taniguchi first used the term “nanotechnology” in 1974 to describe the “process of separation, consolidation, and deformation of materials by one atom or one molecule.” In 1985, fullerenes were discovered by a trio of chemists, who were able to form semiconductor clusters using pulsed molecular beams. In 1991 K. Eric Drexler gained his PhD degree with his work on nanotechnology and the following year published his dissertation, laying the basis for practical applications of the technology. Meanwhile, in 1989 IBM researchers became the first to manipulate atoms using a tunneling microscope.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_NANOTECHNOLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The first decade of the 21st Century saw the initial uses of nanotech in commercial manufacturing, although mostly limited to the use of passive nanoparticles such as titanium dioxide and zinc-oxide in cosmetics and food products, silver nanoparticles in food packaging and disinfectants, and carbon nanotubes in textiles. In March 2011, the Project on Emerging Nanotechnologies identified some 1300 nanotech products, with new applications being made available at the rate of three or four each week. Meanwhile, the National Nanotechnology Initiative was created by the American government for research to “foster the transfer of new technologies for public benefit … and support responsible development of nanotechnology.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_NANOTECHNOLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Despite dystopian scenarios (such as in Crichton’s novel Prey) and the “polite” debate between leading theorists Richard Smalley (the discoverer of the “buckyball” molecule) and pioneer Eric Drexler over the advent of molecular assemblers, along with some concerns about DNA nanotechnology (the first DNA nanomachine which could change its structure via an input was demonstrated in 1999 by Nadrian Seeman), it seems civilization is on the cusp of a “nanotech revolution.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_NUCLEAR_FISSION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mushroom clouds and boundless energy; utopia or annihilation. The technology of nuclear fission carries the promise of both, or neither. In physics and chemistry, nuclear fission is the decay – natural or not – whereby the nucleus of an atom breaks down into lighter nuclei, spinning off neutrons and photons, thus releasing significant amounts of energy. If a chain reaction can be started, whereby these free neutrons and photons cause other nuclei around them to split, a lot of energy gets released all at once.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_NUCLEAR_FISSION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Building on the work of scientific geniuses such as Marie Curie, Ernest Rutherford, Niels Bohr, Enrico Fermi, and Edward Teller, the United States funded the Manhattan Project, headed by physicist J. Robert Oppenheimer, in 1942 AD to create a sustainable nuclear reaction using uranium or plutonium. The result was the first atomic bomb successfully tested in the New Mexico desert in July 1945. The next month, America dropped two more on Japanese cities, leaving between 129 thousand and 246 thousand dead. Once Soviet spies stole the plans, the nuclear arms race was on.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_NUCLEAR_FISSION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Yet nuclear fission also offered the hope for cheap, “clean” energy. In September 1948 in Oak Ridge, Tennessee, electricity was generated by a nuclear reaction for the first time – at least enough to power a light bulb. A second, larger experiment in Arco, Idaho, in 1951 proved the feasibility of building a nuclear power plant. Thus, in 1954, the world’s first nuclear plant to generate electricity for a power grid started operations in Obninsk in the Soviet Union, followed shortly by the world’s first full scale nuclear power station at Calder Hall in England. Despite nuclear meltdowns such as those at Three Mile Island in 1979, Chernobyl in 1986, and the three at Fukushima-Daiichi in 2011, nuclear-generated power may be the savior of modern civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_NUCLEAR_FUSION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In contrast to nuclear fission – where energy is generated by the division of a nucleus – nuclear fusion occurs when two or more atomic nuclei slam together hard enough to fuse, which also releases photons in quantity. Fusion reactions power the stars of the universe, giving off lots of light and heat.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_NUCLEAR_FUSION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>During WW2, research to create a fission bomb subsumed research into nuclear fusion. But in 1946 AD a patent was awarded to two British researchers for a prototype fusion reactor based on the Z-pinch concept, whereby a magnetic field could be generated to contain plasma (akin to that in a star). Commencing the following year, two teams in Britain began a series of ever larger experiments to generate electricity via fusion; another Brit, James Tuck, working at Los Alamos in the United States, built a series of fusion reactors leading to the largest, known derisively as the “Perhapsatron.” As it turned out, the name was apt, for experiments revealed instabilities in all these designs such that fusion was never reached.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_NUCLEAR_FUSION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Instead, it was left to the weapons engineers to create the first man-made fusion reaction – Ivy Mike, the first thermonuclear bomb tested in 1952 at Enewetak atoll. Two years later Castle Bravo was exploded at Bikini Atoll, with a yield of 15 megatons. Meanwhile, the Soviet Union was building and testing its own thermonuclear arsenal. But these were all uncontrolled fusion reactions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_NUCLEAR_FUSION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>In many small steps – and some dead ends – the state of fusion research slowly advanced through the 1950s to the 1990s. Finally, in 1991, scientists at the Joint European Torus in England achieved the first controlled release of fusion power. This was followed, as expected, by lots of scientific papers on ways to improve the process, making any such reactor smaller and more affordable and more controllable. Despite debate and contending claims, in 2014 Lockheed Martin’s “Skunk Works” lab announced development of a high-beta fusion reactor and plans to build a 100-megawatt prototype by 2017, ready for regular operation in 2022.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_PLASTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Synthetic or semi-synthetic organic polymers derived (generally) from petrochemicals of high molecular mass that are incredibly durable, malleable, lightweight and now pervasive in modern civilization. Plastic. It comes in many forms, some tougher, some more flexible, some with a greater or lesser tolerance to heat. Plastic can be molded, pressed, or extruded into virtually any shape desired. It’s found in every facet of life today, used in everything from automobile bumpers to prosthetic limbs, from product packaging to modernist furniture, home entertainment to the latest weaponry.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_PLASTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>There had been some plastic-like materials developed during the Industrial Revolution; for instance, in 1855 AD Alex Parkes, spurred by the near extinction of the elephant, made a material from cellulose as a cheap replacement for ivory. But the first entirely synthetic plastic was Bakelite, invented in 1909 by inventor Leo Hendrik Baekeland. Bakelite was cheap and durable. So it was used to make radios, telephones, utensil handles, piano keys, and billiard balls. Although quite sturdy, Bakelite was also quite brittle.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_PLASTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Following the First World War, radical advances in chemistry (all that production of poison gases and new explosives) led to an explosion of new forms of plastic. Polyvinyl chloride (or PVC), a rigid and durable plastic, began being manufactured commercially in the 1920s by various companies. The transparent polystyrene was commercialized in 1931 by I.G. Farben, and in 1941 – spurred by another war – Dow Chemical invented Styrofoam. (In 1960, Dart Container company, the largest maker of the now-ubiquitous Styrofoam cup, shipped their first order.)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_PLASTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>It was rapidly becoming a plastic world. By the 21st Century, just about every consumer product had plastic components or was wholly plastic. Indeed, the landfills around the world are filled with it, and great floating masses of plastic can be found in the oceans since it does not degrade naturally, and burning it tends to produce noxious fumes. Too, although relatively cheap to make, plastic takes a lot of petrochemicals to manufacture in quantity. So perhaps as oil becomes scarce and expensive, so too will plastic.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_POTTERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“The art or craft of the potter, the skill of creating ceramic items” – in other words, making things out of mud. With pottery, objects (sometimes useful) are shaped out of clay and then placed in an oven and subjected to high temperatures. The resulting product is extremely brittle but is also airtight and more-or-less impervious to corrosion, oxidation, infestation, and other decay. The earliest pottery objects found include jugs and containers to hold liquid or grain. And some really ugly statuettes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_POTTERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The earliest known ceramics are the Gravettian culture figurines (little, faceless representations of fat women) that date back to between 29 and 25 thousand BC. These were shaped by hand, and fired in a pit. Somewhere around 12000 years ago, clever folk figured out that clay – often mixed with sand, grit, crushed shells, or bone – could be used to make more useful items: pots, cups, plates, bowls, storage jars, and so forth. In Japan, during the Jōmon period, potters began putting glaze on their earthenware pots. During this time several types of pottery were developed – earthenware, stoneware, and porcelain.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_POTTERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Until the potter’s wheel was invented in Mesopotamia sometime during the Ubaid period (6000-4000 BC), pots had to be shaped by hand … a laborious process. Harnessing the wheel speeded pottery making. Until the Etruscans made use of molds to “mass produce” pots and other items in the 6th Century BC, a process “acquired” by the Romans when they swept away their bothersome neighbors. In China, meanwhile, the process of slipcasting – another way to mass produce ceramic vessels – evolved during the T’ang dynasty.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_POTTERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Then all these lovely ceramics got replaced by plastic…</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_PRINTING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>No technology since writing so impacted civilization as did movable-type printing. Woodblock printing had been used for decades in China, India and Europe. The pecia system developed in the early 13th Century at Italian universities gave booksellers a method for producing multiple copies of a book in a relatively short time. But books remained expensive, and possessions only for the educated elite.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_PRINTING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>By the 1400s, a faster, cheaper method of reproducing the written word had become the “Holy Grail” for European booksellers, driven by the rise in education and literacy. Even the commoners wanted to read the Bible for themselves, and their kids were learning their letters in new grammar schools springing up all over the continent. In China, moveable type – where each word could be placed in any order in a tray and then inked and pressed against paper – was made out of porcelain by Bi Sheng in 1040 AD, but proved rather fragile and expensive. Moveable wooden type wore out too quickly.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_PRINTING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>It was left to an itinerant German goldsmith and sometime bookseller (and sometimes other professions, none of which he was very successful at) named Johannes Gutenberg to develop movable type made from metal, each small piece representing a letter or punctuation mark that could be rearranged in a tray as needed to make a page. The metal type, made from lead, was durable and easy to cast; when worn, the type could be melted and used again to make more type. The failed goldsmith also devised an oil-based ink that worked well with the metal type to give long-lasting print.  Gutenberg set up a workshop in Mainz, and by 1450 was printing common texts (likely, Latin grammars) and church indulgences; in 1452 Gutenberg commenced work on a printed version of the Bible which was completed in 1455 – the so-called Gutenberg Bible.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_PRINTING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>The invention revolutionized the world, and gave rise to mass communication. It spread rapidly across Europe, since booksellers could now make (and sell) lots of copies. It not only standardized language and knowledge – bringing page numbers, tables of contents, indexes, the ability to cite other works and all sorts of things not possible with hand-copied books – but it taught humanity to think in linear (since that’s how folk read now) terms rather than holistically. And it sparked – or at least promoted – the Scientific Revolution and the Reformation. So, if civilization is a mess, blame it on Gutenberg.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_RADIO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The idea of “wireless” communication begins with experiments in wireless telegraphy – sending impulses through the ground, water and even steel railroad tracks – in the 1830s. In 1888 AD, Heinrich Hertz proved conclusively that electromagnetic waves could be transmitted through the air; his publications set off a mad scramble among inventors and crackpots to produce these Hertzian waves. Even the likes of Nikola Tesla, Amos Dolbear, and Sir Oliver Lodge got involved. But it took an obscure Italian inventor by the name of Guglielmo Marconi to build the first working, completely successful wireless telegraph … or radio, as some folks called it … in 1894. He patented it in 1896 in England. Marconi was awarded the Nobel Prize in 1909 for his work. He also eventually became wealthy, became a senator in the Italian parliament, and joined the Fascist Party in 1923, being made president of the Royal Academy by Mussolini – but that’s another tale.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_RADIO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Initially the radio was used to transmit messages in Morse Code, but in 1900 a Brazilian priest, Roberto de Moura, successfully transmitted the human voice by radio waves (he was granted a patent for his modulator equipment a year later). The next advance was the vacuum tube, invented by engineers working for Westinghouse. Then, using all these together, the first radio broadcast was made from Ocean Bluff-Brant Rock, Massachusetts, on Christmas Eve 1906, a broadcast that included holiday music and readings from the Bible; ships at sea reported picking up this first amplitude modulation (now just termed “AM”) transmission. Two years later, on his way to being a millionaire, Marconi opened civilization’s first radio factory in Chelmsford, England.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_RADIO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In short order there were commercial radio broadcast stations opening all over the place; entrepreneurs had finally figured out how to make money broadcasting commercials (first from station WEAF in New York) and Congress how to make money licensing stations. The first news program broadcast was in August 1920 by station 8MK in Detroit. The first college station began broadcasting in October 1920 at Union College. That same month the college station there aired what is thought to be the first entertainment program, a series of Thursday night concerts. In 1921 the first sports broadcast – a football game between West Virginia and Pittsburgh – was offered. Now the radio programmers really had people’s attention</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_REPLACEABLE_PARTS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Evidence for the use of interchangeable parts can be traced back to the warships of Carthage during the First Punic War, when standardized parts made repairs to their galleys relatively quick. During the Warring States period, the Qin dynasty employed mass-produced crossbows with interchangeable parts to pummel its rivals. So it was throughout the ages, until Eli Terry finally mass made something not a weapon on his production line in America in 1814 AD – a pillar-and-scroll clock. In the mid-1800s, several clock and sewing machine manufacturers started using interchangeable parts in their factories. Both the Singer Sewing Machine Corporation (1870) and McCormick Harvesting Machine Company (1880) adopted the practice, followed by steam engine, typewriter and bicycle manufacturers. And then Henry Ford adopted it for his affordable brand of automobiles.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_REPLACEABLE_PARTS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The development of interchangeable parts in manufacturing was due in large part to the innovation and invention of a number of manufacturing machines, which permitted only very small variances in the final parts. Manufacturing was revolutionized by the slide rest lathe, screw cutting lathe, milling machine and metal planer, in turn. Add electrification of the machines for higher speed, and now hundreds of identical parts could be churned out each hour by skilled machinists. Configuration management evolved in the 1950s as a systems engineering field to insure consistency in performance and physical attributes of manufactured parts. Then came robots to work the assembly lines.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_REPLACEABLE_PARTS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The development of replaceable parts in all realms of consumer products spurred the Industrial Revolution, and boosted the quality of life since all kinds of things became affordable to the average working-class person. Conspicuous consumption was at last within the reach of civilization … or at least, of some of it.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_RIFLING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Rifling is merely the cutting of helical grooves into the inner part of a gun barrel so as to induce spin in a ball or bullet which serves to gyroscopically stabilize the projectile, giving it greater accuracy and range. In short, all this means is that it took a skilled marksman to hit anything specific with a smoothbore musket, but any fool with a steady hand has a fair chance of success firing a rifle at a target.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_RIFLING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Although problematic to decide who first came up with the idea, rifling of musket barrels was begun by several gunsmiths in Augsburg in the late 15th Century; August Kotter, in Nuremburg, improved upon the design around 1520 AD. However, rifling wasn’t particularly effective with black-powder weapons, due to the residue left behind in the barrel (thus mucking up the grooves); the most effective rifled black-powder weapons were breech-loaded pistols, such as the Queen Anne flintlock. Although rifling dates from the 16th Century, it didn’t become common until the wars of the Industrial Age.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_RIFLING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In the early 1700s Benjamin Robins, an English mathematician, proved that an elongated “bullet” rather than a ball would retain the spin from a rifle barrel but cut the air resistance better. Within a couple decades, most continental armies had rifle battalions to augment the musket-armed infantry regiments. At first these units were used to snipe at enemy officers … sharpshooters in truth. But by the time of the Napoleonic wars, and more so during the American Civil War, rifle-armed troops were integrated into the regular line infantry.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_RIFLING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>In 1866, breech-loading rifles were being developed: the German “needle” gun, French Tabatière, British Snider-Enfield. Bolt action rifles such as the Chassepot meant that rifles could be loaded faster and fired even from the prone position. The American Colt “Revolving Rifle” was the first “repeating” rifle. Except for some deadly refinements – like automatic fire and telescopic sights – rifling had reached its apex.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ROBOTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In 1942 AD, the science fiction author Isaac Asimov proposed three “laws of robotics.” In 1948 the American mathematician Norbert Wiener formulated the “principles of cybernetics” as the basis for practical robotics. And in 1961 the first programmable robot – “Unimate” – was constructed to lift and stack hot pieces of metal from a die casting machine. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ROBOTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Automata – self-operating machines – have been around since described in the third-century BC Chinese text 'Liezi' attributed to the philosopher Lie Yukou. In 1495 AD, no less a genius than Leonardo da Vinci offered schematics for a mechanical knight, a proto-robot. The French artist and tinkerer Jacques de Vaucanson built a mechanical duck that was able to eat, flap its wings, and excrete afterward – the “Digesting Duck” in 1738; more significantly, he also built a completely automated loom, perhaps the first commercially viable “automaton.” So “robots” (so-named by Czech Karel Capek in his play R.U.R.) were around long before ABB Robot Group installed the world’s first microcomputer controlled industrial robot in Sweden in 1974.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ROBOTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>But, of course, it is humanoid robots – with a torso, head with facial features of some sort, two or more arms, bipedal locomotion – that get everyone both excited and concerned. The darlings of sci-fi writers and Hollywood studios, such robots are only starting to be realized. In 1973, Wabot-1 was built, able to walk, communicate in Japanese, and measure distance to objects with artificial eyes and ears. (Almost as entertaining as the Digesting Duck, apparently.) Soon enough, just about every year a new robot was delighting the world. In 2005, Wakamaru made its first appearance, a Japanese-built domestic robot intended to provide care and companionship for the elderly and disabled.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ROBOTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Of course, robots need not be humanoid in form. In fact, the human form is an inefficient design, and so there are a plethora of possibilities, all being explored by engineers and manufacturers for various tasks – wheeled robots, spherical-orb robots, tracked robots, etc. – with all sorts of grapplers and manipulators rather than hands. The possibilities are nearly endless. Or as Terry Pratchett asked, “I wonder what makes us build inefficiently-shaped human robots instead of nice streamlined machines?”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ROCKETRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>No one is quite sure who fired off the first rocket. Some historians state that rockets were first used in a battle in 1232 AD by the Chinese against the Mongols, with explosions being heard some 15 miles away. Others claim the first rockets were exemplified by the “ground-rat,” a type of firework, used by the Emperor Lizong on the occasion of his mother Kung Sheng’s birthday in 1264. It is certain that the first written mention of rockets was in the Huolongjing, by the Chinese artillery officer Jiao Yu in the mid-14th Century; it even describes the first multi-stage rocket, seemingly used by the Chinese navy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ROCKETRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Until the Second World War, rockets remained relatively short-range, inaccurate, clumsy weapons … or were used for making pretty fireworks (not that military rockets don’t make pretty explosions). In 1792, iron-cased rockets were used by Tipu Sultan defending Mysore against the avaricious British East India Company. The British, sensing a good thing, developed the solid-fuel Congreve Rocket for use against the French, Americans and other unpleasant sorts. In 1914, Robert Goddard – inspired by the fanciful tales of H.G. Wells – patented several concepts that proved pivotal in the history of rocketry: a combustion chamber, multiple stages, and a nozzle to increase exhaust speed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_ROCKETRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Meanwhile, German scientists were also refining their own designs for rockets – for bombing the enemy, of course. Where the V-1 was a crude, simplistic flying bomb, the V-2 was a marvel, with turbopumps, inertial guidance systems and many other innovations still used by rocket scientists. The end of the war set off a “space race” when the two superpowers “assimilated” many of Germany’s top rocket scientists from Peenemunde, notably America’s acquisition of Wernher von Braun. Although it was the Soviet Union that launched the first satellite and the first man into orbit. But it was America that built the first nuclear-tipped ICBM.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SAILING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since rowing a ship is a lot of work, men developed sails to let the wind push it along. Sailing gave humans a quicker, easier way to travel than over land, and has been used for trade, transport, fishing and warfare since the first mast was raised. The oldest representation of a ship under sail was found on a painted disc in Kuwait, dating to between 5500 and 5000 BC. Tomb paintings c. 3200 BC show reed boats under sail on the Nile. A few hundred years later, the Egyptians were venturing along the shores of the Mediterranean. Along every coastline, from China to Scandinavia, the technology of sailing – distinctive to each seagoing culture – was evolving.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SAILING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Barques, brigs, caravels and clippers and catboats, feluccas, galleons, junks, longships, misticos, schooners and sloops; the technology and design of sailing ships was as diverse as the peoples who sailed these. By 2500 BC, the Egyptians were building sailing ships from planks of cedar wood, lashed together by straps and reeds to seal the seams; the “Khufu” ship discovered intact at the foot of the Giza pyramid in 1954 AD was a vessel of 143 feet driven by oars and cotton sails. Around the same time, the Scandinavians developed a method of boat building with segmented hull compartments, which allowed for ever larger longboats. By 1000 AD, the Vikings were the unchallenged seamen and boat builders of the world, sailing even across the Atlantic to North America.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SAILING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Trial-and-error (a lot of drowned sailors) brought technological improvements in sails, masts, hulls, rigging. Arab, Chinese and Indian merchants ranged along the fringes of the Pacific, opening trade routes and diplomatic relations. But it was the Europeans who would sail the world; from the 15th Century onward, European sailors went further, stayed longer, and explored the globe, creating colonial empires based on their sailing fleets.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SANITATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A clean water supply and sanitation has been rather important for the rise of civilization, since without such folk tend to fall prey to disease and death. Especially when crowded together in urban centers. The earliest signs of city sanitation have been found in the ruins of the Harappan settlements Mohenjo-daro and Rakhigarhi in the Indus Valley c. 2500 BC. There groups of homes obtained water from a common well, and waste water (with all that was in it) was emptied into covered drains which lined the streets.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SANITATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Roman cities and villas had even better water and sanitation systems, with stone and wooden sewers – the famed Cloaca Maxima in Rome, which emptied into the River Tiber – to carry the waste away from civilized folk. But there is little evidence of sensible sanitation across the rest of Europe until the late Middle Ages; hence, the Plague of Cyprian (likely smallpox), Plague of Justinian (bubonic plague), the Black Death. Slowly – because of the expense – during the Renaissance sewers replaced the pail closets, outhouses and cesspits of Europe. (Meanwhile, the Mayan city of Palenque is believed to have had underground aqueducts and flush toilets.)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SANITATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In 1596 Sir John Harington published his work A New Discourse on a Stale Subject in which he described the forerunner to the modern toilet, which he had installed in his home, incorporating a flush valve, a water tank, and a means to wash down the bowl when used. He also installed one for his godmother Queen Elizabeth I at Richmond Palace, but she refused to use it because of the unseemly noise.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SANITATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>With the onset of the Industrial Revolution, urban growth and more disposable income for many workers – and the invention of the S-trap by Alexander Cumming in 1775 – indoor toilets became a practical reality. Inventor Joseph Bramah added a float-valve system to the water tank, and in 1778 began installing toilets in homes and businesses across London, a very lucrative operation by all accounts. For soon, everyone wanted one.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SATELLITES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Beep … beep … beep.” So it began. Sputnik, with an onboard radio signal transmitter, was launched in October 1957 AD by Soviet Russia. Orbiting overhead, the artificial satellite (as opposed to natural satellites like the Moon) Sputnik served notice to the humans huddled on the surface that the world had dramatically changed … for better or not remained to be determined. Sputnik 2 was launched in November, with the first living creature in space aboard, a dog named Laika (who died within hours of the launch).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SATELLITES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Following pressure from the American Rocket Society, National Science Foundation and (the only body that really mattered) the White House, the American military announced its own program to put a satellite into orbit. Three months after poor Laika’s orbit, the United States sent Explorer 1 around the Earth. In 1961, the U.S. Air Force used the newly created Space Surveillance Network to catalogue 115 Earth-orbiting satellites. Space was getting crowded. (Currently, it tracks about 8000 man-made objects circling the globe, much of it space “junk.”)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SATELLITES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Around the time the United States was making a list of satellites, the Soviet Union launched a man into space; on April 12, 1961, Yuri Gagarin became the first human to orbit the Earth, aboard the Vostok 1 satellite. Unlike poor Laika, the cosmonaut returned alive. America’s John Glenn aboard Friendship 7 orbited in February 1962. China became the third nation to put a man in space: Yang Liwei in the Shenzhou 5 in October 2003. And scientists from many nations have served aboard the International Space Station – the largest orbiting satellite to date – since its first component was launched in 1998; it orbits the Earth every 92.69 minutes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SATELLITES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Many countries – even the likes of Qatar (2013), Uruguay (2014) and Turkmenistan (2015) – have placed satellites in orbit. Not to mention dozens of private companies that have paid large sums to put their satellites (mostly telecomm ones) into orbit, spurred on by the passage of the Commercial Space Launch Act of 1984 by the United States Congress. Now there are also a number of firms exploring manned commercial flights into orbit, or beyond.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SCIENTIFIC_THEORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Scientific theories work well to explain how the natural (and unnatural) world works, being based on well-substantiated and oft-observed phenomena that can be replicated. Thus, empirical scientific theories are predictive, universal and testable. Scientific laws, by contrast, offer no explanation of the mechanics of a phenomenon, merely unvarying observation of something occurring. Obsolete theories, such as the phlogiston theory of combustion, are tossed aside once research or instrumentation uncovers new empirical data about the phenomenon.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SCIENTIFIC_THEORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Scientific theory is based upon the evolution of the scientific method, beginning with Aristotle’s inductive-deductive approach to scientific observation as laid out in his Organon. But Aristotle’s was not the only approach to formulating theories; Epicurus laid out his own rules for “inferring” how and why nature functions. Europeans didn’t pay much attention to science during the Dark Ages (being rather more concerned with surviving all the wars, plagues and famines), but in 1021 AD the Arab physicist ibn al-Haytham, known in the West as Alhazen, laid out his method of proposing scientific theories: observation, experimentation and rational logic.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SCIENTIFIC_THEORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Once Europe emerged from its troubles, Renaissance humanists added their own thoughts on how scientific theories should be generated. Francisco Sanches in his writings, 1571 through 1573, argued that the only true method for knowing was based on skepticism, and Francis Bacon thus developed eliminative induction as the basis for proposing scientific theories. Descartes, Galilei and Newton refined his methods. In the 20th Century, Charles Peirce, Karl Popper and Thomas Kuhn debated and advanced the notion of what the scientific method should be, a standard for all inquiry in all the research disciplines.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SCIENTIFIC_THEORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>There are, of course, other, less-empirical ways of understanding the universe, but scientific theories remain grounded in reality … and have brought civilization insights and technologies to make human life much more comfortable.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SHIPBUILDING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Shipbuilding is, of course, the building of ships. Shipwrights follow a profession that traces its roots back to an age before recorded history. Archaeological evidence indicates that humans sailed to Borneo from Asia 120 thousand years ago aboard constructed ships; and later to New Guinea and Australia some 50 thousand years ago. In the fourth millennium BC, the Egyptians were constructing boat hulls from planks of wood, using treenails to hold them together and pitch to make them watertight. Across the ocean in India, the first shipbuilding docks were being utilized by the Harappans around 2500 BC.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SHIPBUILDING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>While the Phoenicians, Greeks and Carthaginians were pretty good at shipbuilding, most of their knowledge was lost during the “Dark” Ages. Save for the Vikings, the Europeans weren’t particularly skilled or innovative. However, in China during the Song and Ming dynasties, shipbuilding reached its peak, building junks and warships that filled the greatest ports of the time. In the Islamic world shipbuilding thrived in Basra and Alexandria, producing the dhows and feluccas that plied trade routes from East Asia to the tip of Africa.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SHIPBUILDING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The Age of Exploration, as the Europeans set out to conquer the world, demanded new approaches to shipbuilding. Shipyards became large industrial complexes (like the Arsenal in Venice), able to turn out ships of a standard design (like the carrack) in a matter of weeks or even days. By the Napoleonic Wars, ships were still being built to basic, standardized plans in expansive shipyards; the British in fact established Royal Dockyards across the globe to support their naval aspirations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SHIPBUILDING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Advances in ship design and materials during the Industrial Revolution for shipbuilding for the first time in centuries made new methods mandatory. Massive iron- and steel-hulled ships such as the Great Eastern and the Titanic and modern dreadnaughts meant that most ships now are constructed in expansive drydocks.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SIEGE_TACTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In essence, siege tactics haven’t changed much since Megiddo (c. 1457 BC), Tyre (332 BC), Carthage (149-146 BC), and Masada (73-74 AD) – not to mention Troy around 1200 BC should one believe Homer. Once the Assyrians and their neighbors began building walls around their cities to keep the riff-raff out, it became necessary for any serious conqueror to have the means to take such places.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SIEGE_TACTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>From time immemorial, the attacker’s first act was usually a “surprise” assault, seeking to overwhelm the defenders before they were ready for or even aware of a threat. That usually didn’t work, but it was worth a try. And so most attackers fell back on investing the town, looking to force the defenders inside to surrender (or hoping for an insider to betray the garrison and open the gates). If the place was completely encircled, food, water and other supplies could be kept from reaching the besieged. If starvation loomed … as it often did … the defenders and civilians were reduced to eating anything vaguely edible – horses, family pets, leather, sawdust and even each other. Disease was also quite effective, and so the practice of hurling diseased carcasses (animal and human) over the walls. But either approach could take some time, especially if the city was large and well-stocked.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SIEGE_TACTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>To get things over quicker – since the besieging army itself might face illness, starvation or a relieving army – a large variety of siege engines were invented to breach or overtop the walls. Ladders and siege towers put men on the walls, while catapults and trebuchets shattered the walls and battering rams and siege hooks knocked or pulled down gates. Digging tunnels to collapse the walls – mining – sometimes worked. If these tactics were successful and the walls breached, it all ended in a bloody great melee in the city. The Ottomans were particularly adept at siege tactics … as Constantinople, Klis and Rhodes can attest.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SQUARE_RIGGING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The first two-mast square-rigged ships appeared in the Mediterranean in the mid-14th Century AD, replacing the triangular-rigged lanteen sailing ships that had been used for the previous thousand years. Perpendicular square sails had been used on sailing ships in Northern Europe before (on cogs and longships), and the design was adopted by the Crusaders for their transports, giving more speed and maneuverability so they could get to the Holy Land quicker. In short order, the Europeans added fore and stern castles, bowsprits, crow’s nests and additional masts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SQUARE_RIGGING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The “Age of Exploration” saw the design of the square-rigged caravel (the caravela redonda – so named for its rounded stern) by the Portuguese for their long voyages around and across the oceans. It quickly became the definitive, most common beast of burden for the explorers, the forerunner of the much-larger galleon; Magellan had an all-caravel fleet when he circumnavigated the globe in 1519. For the next three centuries, naval history was dominated by ever larger square-rigged ships, which carried Europeans to claim the Americas and Africa, plunder the wealth of the Far East, and wage war against each other.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SQUARE_RIGGING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The cannon-armed ships-of-the-line (from the three-deck 1st rates with over 90 guns aboard to the lowly 5th rates with only 18 guns) blasted away at each other into the Napoleonic wars and beyond. Frigates and barques chased enemy merchants. Speedy square-rigged blockade runners slipped past Yankee warships during the American Civil War. Towering clipper ships plied the Pacific and square-rigged American whalers hunted those beasts to near extinction.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SQUARE_RIGGING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>But the romance of the Age of Sail was coming to an end. In 1821 the first iron steamship, the British-built 116-ton Aaron Manby (with no lack of hubris, named after her builder) went to sea. Although sailing ships were cheaper to build and operate, and early iron steam engines were notoriously unreliable (so most carried masts and sails), the end of the square-rigged ship was on the horizon, reduced to being a rich man’s yacht in less than a century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_STEALTH_TECHNOLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The ability to creep around unseen and unleash havoc is the fantasy of every five-year-old; modern scientists are close to making it reality. Modern stealth technology is a combination of multiple military projects and experimental science expanded beyond what humans can see, trying to both hide and detect objects by radar, acoustics, thermal readings, or other less readily visible methods. Low observable technology, as stealth tech is also known, has been utilized since ancient hunters wrapped themselves in vegetation and/or skins to sneak up on animals. In the wake of the Napoleonic Wars, when all those bright red and blue uniforms made soldiers wonderful targets, various European nations began to experiment with camouflage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_STEALTH_TECHNOLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>During the First World War, the Germans tested the use of cellulose acetate as a covering for their airplanes, a transparent fabric that they hoped would make the craft harder to spot. The Canadians and British likewise experimented with “diffused lighting camouflage” during the next world war, but it was rendered obsolete by advances in radar. However, the German U-480, covered with anechoic rubber tiles to absorb the waves of active sonar, was the world’s first true stealth submarine. The Germans also were developing the Horten Ho 229 fighter-bomber, with carbon powder in the glue to absorb radar waves and other tricks to make it “invisible.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_STEALTH_TECHNOLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The Horten never flew, but in 1958 AD the American Central Intelligence Agency requested funds to design a stealth recon aircraft to replace the U-2 spy planes. The United States Air Force initiated its own research project in 1960, developing special screens for the air intakes, radar-absorbent materials and paint. In 1964, Lockheed’s Skunk Works produced the SR-71 “Blackbird.” A high-altitude stealth aircraft with – along with the above – canted vertical stabilizers and composite materials, lowering its radar signature significantly. It was followed in the 1970s by the stealth F-117 fighter and B-2 bomber. No doubt there are newer stealth aircraft, and even ships and ground vehicles, but those are as yet unseen by the public (or anyone else, if the technology works).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_STEAM_POWER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When heated to boiling, water produces steam. Even barbarians knew this. But harnessing that steam wasn’t thought of until Taqi al-Din Muhammed ibn Ma’ruf described a hypothetical steam turbine for turning a spit in 1551 AD. The move towards a workable steam engine gets started a century later when Edward Somerset published a collection on his “inventions,” including a steam pump, a working model of which he built in Raglan Castle. But he died before he could put it to use in mining as he’d planned. In 1680 Huygens published memoirs describing an engine that drives a piston; in 1698 one Thomas Savery builds a virtual copy of Somerset’s machine … and patents it in just about every use to which steam power could be put.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_STEAM_POWER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But in 1705 Thomas Newcomen coupled a steam boiler with a piston in a cylinder. Seven years later, now partnered with the unsavory Savery he installed his first commercial steam engine, intended to pump water out of mines. Soon enough every inventor was harnessing the “power of steam” to every conceivable machine imaginable, though occasionally blowing themselves up along with their boilers. In 1769, James Watt invented the separate condenser, installing a second cylinder with a water jet – making the steam engine both practical and much safer.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_STEAM_POWER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The “Industrial Revolution” arrived with steam. By 1802 steam engines were being installed in boats, and in 1825 steam railroads were in operation. Steam power revolutionized industry and transportation across the world. Within a century the globe was crisscrossed by rail lines and steamship routes. Steam-powered factory machines were turning out tens of millions of tons of commercial and consumer goods. The industrialized nations enjoyed a huge increase in productivity and wealth and pollution. Coal, the primary fuel used in steam engines, was being feverishly mined around the planet.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_STEAM_POWER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Eventually steam engines would be replaced by internal combustion engines, more efficient and a little less polluting. But before oil, steam was king, and our civilized world would never have existed without it.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_STEEL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The earliest examples of steel – an alloy of carbon and iron with both high tensile strength and high ductility – dates to c. 1800 BC in Anatolia; the “historian” Herodotus states in no uncertain terms that steel weapons were used in Iberia at the time of his scribblings, and Noric (Celtic) steel was favored by the Romans for weapons. Seric iron from southern India was reputedly the best for steel, and was used by the Greeks, Romans, Egyptians, east Africans, Chinese and Middle Eastern kingdoms. Steel was especially favored by swordsmiths, for it could be folded and beaten in many layers (such as the famed katanas) and held an edge. Damascus steel was thought better than other types, near legendary and much favored by Arab warriors. Europeans had to make do with “crucible” steel.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_STEEL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Modern steelmaking got its start in 1855 AD, when Henry Bessemer perfected his process using pig iron as the basis to make “mild” (or “low-carbon”) steel in quantity fairly cheaply, a century after Benjamin Huntsman had established the first steelworks in Sheffield, England – a refinement but not much improvement over the old “crucible” method. Within a few decades, however, steel mills were springing up all over the world using Bessemer’s method; the steel industry had been born, producing tons of it for the new bridges, skyscrapers, trains and automobiles, household gadgets and weapons of the modern era.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_STEEL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Along with petroleum, steel is the backbone of modern civilization. In 1980, there were a half-million steelworkers in the United States alone. Between 2000 and 2005, demand for steel increased 6% worldwide, driven by the building boom in India and China. In 2005, China was the world’s leading steel producer, followed (in order) by Japan, Russia and America. In 2008 steel began being traded as a commodity, first on the London Metal Exchange. Seems it really is worth (nearly) its weight in gold.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_STIRRUPS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Along with writing, gunpowder and pre-sliced bread, the stirrup is considered one of the basic inventions needed to spread civilization … at least by some historians. Like all great innovations, it seems such a simple idea. Humans had domesticated the horse around 4500 BC, but where to put one’s feet and how to stay on when the horse began running? The saddle, invented around 800 BC, took care of the latter problem. But adding two pieces of leather with a loop (later made of metal) on the end hanging down didn’t come about until around a half-millennia later – no one is quite sure when or where, although it was somewhere in east Asia as the Chinese Jin dynasty was using it by 322 BC.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_STIRRUPS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The idea of stirrups spread quickly, thanks to those barbarian horsemen of Central Asia who saw the advantages. Images from ancient India c. 200 BC show bare-footed riders using big-toed stirrups. A Kushan engraving made a century later shows a mounted rider with platform stirrups. Digging up Korean tumuli from the 5th Century AD yield stirrups, such as those found at Pokchong-dong and Pan-gyeje; and by the Nara period similar ones were in use in Japan. Meanwhile, European riders had to make do without stirrups until the 8th Century, when the Avars came storming out of Eurasia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_STIRRUPS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The Arabs soon picked up on the benefits, but more importantly so too did the Franks. Slamming into something with a ten-foot pole while astride a big horse was only feasible with stirrups. Especially if encased in heavy armor; indeed, medieval knights would have been hard pressed even to get mounted without stirrups. And thus was born – according to some – feudalism, notions of chivalry and other “advances” that would dominate Europe for the next several centuries.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SYNTHETIC_MATERIALS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once chemistry took hold of civilization, scientists started searching for ways to improve upon naturally occurring animal and plant products. First up, synthetic fibers pioneered by Joseph Swan in the early 1880s; his fiber was made from tree bark, intended as a longer-lasting filament for light bulbs but somewhat better as a textile. Next the Frenchman Hilaire de Chardonnet invented artificial silk, which was displayed to great acclaim at the 1889 Paris Exhibition. Five years later, a trio of British chemists created a synthetic material they called “viscose," and in 1924 it was renamed “rayon.” Then came nylon from Wallace Carothers, who was working for the chemical company DuPont. The first polyester fiber – Dacron – was invented in England in 1941 as part of the war effort.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SYNTHETIC_MATERIALS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>It wasn’t only fibers that were being produced from synthesized polymers; chemists were inventing all sorts of artificial materials in their corporate and college labs. The ‘50s and ‘60s might be thought of as the “Synthetic Age.” Naugahyde (derisively known as “pleather”) was a composite of fabric overlaid with polyvinyl chloride developed by Byron Hunter of the U.S. Rubber Company. The first synthetic diamond was created in 1953. The year 1960 saw a team of researchers in North Carolina create the first artificial turf, which came to prominence when “AstroTurf” was installed in the Houston Astrodome in 1966. Borazon, an artificial cubic form of boron nitride created at temperatures greater than 1800 degrees, in its crystal form is one of the hardest materials known.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SYNTHETIC_MATERIALS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>And new synthetics continued to be crafted at a frantic pace. Tyvek, a flashspun high-density olefin material, is used as a wrapping through which water vapor but not liquid can pass. Teslin was developed as a waterproof synthetic printing medium, a recyclable and non-toxic material used in a variety of ways; the first now-ubiquitous Teslin-based credit cards were produced by Ron Goade in 1984. And in 1965 Stephanie Kwolek at DuPont developed Kevlar, a para-aramid synthetic first used in the early 1970s in racing tires; now Kevlar, rated five times stronger than steel, is found in everything from toys to body armor. Ours truly is a synthetic civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_TELECOMMUNICATIONS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Internet and cable television, cell phones and satellite radio … it’s all telecommunications. Civilization is wrapped in a web of electromagnetic waves (and even a few land-based physical cables as well). The history of telecommunications begins in May 1844 AD when Samuel Morse sent his famous message by telegraph from Baltimore to Washington. It picked up speed in March 1876 when Alexander Graham Bell told his assistant, “Watson, come here,” over a telephone line. Telecommunication engineers have been racing ahead ever since.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_TELECOMMUNICATIONS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Telegraph and telephone communications were carried by wire, much too slow for the modern day. And even though they made the world smaller and changed the landscape of business, war, and politics, scientists and inventors were soon searching for “wireless” telecommunications, the process of sending electronic signals through the atmosphere to special receivers. In 1894 Guglielmo Marconi built the first commercially viable wireless telegraph, soon termed “radio.” In October 1925 Scottish inventor John Logie Baird publically demonstrated the transmission of moving halftone images, soon termed “television.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_TELECOMMUNICATIONS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Satellite telecommunications – or at least the idea for them – can be traced to a piece written by science fiction author Arthur C. Clarke published in the magazine Wireless World in October 1945. Sputnik, with an onboard radio transmitter, was launched by the Soviet Union in 1957; NASA soon followed with the balloon named Echo 1 which was capable of relaying signals between distant stations on the surface. Thus the Information Age floated into history. Now low Earth orbiting (LEO) and geostationary orbiting satellites bounce radio, television and telephone signals all around the globe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_TELECOMMUNICATIONS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>In cultural terms, the advent of satellite telecommunications has increased the public’s access to cultural markers and memes from distant peoples; the world may be on the verge of a single, homogeneous human culture. In financial terms, the international telecommunication industry generated $149 billion in 2007; the world may be on its way to an information economy. Whatever may come, the telecommunications genie is well out of the regulatory bottle.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_THE_WHEEL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Round, like a circle” … well, like a wheel, a circle artificially manufactured, with a hole in the middle for an axle. The wheel and axle combination is considered one of the “six simple machines” upon which civilization is based. Used on vehicles, it allows easy transport of heavy objects over distances; but the axle-wheel is also the basis for the likes of the steering wheel, potter’s wheel, flywheel, water wheel, and a whole host of other wheels that make life more comfortable.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_THE_WHEEL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The invention of the wheel comes in the late Neolithic Age, and along with the advance of several other technologies kicks off the Bronze Age. Archaeological evidence for wheeled vehicles appears in the fourth millennia BC, more or less at the same time in Mesopotamia, the Caucasus and Central Europe (obviously, an idea whose time had come). In China the wheel was certainly in existence by 1200 BC, when Chinese chariots appeared.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_THE_WHEEL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The first wheels were of solid wood, planks with rounded ends that were put together to give a round shape. In other places, stone and even clay (the Harappans of the Indus Valley) were used to make wheels. Spoked wheels first appear around 2000 BC in Asia Minor, where they were used on horse-drawn chariots. Later improvements included iron hubs and rims, greased axles, and the addition of springs or other sort of shock absorber.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_THE_WHEEL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Contrary to popular belief, the American natives did have the wheel before the Europeans arrived, as evidenced by Olmec pottery wheels and wheeled children’s toys; but since there weren’t any domesticated animals large enough to pull carts and wagons, the wheel remained underutilized. Elsewhere, the spoked wheel was getting attached to everything, from cannons to trains; and wheels remained relatively unchanged until the 1870s when wire wheels and pneumatic tires were invented.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_WRITING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Writing is a technology that – like a few others – quite literally changed the course of civilization. The ability to set things down so as to remember them – “external memory storage” – unaltered beyond a single lifetime meant that every aspect of the human condition, every social structural and cultural more, altered significantly. Writing allowed civilization to become organized – organized religion, organized government, organized economy, organized war, organized science. And literature, a great advance (according to authors) over mere oral tales.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_WRITING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Invented sometime around the fourth millennium BC, the earliest form of writing was “pictography,” in which little pictures represent an item or action. This may work adequately for very simple topics, but other methods become necessary when more esoteric topics are discussed. (Drawing a picture of a sheep may be easy, but how about a picture of the sound a sheep makes when it falls off of a pyramid?) Ideographs (pictures representing ideas) and pictographic writing never developed enough to be able to transmit meanings well.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_WRITING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In time, logographic writing – using a single character to represent a word – evolved. In Mayan, the glyphs allowed representation of complex meaning when combined in “sentences.” Likewise, about 90% of the Chinese logographic characters are compounds of a semantic meaning with a phonetic guide. In other languages – Mycenaean Greek, Cherokee, Ethiopic, some Creole tongues – syllabaries were developed, wherein a single written symbol approximates a verbal syllable, and writing got shorter and easier to manage for barbarians.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_WRITING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Finally, the alphabet – dating to the second millennium BC used for Semitic languages in the Levant – evolved, bane of pre-school children worldwide. An alphabet uses a set of symbols, each of which represents a sound in the language. During the following millennium, the Semitic alphabet became the foundation of many differing alphabets across the Middle East, Europe, North Africa and South Asia. The rest is history … written down, of course.</Text>
		</Row>
	</BaseGameText>
</GameData>