<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Ed Beach (Firaxis Games) -->
<GameData>
	<EnglishText>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MACEDON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to legends generally accepted by the ancient Greeks and hardly anyone else, Macedon was founded by Hellenic emigrants from Argos who gradually expanded in the region around Mount Bermius. Perdiccas, one of the original colonists, was acknowledged as the first king of Macedon in founding the Argead dynasty. More likely, the original Macedones were barbarians from the north, distinct from the Hellenes, Thracians, and Illyrians around them, who happened to find a stretch of unoccupied terrain suitable for their goats.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MACEDON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>We know that Caranus, Macedon's first recorded king, began his rule in 808 BCE. Although exact details are hazy, the next three centuries saw the rather ruthless and brutal Macedones master Pieria and Bottiaea, cross the Axius to conquer Mygdonia and Anthemus, dislodge the Eordi tribe, and deal similarly with the Almopes. Eventually they came to control all the lands between Thrace and Thessaly. Unfortunately for them, the Persian advance into Greece was a sudden check on their golden age of prosperity and slaughter.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MACEDON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>After wisely submitting, the Macedones became Persian subjects in 492 BCE, and were allowed to retain their own laws, customs, and kings. Alexander “Philhellene” played a minor part in the great invasion of the Persian king Xerxes, but quickly resumed the family business of conquest once the Persians were repulsed. Crestonaea and Bisaltia were reduced, and Macedonian control pushed eastwards almost to the river Strymon. A number of older Macedonian hill tribes submitted—the Lyncestis, the Eleimiots and others—but retained their own kings, who paid tribute.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MACEDON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Despite their differences, Macedon became progressively involved in the politics of the squabbling southern city-states of Greece during the 5th Century BCE. Macedonian palace culture was more Mycenaean than Hellenic, while the Greek city-states possessed aristocratic or democratic institutions. Alexander Philhellene’s son Perdiccas II spent his spare time inciting a war between Sparta and Athens, created his own Olynthian League from Greek colonies neighboring Macedon, and switched sides during the Peloponnesian War whenever such perfidy looked advantageous.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MACEDON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>The next tyrant, Perdiccas’s bastard son Archelaus, transformed Macedon into a regional economic power and thus laid the foundation for its later military fury. He built roads and scattered fortresses all over the land. Since “barbarians” such as the Macedones were forbidden to compete in the Olympic Games, Archelaus founded a competing competition. He encouraged his people to develop a taste for Greek literature, even welcoming the controversial playwright Euripides into his court. Unfortunately, Archelaus was treacherous and licentious. He was assassinated, supposedly by one of the victims of his lust.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MACEDON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>The murder of Archelaus in 399 BCE brought a long period of “disturbance” both internal and external. With a direct line of succession broken, the Macedonian court became the scene of plots and assassinations while a seemingly perpetual civil war raged throughout Macedonian territory. Numerous pretenders to the throne sprang up, backed by Illyrians, Thebans, Lacedaemonians, and even Athenians. It seemed for a time that Macedon might disappear entirely into the morass of history, bits being absorbed by its various greedy neighbors, until stability was re-established by Amyntas III.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MACEDON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Amyntas had three sons. His first, Alexander II, turned to an expansionist policy to solve Macedon’s problems. He invaded northern Greece, placed Macedonian garrisons in Thessaly's cities, and refused to withdraw them. Unfortunately for Alexander, the Thebans eventually forced their removal and took his brother hostage to ensure compliance. Upon Alexander II's death, Perdiccas III took the throne … until he managed to get 4,000 Macedones killed in a battle with the Illyrians, himself among them. The infant heir to Perdiccas was swiftly deposed by Amyntas’ third son, Philip II—a turning point in world history.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MACEDON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Until Philip II's ascension in 359 BCE, the most outstanding qualities of the Macedone kings had been their rude valor and their opportunistic cunning concerning diplomatic relations. Philip added "military genius" to the mix when he set out to restore the reputation of Macedones as mighty warriors—no easy task after recent events. Besides his deposed infant nephew, there were at least five pretenders to the Macedonian throne, two of whom were supported by foreign troops. The Illyrians, flushed with victory after Perdiccas III's defeat, had invaded Macedon and occupied most of the western provinces. Paeonia to the north and Thrace to the east rattled their spears.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MACEDON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Philip spent two years reorganizing and reforming his own military. He introduced a number of variations to the normal hoplite organization and its use. Among other things, he lengthened the spear and reduced the size of the shield. He added armored heavy cavalry called hetairoi and created more light infantry units to use as skirmishers. Once satisfied, Philip proceeded to introduce all who threatened his kingdom to his new hammer-and-anvil tactics. He drove back the Illyrians before turning on the Paeonians, annexing the regions of Pelagonia and southern Paeonia after slaughtering their armies. But Philip wasn't content to merely conquer his neighbors.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MACEDON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>While the Athenians were distracted by the first Social War in 357-355 BCE, Philip laid siege to their ally Amphipolis. Having taken the city, he proceeded to capture the Athenian possessions of Pydna and Potidaea, then overran the entire coastal areas between the Strymon and Nestus to gain access to the Thracian gold mines—from which Macedon soon claimed an annual revenue of 1000 talents.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MACEDON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>With the occupation of Nicaea, Cytinium and especially Elateia, the Athenians finally decided to do something about the upstart Philip, only to be smashed flat at the battle of Chaeronea by the irresistible Macedonian phalanxes. Macedon’s control of Greece was formalized at the Congress of Corinth in 337 BCE, attended by all the city-states except the Spartans, who Philip was content to ignore. With Greece conquered, Philip turned his attentions to Persia … but found himself decorating the sword of Pausanias, one of his seven bodyguards, during his own daughter’s marriage celebration. He died at the age of 47, having reigned for nearly half of his life.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MACEDON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>Philip’s son Alexander III promptly continued his father's plans to invade Persia, and ended up forming the largest empire known to the ancient world. Though Alexander the Great's story is detailed elsewhere, the aftermath of his untimely demise was Macedon's own death knell. Nearly all Alexander's arranged marriages between Greeks and Susa noble families dissolved, and the Greek city-states rebelled. Various claimants crawled forth for the crown of Macedon itself.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MACEDON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_13">
			<Text>After a decade of bloodshed, the terms of the peace treaty in 311 BCE were that each surviving general should keep what he possessed, that all the Greek cities should become independent, and that Cassander—son of the general Antipater—would retain power in Macedon until Alexander’s son by his wife Roxana came of age to rule. This led to the murder of Roxana and young Alexander IV on the orders of Cassander, who proceeded to found the Antipatrid dynasty when he declared himself King of Macedon in 305 BCE.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MACEDON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_14">
			<Text>Cassander’s untimely death from dropsy in 297 BCE saw the Antipatrid dynasty fall to the Antigonids. As the dynasties fought, the whole country slipped into anarchy and the remnants of Alexander's empire went their own various ways. It wasn’t until Antigonus II that Macedon regained stability. Under his successors, Macedon even began to reassert its military prowess.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MACEDON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_15">
			<Text>The Romans had other ideas. Their legions roundly defeated Philip V's vaunted Macedonian phalanxes. His son Perseus was forced into a losing engagement with the Romans near Pydna in 168 BCE, after which the fallen king fled to Samothrace with some 6,000 talents, the bulk of the Macedonian treasury. The conquered kingdom was itself divided into four distinct “provinces” by the Romans, who were content to receive half the tribute Macedones previously tithed their king. Consequently, few were upset by the demise of Macedon as an independent nation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ALEXANDER_QUOTE">
			<Text>I am not afraid of an army of lions led by a sheep; I am afraid of an army of sheep led by a lion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ALEXANDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Alexander the Great is unquestionably one of the greatest warlords of all time. In 12 short years he marched his army to victory after victory across Europe, Asia, Africa and the Middle East, conquering every civilization he could reach, before dying at the age of 32. After his generals divided Alexander's empire amongst themselves, they were soon busy waging war against one another for more pieces of an ever-dwindling pie.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ALEXANDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Alexander III of Macedon was born in 356 BCE to King Philip II, an extremely successful leader who had restored his kingdom from the verge of extinction. Philip led his people to triumph by conquering Athens, Illyria, and Thrace—the three powers who, a few short years before, had been on the verge of conquering Macedon. As the son of the most powerful monarch in the “civilized” world, Alexander got the best of everything, including education. The scholar Aristotle, one of the Hellenistic period's greatest philosophers, was hired as a tutor for the young prince.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ALEXANDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Taught by his mother Olympias that he was descended from Hercules and Achilles, Alexander did not lack self-confidence, which is the polite way of saying his ego was bigger than the empire he would one day conquer. When Philip left him in charge of Macedon while he was away attacking Byzantion, a 14-year-old Alexander kept busy by crushing a Thracian rebellion, founding Alexandropolis, and settling it with Greeks—not the last time Alexander would name new cities after himself. Two years later he commanded the left wing of his father’s army during the battle at Chaeronea, in which Philip’s forces defeated the allied Greek states and subdued all of Greece.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ALEXANDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>The next year Alexander’s good fortune seemed to desert him. King Philip divorced Alexander’s mother and married Cleopatra Eurydice, leaving his ex-wife and son to flee Macedon. While Olympias sought refuge with her brother the king of Epirus, Alexander went into hiding in Illyria. Though father and son later reconciled, Alexander’s position as Philip’s heir was in grave jeopardy if Philip could produce another son. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ALEXANDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Following the conquest of Greece and the Balkans, King Philip raised an army to invade and conquer Persia. But in 336 BCE Philip was assassinated by the captain of his own bodyguard, Pausanias, while attending his daughter’s wedding. (Alexander’s mother, Olympias—or indeed Alexander himself—may have been behind the assassination, but as Pausanias conveniently died during the murder, there was no actual proof.) In 336 BCE, at the age of 20, Alexander was proclaimed king by the Macedonian army and nobility.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ALEXANDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>The young king celebrated his victory by murdering all potential rivals to the throne, then resumed planning his father’s invasion of Persia. Although he was briefly distracted until 334 BCE with several revolts in the Balkans, Alexander and his army crossed the Hellespont into Asia. His force consisted of about 48,000 foot soldiers and 6,000 cavalry, a huge army for the day, accompanied by engineers, surveyors, scientists, and even historians to record his successes for posterity. In battle Alexander had amazing success against the Persians, repeatedly beating their best generals, and routinely fighting against daunting odds.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ALEXANDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Alexander's accomplishments can be attributed to his military genius, to his soldiers' superb training and equipment, and to a magnificent esprit de corps, largely engendered by his army's faith in Alexander’s invincibility. This myth was so broadly believed because Alexander appeared to be charmed by the gods from whom he claimed a common lineage. He regularly led his elite “Companion Cavalry” into the thick of battle, and he received a number of dangerous wounds during his military career, none of which dampened his military ardor.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ALEXANDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Once he secured most of Persia's surrender, Alexander then moved south to conquer Syria, the coast of the Levant, and eventually Egypt. He returned to Persia, by way of conquering Babylon, and destroyed the last of the Persian forces at the battle of Gaugamela. Rather than pursue the Persian king Darius III who fled the field, Alexander seized the treasury at Susa. He then captured the ancient Persian capital of Persepolis, which he allowed his men to loot for several days. Alexander remained in the city for five months until it burned down … supposedly by accident.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ALEXANDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>With this, Alexander returned to the campaign, chasing Darius and his disintegrating army into Media, and then Parthia. There Darius was taken prisoner by his kinsman Bessus, who had Darius killed before he himself retreated into the mountains to conduct a guerrilla war against the Greeks. But Bessus was himself betrayed to the Greeks in 329 BCE, and the Greek general Ptolemy had him executed. Alexander, it seems, was too busy defeating a Scythian host at the battle of Jaxartes to bother with a regicide-friendly Persian noble. As for the Scythians, the leader Spitamenes was killed by his own tribe, which promptly sued for peace.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ALEXANDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>All this had taken Alexander’s slowly eroding army through Media, Parthia, Aria and Bactria (modern Afghanistan), Drangiana, and Scythia. Along the way, the young king married the Bactrian princess Roxana to help placate the eastern fringe of the old Persian Empire. But soon enough, Alexander determined to try his hand at conquering the Indian subcontinent, which rumors claimed was even richer than Persia. Eventually Alexander came into contact with the great Indian King Porus, who fought him to a standstill. Alexander won the conflict, but at such a heavy cost that his men begged him to end the campaign and let them return to their families.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ALEXANDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>Alexander himself went to rule his empire from the captured city of Babylon. Apparently he found this quite boring, for “when Alexander saw the breadth of his domain, he wept for there were no more worlds to conquer."</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ALEXANDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>Once back in Babylon, Alexander began an inexorable decline. Drinking heavily and engaging in all kinds of available debauchery (and there was much debauchery to be found in Babylon), he became subject to fits of anger and bouts of paranoia. In June of 323 BCE, his body weakened by his excesses, Alexander died.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ALEXANDER_CHAPTER_CAPSULE_BODY">
			<Text>Alexander's Macedon is the one civilization that is prepared to go to war and stay at war for the entire game.  With no war weariness, the ability to learn from captured culture, and the ability to heal when capturing wonders Alexander can keep moving forward on his quest to reach the world's end.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ALEXANDER_CHAPTER_DETAILED_BODY">
			<Text>Alexander's classical era military is one of the scariest opponents you can ever meet. With both the Hetairoi and Hypaspist unique units, Macedon is the rare civilzation that has two unique units active at the same time. If their units are trained at the Basilikoi Paides, Macedon advances in technology without having to expend the time on developing a campus. Further advancement comes in the field as they capture enemy cities with a Campus, Encampment, Holy Site or Theater Square.  And with no war weariness penalties and the ability to recover from combat damage when they capture a city with a wonder, Alexander's plan is to go to war and stay in conquest mode until the world is Macedonian.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>At its height, the Persian Empire encompassed most of Mesopotamia, Asia Minor, the shores of the Black Sea, some of Central Asia (what would one day become Afghanistan), parts of the Caucasus mountains, Egypt, Thrace, and Macedon. For nearly two centuries, Persia had mastered the “cradle of civilization”—until a Macedone upstart named Alexander crushed the world's greatest power in less than four years.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Just as notable as its ignominious collapse was its improbable start. According to several accounts (all of them suspect), it all began when a young Cyrus II couldn’t get along with his grandfather Astyages. To be fair, the old king did try to have Cyrus killed at birth … so when Cyrus proclaimed himself king of Persia in 546 BCE, his grandfather’s lands were first on the list of conquest. By roughly 540 BCE he overran Lydia and a year later marched in triumph to capture Babylon. He now ruled an empire that reached from the borders of Egypt to the shores of the Black Sea, encompassing all of ancient Mesopotamia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>By all accounts, Cyrus II—now known as "Cyrus the Great," or the “King of Kings”—was, for his time, an relatively enlightened ruler. His Persian Empire was the first in history to govern a slew of distinct ethnic groups on the basis of equitable responsibilities and rights for each, so long as his subjects paid their taxes and kept the peace. Cyrus established a system of local nobles called "satraps" to administer each province autonomously, and pledged not to interfere in the local customs, religions, and economies of the conquered peoples. He built fortresses along the eastern border to limit the depredations of barbarians from the steppes, such as the Scythians, who may (or may not) have been the cause of his untimely death in 530 BCE.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Cyrus was succeeded by his son Cambyses II, who promptly murdered his own brother Bardiya to ensure his rule would not be challenged. As was the style at the time, he followed fratricide with an invasion. Cambyses marched his armies to Egypt in 525 BCE, winning victories at Pelusium and Memphis, but his attacks on neighboring Carthage and Nubia did not fare as well. Nonetheless, Egypt and its wealth was a nice addition to the empire. In the midst of all this campaigning, Cambyses received word of a revolt against him led by his brother, Bardiya—the same one he had previously murdered. On the way home to make sure his brother's death took this time, Cambyses himself died under mysterious circumstances.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Coincidentally, a distant relative of Cambyses named Darius—one of the Persian generals with access to his king around the time of his death—claimed that Cambyses took his own life out of despair. Darius marched his troops to Media and killed Bardiya, who he labeled an imposter. Without a clear line of succession to dissuade him, Darius claimed the throne, leading several provinces to immediately revolt at his presumption. After 19 battles in a single year, Darius had put paid to most of these uprisings.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Tranquility returned to the empire. Darius was in firm enough control by 521 BCE that he reorganized the administration, made Aramaic the official language of the sprawling empire, and created a uniform monetary system based around the “daric,” because naming a coin after one's self was one of the perks of (presumed) usurpation. Under Darius, the Persian Empire also standardized weights and measures, instituted a program of road construction, such as the rebuilding and completion of the 1677-mile “Royal Road” from Susa to Sardis, and began lots of public works in the cities of Susa, Babylon, Memphis, Pasargadae and new Persepolis.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>By 516 BCE, he considered his rule stable enough to invade the distant Indus Valley, which he conquered within the year. After appointing the Greek Scylax to serve as his satrap from the city of Gandhara, Darius decided to reorganize the empire. He divided it into 20 provinces, each under a satrap he appointed (usually one of his relatives), and each paying a fixed rate of tribute. To prevent the satraps from building a power base to threaten rebellion, Darius appointed a separate military commander in each satrapy, answerable only to him. Imperial spies (known as “King’s ears”) kept tabs on both satrap and military commander, reporting back to Darius on a regular basis.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Having returned from India victorious, Darius (now known as “the Great”) turned his attention to the Scythians. The horse barbarians refused to engage in a pitched battle, but their constant withdrawals cost the Scythians their best pasture lands, scattered their herds, and lost them several allies. Still, the Persian infantry were suffering from fatigue and privation themselves after a month of marching into the wilderness. Darius, concerned that the fruitless campaign would only cost him more men, and convinced that Scythian fortunes had been damaged enough, halted his army on the banks of the Oarus. According to Herodotus he built “eight great forts, each some distance from each other." After declaring his stalemate a victory, he departed to seek far less mobile foes in Europe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>The expedition began with Darius crossing the Hellespont and getting involved in fractious Greek politics. This led to the invasion of Thrace, followed by the capture of several city-states in the northern Aegean. Macedon submitted voluntarily to Persia, becoming a vassal kingdom. Darius left his general Megabyzus to finish off Thrace while the king returned to relax at Sardis. But it wasn’t long until a number of Greek cities in Ionia revolted and, supported by Athens and Eretria, an Ionian force captured and burnt Sardis in 498 BCE—to the presumed irritation of Darius.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>With the “Ionian Revolt” finally and utterly crushed, Darius sent his son-in-law to reconquer Thrace and Macedon in 492 BCE, then dispatched an expedition to Greece to force Eretria and Athens to submit to his will. After island hopping across the Aegean, overwhelming Naxos on the way, the Persians besieged, captured and burnt Eretria in 490 BCE. They then marched south along the coast of Attica, looking to do the same to Athens, but were thoroughly defeated by 30,000 allied Greek soldiers at Marathon. Darius immediately began preparations for another invasion, this time planning to personally take command, but died three years into the effort.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>His successors—starting with his son Xerxes I—were left to deal with the upstart Greeks. And, despite ruling the greatest empire yet known to the world, they managed to bungle it.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>Xerxes first quelled a revolt in Egypt, but unlike his predecessors, Xerxes dealt harshly with the rebellious province by removing the local leaders and imposing direct Persian control on the citizens. He did the same to the Babylonians when they revolted in 482 BCE. Finally, Xerxes led a great army into northern Greece, supported by a powerful Persian navy. The city-states in his path fell to the invaders fairly easily, and despite a heroic stand of Spartans and Boeotians at Thermopylae, the Greeks were unable to stop Xerxes’s army from marching to Athens and sacking the most important city-state in Greece.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_13">
			<Text>However, the Athenians had evacuated their city before the Persians arrived, and their navy remained a potent force. Xerxes learned just how potent at the battle of Salamis in 480 BCE, when a Greek fleet of some 370 triremes soundly defeated 800 Persian galleys, destroying perhaps 300 Persian vessels at a cost of 40 Greek ships. This defeat delayed the planned Persian offensive further into Greece for a year, giving the Greeks time to strengthen their defenses against the invaders. Xerxes was forced to return to Persia, leaving his general Mardonius in command, and the Greeks promptly won several important naval and land battles against the new leader. With Mardonius's death in the battle of Plataea, the campaign was over and the surviving Persians withdrew from Greece in disorder.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_14">
			<Text>Xerxes never mounted another invasion of Greece, though this was more due to his assassination than a lack of interest. In 465 BCE he fell victim to a plot engineered by the commander of his own royal bodyguard, who was in turn was killed by Xerxes's son Artaxerxes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_15">
			<Text>Ruling from 465 BCE to 404 BCE, the three Persian kings who followed Xerxes I—Artaxerxes I, Xerxes II, and Darius II—were weak and uninspiring. At the end of the 5th Century BCE the Persians regained some power in the Aegean, successfully playing the Greeks against one-another during the long Peloponnesian War between Athens and Sparta. However, an Egyptian revolt in 405 BCE wrested the wayward province out of Persian control for more than 50 years.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_16">
			<Text>Darius II was succeeded by Artaxerxes II, who ruled for 45 years. During his long reign Artaxerxes II fought a war against Sparta, once again over the Greek colonies in Asia Minor. Persia allied with the Athenians (who were recovering from their disastrous defeat in the Peloponnesian War) and Sparta was forced to come to terms.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_17">
			<Text>Despite these occasional successes, Persian weakness and disorganization grew as the 4th Century BCE progressed. In 373 BCE a group of satraps revolted. They were put down, but other revolts followed, and with growing frequency. The position of king was increasingly unstable. Artaxerxes III came to the throne as a result of treachery in 359 BCE, and in an attempt to secure his position he promptly murdered as many of his relatives as he could find. In 338 BCE Artaxerxes III was poisoned at the orders of the eunuch Bagoas, who placed Artaxerxes's youngest son Arses in power. Arses promptly tried to kill Bagoas, but his effort failed and he himself was killed. Bagoas then elevated Darius III to the throne.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_18">
			<Text>A former satrap of Armenia, Darius III was only distantly related to the late king(s)—but nearly everybody else with a better claim was dead. It is difficult to tell if he was an effective leader, for the Persian Empire had been in decline for well over a century by the time he assumed the throne. Its many component parts were in near-constant revolt against the increasingly inept central government. Palace intrigue further crippled the monarchy, and leaders who wished to survive spent as much time watching their backs as they did looking out for the interests of the empire. Any leader who took power under those circumstances would be in trouble.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_19">
			<Text>However bad things were at home, they paled into insignificance with the troubles headed Darius’s way from across the Hellespont. In 336 BCE a young Macedone king named Alexander, later labelled “the Great,” sought to topple the tottering Persian Empire. Darius repeatedly met him in battle, often with far superior numbers, and Alexander simply destroyed his armies one after another. The Persian capital Persepolis fell to Alexander’s armies in 330 BCE, and Darius was murdered the same year. The last Achaemenid “King of Kings” had fallen. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CYRUS_QUOTE">
			<Text>Do not be distressed by the slurs of our enemies, nor enticed by the praise of our allies. Trust in yourselves or no one at all.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CYRUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Cyrus II, nigh legendary first king of Persia, nearly wasn’t. He was born to Cambyses, king of Anshan, and Mendane, daughter of King Astyages of Media, in either 600 BCE or 576 BCE. (Ancient calendars being what they were, subsequent historians aren’t quite sure which.) According to the tales, Astyages was convinced by repeated dreams that his grandson would someday overthrow him. Since power was thicker than blood for the Median king, he summoned his pregnant daughter and insisted the child be killed as soon as it was born. The task was delegated to a shepherd, Mithradates, who did not kill the infant Cyrus and instead raised him as one of his own sons. Herodotus claimed the ruse was uncovered when Cyrus reached the age of 10 because his behavior was “too noble.” Caring for neither a civil war nor conflict with Cambyses, Astyages sent Cyrus back to his biological parents in Persia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CYRUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Astyages was right to be concerned by his grandson. Although his father did not die until 551 BCE, Cyrus had already ascended to the throne in 559 BCE. Like his predecessors, Cyrus was forced to recognize Median overlordship … at least until a surprise attack against his grandfather in 553 BCE. Rallying the tribes—including the Achaemenian relations of his wife Cassandane—Cyrus defeated the Medians in several pitched battles, eventually capturing the capital at Ecbatana in 549 BCE. Accepting the crown of Media in 546 BCE, Cyrus proclaimed himself “King of Persia.” History doesn’t record what became of Astyages, but it is considerably less likely he was adopted by a shepherd tasked with his murder.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CYRUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The conquest of Media was only the start of Cyrus's bloodshed. Astyages had been allied to Nabonidus of Babylon, Amasis of Egypt, and his brother-in-law Croesus of Lydia. Within a year of Astyages’s defeat, the Lydians were on the march. Cyrus levied troops from throughout his lands and fought Lydian forces to stalemate at Pteira. He next attacked the Lydian capital at Sardis, where he routed the vaunted Lydian cavalry by putting camels in the front lines. According to Herodotus, Cyrus spared Croesus and made him a trusted advisor—but the 'Nabonidus Chronicle' disagreed, claiming Cyrus double-crossed the fallen king and had him slain.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CYRUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>After putting down a revolt in Media by the official transporting Croesus’s supposed vast treasury to Cyrus’s palace, the Persians proceeded to capture Elam’s capital on the way into Babylonia. Around early October 540 BCE, Cyrus finally forced the Babylonians to battle near their city of Opis on the banks of the Tigris, just north of Babylon. The Babylonians were routed, Nabonidus fled, and Cyrus negotiated a truce, thus entering Sippar unopposed. Reaching Babylon, Cyrus used an existing great ditch to divert the Euphrates and walk his troops across the riverbed. They invaded the city at night against meager defenders and "detained" Nabonidus. (The 'Nabonidus Chronicles' said he was exiled and allowed to live out his life in nearby Carmania, where Cyrus could keep an eye on him.)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CYRUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Having added fallen Babylonia to his now extensive holdings, Cyrus also acquired various pieces of its empire in Syria, Judea, and Patraea. Feeling quite pleased with himself, Cyrus proclaimed himself “King of Babylon, King of Sumer and Akkad, King of the Four Corners of the World.” This is known from the (in)famous “Cyrus Cylinder,” etched and laid in the foundations of the Esagila temple dedicated to Marduk, the primary Babylonian god. The cylinder denounces Nabonidus as impious and depicts Cyrus as “pleasing to Marduk.” It also details how Cyrus improved the lives of the Babylonians, restored temples and cults previously outlawed, and repatriated displaced peoples—such as his 538 BCE decree allowing captive Jews to return to Judah.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CYRUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Although some historians and other wishful thinkers have asserted that the cylinder represents an early form of human rights charter, most scholars portray it in the context of the long-standing Mesopotamian tradition of new rulers beginning their reign with declarations of largesse and reforms, especially after the fall of an unpopular king.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CYRUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Cyrus spent his last years putting the Achaemenid dynasty on a sound footing. To avoid unrest in newly conquered lands, he allowed most nobles to become government officials and gave them equal status with Persian nobility. He left the institutions in conquered lands alone, allowing the people to largely govern themselves, and didn’t meddle with local religions, which proved an exceedingly wise decision. Cyrus also built a series of fortified towns along the eastern borders to protect his empire from the nomads of Central Asia, and formed a streamlined central government at his capital at Pasargadae which administered the regions through local elders. In short, he successfully organized the vast territory he had conquered into something resembling an empire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CYRUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>The details of Cyrus's passing vary. According to Herodotus (whose tales are largely just that), a backstabbing Cyrus met his fate at the hands of the warrior-queen Tomyris of the Scythians. (That theory of his death is recounted in Tomyris's Civilopedia entry.) Ctesias, even less reliable than Herodotus, wrote in his 'Persica' that Cyrus was killed while putting down resistance from the Derbices. Berossus claims the Persian king met his death while fighting against Dahae archers northwest of the headwaters of Syr Darya. A final alternative is that from Xenophon’s Cyropaedia, which says that Cyrus died peacefully resting at his capital. Whatever the case, Cyrus’s remains were interred in a limestone tomb in Pasargadae (which tends to give credence to Xenophon’s account), which many believe still exists in the ruins of that great city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CYRUS_CHAPTER_CAPSULE_BODY">
			<Text>Cyrus looks for juicy opportunities to expand his empire with quick strike surprise wars. Once captured, this new territory can be rapidly integrated into the Persian network of cities connected by a highly efficient road network.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CYRUS_CHAPTER_DETAILED_BODY">
			<Text>Persia is at its strongest when it can build a tightly consolidated empire. Their bonuses to internal [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Routes make such an empire lucrative. Their Immortal unit and enhanced road network allow them to rapidly deploy effective defense forces against any threat. With [ICON_Culture] Culture bonuses from internal trade and the Pairidaeza, the Persians should be at or near the lead in civics in most games. It is only when Cyrus needs to expand this empire that he wants to strike outside this shell. Given his bonuses in surprise wars, watch out if you are bordering Persia!</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_MACEDONIAN_HYPASPIST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Among the Greeks, a hypaspist (or “shield bearer”) was a lightly-armored soldier who possessed great flexibility on the battlefield. Philip II of Macedon turned them into legends. The Macedonian phalanx, while very nearly impregnable, was most vulnerable at its flanks and in its rear. Though the hetairoi (or “Companions”) could help protect against such attacks, their essential role as shock cavalry meant they were best used in a more offensive role.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_MACEDONIAN_HYPASPIST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Thus, the hypaspistai. With a solid round shield, linen armor, and a short spear, the hypaspistai could rapidly maneuver to protect against attacks from infantry or cavalry. In turn, the hetairoi would protect the hypaspistai, providing progressively flexible flanks around an exceptionally spiky and slow-turning center. Philip’s elevation of the hypaspistai stressed the importance of maintaining the phalanx, and in turn provided an elite unit for young soldiers of Macedon to aspire. His son Alexander the Great would continue Philip’s tradition.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_MACEDONIAN_HETAIROI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The powerful hetairoi (known simply as “the Companions”) were an elite cavalry unit who served as the hammer in Macedon’s famed hammer-and-anvil tactics, popularized under Philip II and used to great effect by his son, Alexander the Great. While the Macedonian phalanx pinned a rival army in place with their extra-long spears (known as sarissas), the hetairoi would organize into a wedge and charge directly into the enemy flanks or rear.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_MACEDONIAN_HETAIROI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>An abrupt attack by the shock cavalry nearly impossible to avoid or deter, and was often enough to break the will of less seasoned troops. As they fled for their lives, they were easy pickings for the hetairoi who could ride them down and dispatch them in their leisure.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_MACEDONIAN_HETAIROI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Most of the Companions came from the ranks of Macedon’s noble families, though the king could technically admit anyone to their ranks. They were armed with short spears and swords.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_PERSIAN_IMMORTAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The elite heavy infantry of the ancient Persian Empire has a fearsome reputation, but much that is known of them comes from the writings of Herodotus, whose accounts were widely read but not necessarily accurate. For example, the very name by which they are known—the Immortals—was of Greek origin, not Persian.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_PERSIAN_IMMORTAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>According to Herodotus, they were said to maintain a force of exactly 10,000 soldiers who, upon injury or death, were immediately replaced so they would never be anything less than full strength. As elite troops they were afforded special luxuries, such as their own food kept separately from the rest of the army. Their clothes were vibrant, covering coats made of armored metal scales, and they carried a variety of armaments such as short spears, swords, and powerful bows. Whatever their actual disposition, they were respected (and feared) by their contemporaries.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_BASILIKOI_PAIDES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The basilikoi paides (roughly “royal page school”) was a long-held tradition in Macedon, but Philip II transformed it into a powerful tool to advance the needs of both king and state. Macedon’s noble sons, as well as those the king deemed worthy, were admitted to the basilikoi paides—a prestigious manner of dealing with royal hostages. Philip spared no expense in hiring the finest tutors, including renowned philosopher Aristotle, who likened the basilikoi paides to a “school for generals.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_BASILIKOI_PAIDES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Indeed, beyond the arts of war and administration, the young pages were taught to honor and obey the king, to protect him with their lives, and to serve Macedon’s interests above all others. This helped forge national bonds that superseded familial ties, in turn reducing chances of rebellion among the nobility. Graduates were afforded a position of prominence within the hetairoi (Companion cavalry). Alexander continued the tradition after his father’s death.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_APADANA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Though an apadana was a specific style of ancient construction, the Apadana at Persepolis most typified the style. Dozens of columns supported a wooden roof, all built atop an elevated stone surface accessible by large staircases. The structure was open to the elements, though temporary “rooms” could be created by hanging cloth between columns.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_APADANA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Darius the Great began construction of the Apadana at Persepolis, and Xerxes I completed it. The dynasty’s accomplishments were literally carved into the wall, whether text declarations or reliefs depicting the splendor and majesty of the Persian kings. Unfortunately for the Achaemenids, the Apadana was mostly destroyed by Alexander the Great’s forces during his Persian conquests. Some of its columns remain standing in the modern day.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_HALICARNASSUS_MAUSOLEUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Persian satrap Mausolus had a tomb built for himself that was so lavish and beautiful that the term “mausoleum” would subsequently be used for any stately tomb. Planned before his death in the city of Halicarnassus, a coastal town on the shores of what is now western Turkey, it was completed after his death in 353 BCE. Many writings from antiquity mention the Mausoleum’s beauty, and it was declared one of the seven wonders of the ancient world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_HALICARNASSUS_MAUSOLEUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Artemisia, widow to Mausolus, hired famous sculptors to work the stone and marble, and its sides were emblazoned with bas-reliefs of mythical creatures. Atop a pyramidal roof, supported by columns and solid stone, was a bronze chariot bearing depictions of Mausolus and Artemisia, together in death for eternity—or the early 15th Century, when the whole thing was toppled by earthquakes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_PAIRIDAEZA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A pairidaeza is a specific style of garden consisting of cultivated land within an enclosure. Also known as a “paradise garden,” the pairidaeza is thought to originate in the time of the Assyrian Empire. Its rectangular construction serves to contrast the external wildness of nature with an ordered and beautiful garden. Water was often an important element of their construction—ponds, canals, or even fountains flowed freely within the walls.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_PAIRIDAEZA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As a tool of state, they were invaluable in flaunting a kingdom’s ability to bring life to an area that would otherwise have none. The Achaemenid dynasty melded the pairidaeza with their royal hunting parks, a not so subtle way to show their command over both their empire and the natural world within it.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_BUILDING_HALICARNASSUS_MAUSOLEUM_QUOTE">
			<Text>“A vast tomb lies over me in Halicarnassus, of such dimensions, of such exquisite beauty as no other shade can boast.”[NEWLINE]– Lucian of Samosata</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_BUILDING_APADANA_QUOTE">
			<Text>“My ancestor Darius made this Apadana, but it was burnt down. By the grace of Ahuramazda, Anahita, and Mithra, I reconstructed this Apadana.”[NEWLINE]– Artaxerxes II</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</GameData>
