<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<GameData xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<LocalizedText>
		<!-- Delete existing text entries-->
		<Delete Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRESLAV_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1"/>
		<Delete Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_ILKUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1"/>
		<Delete Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_MEDINA_QUARTER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1"/>
		<Delete Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_PIOPIOTAHI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1"/>

		<Update>
			<Where Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MEDIEVAL_FAIRES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1" />
			<Set Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MEDIEVAL_FAIRES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1" />
		</Update>
		<Update>
			<Where Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MEDIEVAL_FAIRES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2" />
			<Set Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MEDIEVAL_FAIRES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2" />
		</Update>
		<Update>
			<Where Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MEDIEVAL_FAIRES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3" />
			<Set Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MEDIEVAL_FAIRES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3" />
		</Update>
	
	
		<!-- Add text-->
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CNUT_TITLE">
			<Text>Canute</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CNUT_SUBTITLE">
			<Text>King of Denmark</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CNUT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Canute – also known as Cnut, Knut, Knud, and various other variants depending on the historian – would at times serve as king of Denmark, Norway, England, and even bits of Sweden. All of that when the borders were somewhat fluid, of course. He was a power in the shifting fortunes of northern Europe in the 11th Century AD, treated with deference by both the Emperor and the Pope.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CNUT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>No one is quite sure when and where he was born exactly, but it is certain that he was the son of Sweyn Forkbeard, the King of Denmark, for Canute accompanied the old warrior during the 1013 invasion of England. Left behind in Lincolnshire in charge of the fleet, he took up with Aelfgifu, who would bear him two sons. Sweyn was accepted as king of England but died in 1014 and the Brits brought back Aethelred to be their king. Within the year, Canute returned to challenge Aethelred’s son for the throne. By the end of November 1016 it was all over, and Canute ruled the whole of England. He then spent most of the rest of his life (dying in 1035) dealing with threats to his Danish crown, usually using English troops to do so.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_OLOF_TITLE">
			<Text>Olof Skötkonung</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_OLOF_SUBTITLE">
			<Text>King of Sweden</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_OLOF_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Olof III – born Olof Eiriksson (son of Erik VII Bjornsson, “king” of the Svear, better known today as Sweden) and occasionally known as Olof Skotkonung – spent the best years of his life fighting King Tryggvason of Norway. Gaining the throne of Sweden in 993 AD, what historians know of Olof is based on the accounts of Snorri Sturluson and Adam of Bremen.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_OLOF_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>According to Adam, Sweyn Forkbeard was forced to defend his Danish throne from Olof’s claims, but that squabble was resolved soon enough when Sweyn married Olof’s mother, Sigrid “the Haughty.” Besides, according to Snorri, they both soon made common cause to defeat the Norwegian king Olav Tryggvason at the naval battle of Svolder in either 999 or 1000 (Snorri not being so certain of the year, but did know the month was September). Sweyn and Olof thereafter divided Norway between themselves.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_OLOF_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>His efforts to bring the other Swedes to the light did not go quite as well. Converted to Christianity by St. Sigfrid c. 1008, Olof attempted to force the new faith on his subjects. It didn’t go so well, according to Adam, as he was martyred in Stockholm by rebel jarls c. 1021 when he refused to make a sacrifice to pagan idols.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AL_HAKAM_II_TITLE">
			<Text>Al-Hakam II</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AL_HAKAM_II_SUBTITLE">
			<Text>Caliph of Al-Andalus</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AL_HAKAM_II_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Second Umayyad caliph of al-Andalus, son of the great Abd al-Rahman III, born in November 915 AD in the great city of Cordoba, died in that same great city in October 976, his great reign represented the greatest period in the caliphate; under his personal patronage, Moorish arts and science reached a golden age in al-Andalus.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AL_HAKAM_II_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Al-Hakam II sought to improve his people’s lot, despite the Christians battering at the door. Already a rich kingdom, al-Hakam sponsored irrigation projects to boost agricultural output, widened streets in his towns, and ordered the building of more markets. He assembled a great personal library for use by scholars invited from across both Muslim and Christian lands, supposedly as large as 600 thousand books (more than one historian disputes this, many pegging the figure at a only 400 thousand). Construction projects included the expansion of the mosque in Cordoba and the completion of the royal residence Medina Azahara.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AL_HAKAM_II_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>But it wasn’t all peaceful; early in his reign al-Hakam waged a successful war against the invading Christian kings of Navarre and of Castile and León. His naval forces defeated sea raiders and Norman pirates. And in 973 his forces took Tangier from the last Idrisids, thereby annexing Morocco just before al-Hakam’s death.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_BASIL_II_TITLE">
			<Text>Basil II</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_BASIL_II_SUBTITLE">
			<Text>Emperor of Byzantium</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_BASIL_II_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Basil II – also known as Basil Porphyrogenita (“born in the purple”) and Basil Bulogaroctonus (“slayer of the Bulgars”) – was born eldest son to the Byzantine emperor Romanos II in 958 AD, and himself reigned as emperor from 976 to 1025. The early years of his reign were dominated by a lengthy civil war. Basil turned to Vladimir of the Viking settlement in Kiev for assistance, and Vladimir was rewarded with the hand of Basil’s sister Anna (on the condition that he adopt Christianity). After the fighting died down, many of the Northmen  remained in Byzantine service, forming the initial cadre of the famed Varangian Guards.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_BASIL_II_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>After his victory in the civil war, around 989, the rest of his reign was marked by a state of near-constant war. Basil II aimed to extend and consolidate his holdings, building a buffer around the tottering empire. The sometime theaters of this were in Syria, Armenia and Georgia to the east. He is, however, best known for his persistent and victorious campaigns against the revived kingdom of Bulgaria under its last tsar Samuel. With the fall of its capital Ochrida, Bulgaria was incorporated into the empire. At Basil’s death, he was overseeing preparations for the Byzantine reconquest of Sicily.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_TITLE">
			<Text>Charlemagne</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_SUBTITLE">
			<Text>King of Francia</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Charles I – Charlemagne – is one of the great figures of medieval history, chivalry, and civilization itself. By the time he died in January 814 AD, he ruled most of what is now France, Germany, the Low Countries, Italy, and bits of Iberia and East Europe. He became “joint” king of the Franks with his brother Carloman I upon the death of their father, Pepin the Short in 768, but in 771, Carloman died under “unexplained” circumstances.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In 774, at Pope Adrian’s behest, Charlemagne stomped the Lombard king Desiderous and thus became king of his extensive holdings that year. Engaged in fighting Saxons, in 776 he rushed back to north Italy to defeat the rebellious dukes of Spoleto and Fruili. Meanwhile, his campaigns against the Saxons dragged on for some 30 years, marked by submission and then insurrection in a cycle that didn’t end until 804. With the collapse of the Saxon kingdoms, Bavaria submitted to Charlemagne’s rule in 794.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Interspersed with all this, Charles (now being called “the Great”) periodically fought the pagan Avars, who had decided to settle in Hungary; leading a great force, he finally forced the Avars to accept him (and Christianity) as their new ruler. And he drove the Moors back in Iberia, pushing south to the banks of the Ebro by 811. For all this “Lord’s work,” Charlemagne was made Holy Roman Emperor on Christmas Day in 800 AD by Pope Leo III.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_DENMARK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Beginning in the late 8th Century AD, each spring the Viking lords of Denmark would conduct raids across the North Sea and down past the English Channel; the famed Viking raid on the Christian monastery of Lindisfarne would serve to herald the “Viking Age.” So pervasive and feared were these incursions that some small kingdoms along the European coasts would make increasing larger payments – known as “Danegeld” – just to be left alone. A sort of annual ransom that helped fund the development of Denmark for decades.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_DENMARK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Old King Gorm (he was known as “Gorm the Old”) laid the foundations for the creation of the kingdom by unifying many of the Danish Vikings c. 936, ruling until his death in 958. He would be followed by Harald Bluetooth, Canute the Great, and Sweyn Forkbeard. Thanks primarily to the efforts of Sweyn II, Christianity took hold among the Vikings; during his 27-year reign, churches were constructed all over Denmark and he sponsored efforts to force kids to learn Latin. During his lifetime, the prolific old king fathered over 20 children himself, such that his heirs would rule Denmark for the following 60 years … guiding Denmark into the mainstream of medieval European culture and affairs.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SWEDEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>While their Danish counterparts were best known for raids in England and France, and the Norwegians were wandering about the North Atlantic, the Vikings of Sweden sailed across the Baltic Sea and along the river inlets into the Russian frontier. Throughout the “Viking Age” they were well known for their far-reaching trade routes, reaching deep inland, even unto fabled Byzantium.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SWEDEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Moving into Russia, Belarus, and Ukraine down the Volga during the 9th Century AD, many of the Swedish Vikings settled in these eastern lands, where they came to be known as the Rus. After capturing the city of Kiev in c. 850, the Rus formed a state that survived for nearly 400 years (until the arrival of the Mongols).</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SWEDEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Throughout the first millennium, Sweden itself was a loose collaboration of independent provinces. Although a number of early kings are mentioned in various Norse sagas, attempting to separate legend from factual history leaves their lineage and succession still somewhat muddled. Olof Skotkonung, son of Eric the Victorious, ruled from 995 until 1022, and is considered the first to truly unite the Swedish tribes, ruling over both Svealand and Gotaland.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AL_ANDALUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In April 711 AD, the Berber commander Tariq ibn-Zivad, on the orders of the Umayyad Caliph al-Wadi I, landed a small force at Gibraltar across the straits from the Muslim lands. After decisively defeating the Visigoth king Roderic, the Moors would overrun most of Iberia. Thus began al-Andalus, initially part of the expanding Umayyad empire. But in 756 the exiled Umayyad prince Abd al-Rahman I ousted the governor of al-Andalus and installed himself as the emir of the realm, with his capital at Cordoba.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AL_ANDALUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>After some decades of decline, the great Abd al-Rahman III, who took power in 912, not only rapidly restored the kingdom’s fortunes and prestige, but extended it through conquest. In 929 he proclaimed himself “caliph,” elevating al-Andalus to among the greatest kingdoms of Islam. His son al-Hakam II elevated it even further. Dominating the trade routes into the Mediterranean, the kingdom entered a golden age of cultural and scientific advances, as well as expanding into North Africa with the capture of Tangier.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AL_ANDALUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>But the Cordoba caliphate collapsed during a ruinous civil war that raged from 1009 through 1013. Although it stumbled along until 1031, al-Andalus devolved into a welter of small kingdoms and cities. Thus giving impetus to the efforts of those Christian kingdoms to drive the Moors out – the Reconquista.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BYZANTIUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Under the Macedonian dynasty (867 to 1057 AD), the Byzantine Empire – heir to the power of Rome and culture of Greece – reached its greatest height of expanse and influence, recovering from a couple centuries of decline. Commencing with Basil I, a number of competent leaders managed victories over the Arabs and the Bulgars, regaining lost territories in Syria and the Balkans. These successes were matched with economic growth, and a flowering of the arts, sciences, and religion. All that thinking about religion by the patriarchs of the land led, it appears, to the “Great Schism” … the break in communion between the Eastern Orthodox and Roman Catholic faiths in 1054.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BYZANTIUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Byzantine leaders, commencing in 850, developed the proverbial love-hate relationship with the Viking kingdom of Kiev to the north. The empire quickly became the major trading partner to Kiev, swapping luxury goods for the raw materials so plentiful in the interior north of the Black Sea. After “Christianizing” the Rus, Vladimir of Kiev brought in Byzantine architects and artists to work on all manner of religious projects. Over the next couple centuries, the Kievan and Byzantine imperial families intermarried frequently, and Byzantium made liberal use of the fierce Viking warriors, employing them as mercenaries (notably, in the famed Varangian Guard). But relations were not always so cordial, for several times Viking or Rus raiders attacked Byzantine settlements over the decades.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_FRANCIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once the Romans gave up trying to govern the Gauls, a number of Frankish kingdoms rose during the early Dark Ages, most of these lasting but a couple generations. Finally, the medieval Kingdom of Francia emerged, founded by Clovis I, crowned king of the Franks in 496 AD. Thanks to the near continuous campaigns of the next few generations – culminating in the rule of Charlemagne – West Francia was well-established and secure by the early 9th Century. Following the death of Louis the Pious in 840, however, the whole thing got divvied up between his three sons.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_FRANCIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Just in time for the Danish Vikings to begin raiding the coastlines, culminating with the sack of Paris in 845 … withdrawing only after they were bought off with 7000 livres of gold and silver by Charles the Bald, king of West Francia. They would return several more times for plunder and ransom, until finally, in the winter of 885, the city walls would hold.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_FRANCIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>With the death of the last Carolingian king, to avoid the bloodshed of a dynastic civil war in the face of the Viking threat, the Archbishop of Reims convened the great lords of Francia to elect a new ruler. Duke Hugh Capet of the demesne Ile-de-France was eventually chosen as king, and crowned in July 987. At one stroke, modern France was created just as the Viking threat subsided.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_FRANKISH_CABALLARII_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The vast majority of the Frankish troops during the Carolingian dynasty were simply infantry spearmen – the Franks having long before abandoned their traditional 'francisca' throwing ax – but the king did maintain an elite mounted contingent of heavy cavalry… the famed caballarius. Initially these caballarii were housed in or near the palace, but in time spread among the greater landed magnates as well. Whereas most of the troops were merely levies called up in time of war, the caballarius were “professionals,” and even provided temporary leaders for the less well-trained Frankish units. Divided into 'scara' (non-standardized regiments), the caballarii of Charlemagne seem to have been divided into three ranks of prestige, with the 'scholares' being the king’s personal bodyguard. The caballarii could, it seems, be used as true shock troops when mounted, or could dismount and fight on foot. And proved quite effective in either case.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_MOORISH_FARFANES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The use of mercenaries was quite accepted in the medieval world, and the Muslim states employed a wide variety. The Moorish caliphs of al-Andalus in particular used farfanes – mercenaries from the opposing Iberian Christian kingdoms – fighting in European fashion in dense formations, both mounted and afoot. The reasons for these Christian soldiers to fight under the banners of Islam were many. In some cases, as with the famed El Cid, it may have been because they had been banished or exiled from their homelands. Others may have been recent converts to Islam from among conquered peoples, or Christian slaves or prisoners-of-war promised freedom for service. Whatever the reason, the farfanes came to be feared among the Moors’ many enemies… and were well paid.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_HUSCARL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The huscarls (or “housecarls”) were elite soldiers, first raised as a military force by Canute; he modelled them on the quasi-mythical Scandinavian warrior-brotherhood known as Jomsvikings. Indeed, supposedly the original formation of huscarls were built around a nucleus of Jomsvikings that had come to England under famed Thorkell. Supported by a special tax, Canute maintained three “corps” (totaling 3000-4000 men) – two near London and the third near York. Armed with the usual collection of weapons and armor, the huscarls were especially adept at the “shield wall” tactic, which demanded both discipline and fortitude. Canute and other Viking rulers usually placed their huscarls in the center of the line to steady the rest of the army, or spread them along the entire front to take the initial enemy assault. Their exploits in battle were the stuff of legend; for instance, the huscarls formed the iron core of Godwinson’s army at Stamford Bridge and at Hastings.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_APUOLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A tiny village even now (the Lithuanian census of 2011 lists only 119 residents), in the early medieval years Apuolé was a hill fort of the Curonians, a tiny Baltic tribe. The chronicles of Rimbert describe how in 854 AD the Curonians refused to pay their annual tribute to the Swedish Vikings to be left in peace. The fortress was first assaulted by Danish Vikings looking to replace the Swedes as recipients of said unspecified tribute. The locals defeated the Danish force, gaining much loot. After hearing of the Danish repulse, King Olof of Sweden gathered a great fleet and descended on the Curonians. According to Rimbert, the 15000 tribemen there held out for eight days before surrendering. Supposedly the Curonian chieftain paid a silver ransom for each man in the fortress, pledged his loyalty to Olof, and gave 30 hostages to guarantee future payments.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ARLES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Reaching its peak in the last stages of the Roman Empire – in 395 AD it was the seat of the Praetorian Prefecture of Gaul, and the Emperor Constantine I had baths built there – the city of Arles lay on the Rhone in the province of Gallia Narbonensis. But from the 5th through the 8th centuries it was repeatedly devastated by invasions and raids of Visigoths, Saracens, and even barbarians from the north. Finally, in 739 Charles Martel brought Provence to heel and Arles began a resurgence. In 855, the city became the capital of the Kingdom of Arles. Then in 933, Hugh of Arles gave up his kingdom to Rudolph II, who merged it with holdings in Burgundy; finally, upon the death of the last of Rudolph’s descendants, the kingdom was inherited by the Salic Emperor Conrad II. Thus began a slow process of absorption into France, until by the 1600s the kingdom was no more.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ASILAH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Having once been the site of a Phoenician port, the settlement of Asilah was established by the Idrisids at some point in the 8th Century AD as a fortress to protect coastal trade. Around 860 Bjorn Ironside and his brother (or perhaps half-brother) Hastein led a fleet of 62 longships from the Viking settlement on the Loire to raid the Mediterranean coasts. The voyage did not go well at first, with the fleet being defeated first by the Asturians, and then by the forces of the Caliphate of Cordoba. But the Vikings' looting was successful once they descended upon the town of Algeciras, and again when they reached Africa to ravage the coastal towns of the Idrisid caliphate and Umayyad towns on the Balearic Islands. While Asilah may have been spared (historians are uncertain), several attacks by Normans from Sicily during the 10th Century nearly eliminated what remained of the fortress town.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BALARM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The city now known as Palermo has been renamed by every conqueror, and it has had many. Founded c. 730 BC by the Phoenicians as Zis, it became a possession of Carthage, then Rome, then Vandals, then Ostrogoths, and then Byzantium. When the Muslims took the island in 904 AD after fierce fighting, the Arabs renamed the town Balarm, and made it the capital of the Emirate of Sicily. Over the course of the next decades, Balarm blossomed, until – it was said – it could compete with Cordoba and Cairo in influence and splendor. Under the  rule of the Fatimid caliphs, the flourishing port became a center of trade (mostly agricultural … the Muslims introduced oranges, lemons, pistachios, and sugarcane) and culture. But after dynastic quarrels among the Muslims, Sicily was overrun by Christian mercenaries, including the Norman Robert Guiscard, in 1072.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_DUMBARTON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The key to Dumbarton’s history – at least, according to local historians – is the double pointed plug of volcanic rock sticking up over the countryside. As early as the Iron Age, its strategic location was recognized. The first documented evidence of a settlement at Dumbarton is a letter St. Patrick wrote to Ceretic, king of Strathcylde and Alcluith c. 450 AD. For the next few centuries, the history of the town is unclear. However, by 870 Dumbarton Rock was a nice little British fortress and settlement, seemingly prosperous and peaceful. But then the Vikings arrived, a force under Ivar Beinlaus en route from sacking York; Olaf the White joined him from Ireland. Together they besieged the town for 15 weeks, before finally storming it, burning it, and carrying off everything not nailed down – including the survivors – in a fleet of 200 longships back to Ireland.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_GIJON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A non-descript place lying on the north coast of Iberia lay Gijon. Indeed, at various times the town has been abandoned, notably in the 9th Century AD when a Norman fleet docked there and declared the place 'civitas deserta.' Previously, various barbarian settlements had left no trace either; by the 7th Century, the Visigoth king Susebut had supplanted the rather tenuous Roman hold. Gijon was, for about a century, capital of the Muslim territories along the Cantabric Sea, until 722 when Pelagius won the battle of Covadonga to become the first king of Asturias. Until 1270 AD, the town is not mentioned again in any records; in that year, it seems that Alfonso X granted it its “Carta Pueblo.” Between the battle and the carta, the only mentions of Gijon are in a couple Danish sagas.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KAIROUAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Founded by the Umayyad caliph Mu’awiya around 670 AD, Kairouan – located on the north coast of Africa – would become one of Sunni Islam’s most important centers of scholarship and education, its university attracting scholars from across the Arabic world. Thus, its fame spread even to Northern Europe – although tales of its wealth were greatly overblown. Following the mass conversion of the Berbers by the Prophet’s words, they captured Kairouan with its luxurious gardens and expansive olive groves in 745. Power struggles saw various rulers, some benevolent and some less so. In the reign of Imam Sahnun and Asad ibn al-Furat, palaces, fortifications and waterworks were built, making the town ever more famous. Envoys from the courts of Charlemagne and the Holy Roman Empire returned with fabulous tales of Kairouan’s great gardens and libraries. With the rise of the Fatimid dynasty c. 909, however, the town lost its importance and influence as the new rulers transferred their capital elsewhere more defensible.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PAMPLONA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Located in the middle of the foothills of the Pyrenees, in a rounded valley in Navarre, Pamplona alternated between self-rule, Visigoth domination, and Frankish suzerainty throughout the 9th Century. Expanding and contracting in cycles as well, the ruler of the Kingdom of Pamplona, Garcia Iniguez, allied his land with Christian Asturias to fend off the Moorish threat. It didn't do him much good against the Vikings, however, who captured the king in 859 (or so) and returned him only for a hefty ransom (according to legend, some 70 thousand gold dinars). The historian Ann Christys makes a strong case, however, that this whole episode is unsupported by records and probably apocryphal. As for Pamplona, the kingdom was eventually saved for Christianity when the freed king Garcia and his new friend Ordono I of Asturias together defeated Musa ibn Musa and a Cordoban army at the battle of Albelda.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PISA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>During the last years of the empire, Pisa did not suffer the decline of civilization quite as much as other Roman cities. Indeed, by the mid-700s the town was on its way to being a thriving port and a major trading center. Then came the Vikings Bjorn Ironside and Hastein, who had been raiding the Mediterranean Muslim towns and now set their sights on a few Christian ones. After pillaging the south of France and wintering there, they descended on unprotected Pisa, capturing and sacking it in 861 AD. Proceeding inland, the horde took the walled town of Luni, which according to legend the ignorant savages believed to be Rome, by ruse. With the surviving Norse warriors fretful, and since the leaders had always declared Rome the final target, they sailed back to the straits at Gibraltar … where they suffered heavy losses (some 40 ships and crews) in a naval battle with the Saracen navy from al-Andalus. Pisa was rebuilt, and never again troubled by Vikings.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRESLAV_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A minor Slavic settlement, Preslav began its rise in status when it was fortified in the early 9th Century AD; and its proximity to the Bulgarian capital of Pliska led to its expansion and prosperity under the khans Krum and Omurtag. Moreover, when the Bulgars converted to Christianity in 864, a number of churches and monasteries were built in and around the town walls. Being an important strategic and religious center, however, proved Preslav’s undoing. In the 960s and for several decades thereafter, the wars between the Byzantines and the Kievan Rus saw it ravaged and burnt several times. The cycle of conquerors looted the treasury, carried off the crown regalia, and even stole a large part of the famed library of Simeon. The outskirts and monasteries were largely abandoned. Although it regained some significance during the Second Bulgarian Empire, it soon after slipped even further into the shadows.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ROME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The story of the Eternal City during the Viking Age is mostly the story of the creation and early decades of the Papal States. It remained a cultural center, and one could even spot the occasional Dane or Rus wandering about viewing the sights. Since Bjorn and Hastein managed to sack the wrong town – they thought the walled city of Luni to be Rome – the Romans never had to suffer the wrath of the Norsemen. Other than that, the primary interaction between Rome and the Vikings was the persistent efforts of various pontiffs to convert them to the “True Church."</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_TAMWORTH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Kingdom of Mercia was created in the early 600s AD, with Tamworth as the “royal center” under its first recorded king, Penda. By the reign of King Offa, it was the official capital of England’s central and largest kingdom. But its size and location didn’t help much when the Danish Vikings showed up. In 868 Viking invaders, looking to stay awhile, occupied the vital Mercian town of Nottingham. As part of the Danes’ campaign to drive the king of Mercia (one Burgred) out, the Vikings sacked Tamworth in 874. The place remained a ruin until 913, when Aethellaed – the so-called “Lady of the Mercians” – had it rebuilt and made it her principle residence. In 926, Tamworth Church served as site for the marriage of King Aethelstan’s sister to Sitric Caech, the Norse king of Dublin and Northumbria. In 1016 Mercia, its days of glory well past, was given over to Cnut.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_THETFORD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Thetford was settled around an important crossing on the Little Ouse river sometime before the Iron Age; in its heyday, Thetford was the Saxon capital of East Anglia … at least until November 869 when Edmund “the Martyr,” last native king of the Angles, managed to get himself and most of his army killed by a Viking host under the command of Ivar the Boneless and his brother Ubba. The town then fell into the Danelaw, that part of England under Viking rule. But it wasn’t all bad for the town, for under the Vikings it prospered through the 900s, lying as it did on a navigable river at a broad ford. Its location made it a center of trade and craftsmanship (especially pottery production). But Sweyn Fordbeard’s campaigns against the Vikings and English led to him sacking it in 1004 and again in 1010. With Sweyn crowned king of England in 1013, peace returned.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_TMUTARAKAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Tmutarakan was a principality of the Kievan Rus, a preeminent trading center lying on the Crimean passage between the Black Sea and the Sea of Azov. Although the Khazar had built a “great” fortress there in the 7th Century AD, by the late 10th it was controlled by the Rus – although the exact date and circumstances of Tmutarakan’s acquisition are unknown. An international emporium of trade in every commodity from spices to slaves, it was one of the towns given to his sons by Vladimir the Great before his death in 1015. After Vlad’s son Mstislav passed on, Tmutarakan was ruled by a succession of short-lived petty tyrants. It was even claimed by Byzantium for a time. But finally, in 1083, Oleg Svyatoslavich returned the town to the Rus, and it in turn returned to its primary pursuit … making a profit.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VENICE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Lying in a swampy lagoon between the mouths of the Po and Piave rivers, no exact date is known for the founding of Venice, but some archeological evidence shows that the city's original citizens may have been Roman refugees fleeing the Germanic invasions and the Huns. As the centuries passed, the originally small settlement began to spread across the 118 islands therein, its inhabitants using the small rivulets and canals as their roads. In the late 700s AD, the ducal seat was moved to Venice and a basilica dedicated to St. Mark the Evangelist was built, heralding the birth of the “Queen of the Adriatic.” During the Middle Ages, the city flourished as a trading center between Europe and the rest of the world, its strategic location making its commercial and naval power unmatched in the Adriatic.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_WINCHESTER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Shortly after the Romans arrived, it seems the Belgae tribe in the region of the hill fort that would become Winchester welcomed the invaders with open arms. The Roman town became an important market and military center, remaining so even after the Romans withdrew. When eventually Alfred the Great became ruler of the West Saxons after he defeated the Danish Viking horde at Ashdown, he made Winchester the capital of a reborn Wessex in 871 AD. Almost immediately he set about shoring up the kingdom’s defenses against the next Danish incursion. In Winchester this meant urban renewal of a sorts, as he strengthened the walls and laid out the streets on a grid pattern to help the troops move about in it. He also organized the local militia into a “rapid reaction force.” Following the battle at Hastings, King Harold’s widow, sheltering at Winchester, surrendered the fortified town without a fight to the Normans.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_WOLIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Wolin is a Baltic island just off the coast of Pomerania where the rivers Swina and Dziwna empty into the sea. The ford to the island across the Dziwna meant it was settled as far back as history reaches. At some point in the 9th Century AD it was filled seemingly by a mixture of Scandinavians and Slavs; fortifications date to this period as well, as it became both a commercial and fishing center. Indeed, during the Viking Age it was the second-largest Viking marketplace, behind only Hedeby. Historians have speculated that Wolin may have been the basis for the semi-legendary Viking stronghold of Jomsborg that existed between the 960s and 1043. According to the sagas, the Jomsvikings were a band of elite warriors who adhered to a special codex and were loyal only to their leader. Supposedly, when their last jarl Sigvald died, most of the Jomsvikings left, following his brother Thorkell to England, where they took up arms as Cnut’s fierce huscarls.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_YORK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>After the Saxon settlement of northern England, York was the capital of the kingdom of Deira and then Northumbria. It was first captured by the Vikings when, in 866 AD, the “Great Heathen Army” under Ivar the Boneless (so called because he was either impotent or missing a leg, historians disagreeing as to which) came calling. A Viking horde returned in 875 and its leader Halfdan made York the center of a new Viking kingdom, known as Jorvik. Some 75 years later the last king of Jorvik, Eric Bloodaxe, was expelled and his lands absorbed into England, with local power vested in the Earl of York. Under the earls, the town became both a political and ecclesiastical seat. Some of the earls were Norse, some English. But it didn’t matter once William the Conqueror arrived. Although there were sporadic attempts by Danish Vikings to re-establish Jorvik, they all came to naught.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_ILKUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The leiðangr was a sort of conscription to fill out Norse fleets for seasonal raids or to defend the land … in effect, a fleet levy lasting (usually) two or three of the summer months. Since all sources which mention leiðangr are medieval, it is uncertain when the practice started or how widespread it was; according to these vague accounts, each district (skipreida) was to provide one ship and crew when called upon by their ruler.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_MEDINA_QUARTER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The thing (or the several variant spellings) was the “assembly” of a Norse settlement (even provinces and countries), composed of the free men (and occasionally women) that elected leaders, settled disputes, passed laws, punished lawbreakers, and generally tried to keep the Vikings from killing each other. Mostly, the thing worked as a cultural counterweight to the clan wars and blood feuds.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_SIEGE_TACTICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Given that most of the towns they attacked either had no walls or simple wooden palisades, and that Viking strategy relied on mobility and ferocity and surprise, Viking “siege weapons” tended at most to be improvised rams or towers. In Abbo’s account of the siege of Paris in 845 AD, crude ballistae are mentioned in passing … but no other extant works refer to the Vikings as using siege weapons; rather they just used ladders to battle over the walls and get inside.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_VOLLEY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The bow commonly used by the Norse for hunting or warfare was made of yew, ash, or elm, and had a draw of about 90 pounds, although warbows have been found that have higher; arrows had heads of iron or bone. In the late Viking Age, laws in Sweden and Norway specified that free landholders when called to a general muster were to bring not only a sword or axe and a shield, but be armed with a bow and arrows as well.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_TRAVELING_MONKS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Whereas most Christian monks lived in stable, monastic communities, the mendicant orders adopted a lifestyle of poverty, itinerant travelling, evangelization, and ministry, especially to the commoners. As such, since they had no lands or trade, these “travelling monks” depended on the goodwill of those to whom they preached for their well-being, though it didn't always work. </Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_BJARNI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Some believe that it was Bjarni Herjolfsson who should get the fame for “discovering” North America, not Leif Erikson. A merchant captain born in Iceland, and a dutiful son, each summer Herjolfsson would sail from Norway to visit his father. Finding that his father had sailed off with Erik the Red for Greenland, Bjarni set out to find him, but instead – blown off course – found an uninhabited coast covered with trees and hills. Although his crew wanted to explore, the captain refused and instead sailed to Greenland. This in 986 AD. In Greenland, his tales of a rich land to the west caught the ear of Leif, who decided to retrace Bjarni’s journey.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_ERIK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Erik Thorvaldsson—better known as Erik the Red—was a Norwegian who, having been banished from the company of “civilized men” in Iceland for “some killings,” founded the first Norse settlement in Greenland. (He was continuing the legacy of his father, who’d previously been banished from Norway for manslaughter.) Although other Vikings had previously visited Greenland, the sagas claim Erik spent his three years of exile exploring it. After wintering in Iceland, he gathered a host of colonists and returned to Greenland in 985 AD. There he established two settlements, which managed to struggle along until Greenland was abandoned by the Norse during the Little Ice Age.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_INGVAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>During the 10th and 11th centuries AD, Vikings from the north as well as the Rus mounted raids in the Caspian Sea against the Saracens and others. The last, under the leadership of Ingvar “the Far-Travelled,” departed from Sweden in 1036, possibly under the auspices of old King Anund Jakob. The expedition sailed down the Volga to the lands of the Saracens, where the Vikings under Ingvar took part in the battle of Sasireti. Though, there is no mention of Ingvar’s voyage in any of the extant Norse sagas, the sole source of the fragmentary story being some 26 rune stones scattered about Uppland in Sweden.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_FREYDIS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Freydis is believed to have been born sometime c. 970, daughter to Erik the Red and sister (or half-sister) to Leif Erikson. As a woman, she is mentioned only briefly in two of the ancient sagas; the 'Groenlendinga' and the 'Eiriks Rauda.' Although details vary, both have her going to Vinland, being a fierce and strong-willed woman seeking glory. But in one she helps fight off an attack by “Red Skins”; in the other, she engineers an attack on a rival Viking encampment, herself using an axe to slaughter the women. In both, she then returns to Greenland and disappears from the tales.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_LEIF_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Old Norse, he’s Leifr; in Icelandic – land of his birth – he’s Leifur; in Norwegian – land of his blood – he’s Leiv. Whatever the spelling, Leif Erikson was born to Erik the Red in Iceland, c. 970 AD. He is also the greatest of the Viking explorers, according to the sagas of Iceland. For he is now considered by many the first European to land in North America, well before Columbus. Although the history surrounding Leif’s discovery of Vinland is predictably hazy, according to the sagas he established a Norse settlement on the northern tip of Newfoundland (which didn’t last long though).</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_HALFDAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Best known as one of the leaders of the Great Heathen Army that stomped its way across England from 865 to 878 AD, Halfdan Ragnarsson ended up the disputed king of Dublin for a couple years and the undisputed king of Jorvik (York) for one. Mostly though, he lurched about England with the army, invading East Anglia in 865, then Northumbria in 866, then Mercia … East Anglia again … Wessex … and so forth. According to the “Annals of Ulster,” the King of Dublin was killed in 875 and somehow Halfdan took the throne. But when he returned to claim Jorvik, he was disposed in Dublin. Back in Ireland in 877, he was killed in the battle of Strangford Lough.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_RORIK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>For aiding Lothar I in the struggle against his father Louis the Pious, several minor Viking lords were granted bits of dead Louis’s lands in Frisia in 841, including one named Hrorik. There he established an island base on Wieringen for raiding. His reign extended to Dorestad … or so he claimed. In 850 AD Hrorek made it official, seizing and holding Dorestad and Utrecht. Since the Viking was willing to swear fealty and collect taxes, Lothar acknowledged him as ruler of Friesland. Dorestad’s importance as a commercial port had already begun to decline, so it was no great sacrifice. When Hrorek died in 882 his lands were given to the “Sea-King” Godfried.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_SVIATOSLAV_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Grand Prince of Kiev from 945 to his death in 972 AD, Sviatoslav was the first of the rulers of the Rus to have a Slavic—rather than Norse—name. In effect, his reign marks the end of Varangian influence on the Rus, whose concerns and culture now diverged dramatically from the Vikings. Sviatoslav had the typical Viking approach to life, for his rule was marked by persistent warfare against the Khazars, the Bulgarians, various East Slavic tribes, the Alans, and the Volga Bulgars. He was either warring or allied with the Perchenegs and Magyars, depending on the year. At his death, Sviatoslav had carved out the largest state in Europe … for the time.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_OLAF_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>King of Norway for five eventful years (995 to 1000 AD), Olaf was the grandson of Harald Fairhair and son of the chieftain Tryggvi (who was killed just before the boy’s birth, an occupational hazard for Vikings). According to legend, Olaf’s mother Astrid took the infant and fled to Kiev, where the boy was trained in Viking ways. After joining in raids on England, Olaf learned of a revolt in Norway against King Haakon; returning thence, he was declared king upon Haakon’s death in 995. And set about trying to impose – forcibly – Christianity on his subjects. Olaf didn’t make much progress before being killed at the battle of Svolder.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_WILLIAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>William I – also, not without reason, known as William the Bastard and William the Conqueror – at the tender age of eight, the descendent of Vikings, became the Duke of Normandy. Aided by King Henri I of France, William managed to hang onto his dukedom and life until he came of age. Being an ambitious sort, by 1064 AD William had managed to add the neighboring provinces of Britanny and Maine to his Norman holdings. In 1066 William took himself off across the Channel to pursue his tenuous claim to the English throne. The rest of his life was then spent trying to consolidate his hold on England, fend off threats to his continental lands, and dealing with his troublesome eldest son.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_THORFIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Thorfinn was the youngest of five sons of Sigurd Hlodvirsson, Earl of Orkney … but the only one to the earl’s second wife, who happened to be daughter of Malcolm II of Scotland. When Sigurd was killed in Ireland in 1011 AD, Orkney got divided between the four surviving brothers, with two-year-old Thorfinn getting the least share. With the support of King Malcolm and of King Olaf of Norway, by 1030 21-year-old Thorfinn held control of the Orkneys entire. Thorfinn spent the rest of his life conquering the Hebrides, raiding Ireland, helping his cousin Macbeth gain the Scottish throne, and turning his subjects Christian.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_ROGER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Roger (also known as Jarl Rogeirr) was the self-styled Norman Count of Sicily from the opening of his efforts to reclaim the island from the Muslims until his death 29 years later. Roger first went to Italy in 1057 AD to aid his greedy brother Robert Guiscard in taking Calabria from the Byzantines. In May 1061 the brothers decided to conquer the whole of Sicily. After they took Palermo in January 1072, Robert as suzerain invested Roger as “Count of Sicily.” In 1098 the Pope granted Roger and his heirs the Apostolic Legateship of the island as well.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_VIKING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Most historian-linguists now associate the term “Viking” with the Norse vikingr, meaning “pirate.” But not in the sense that most would assume; rather, to go a-viking simply meant to undertake any overseas expedition, not just for raiding, although there was certainly that angle, but for exploration, trade, or mercenary service.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_NAVAL_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When the Vikings began raiding the coasts, they were successful largely due to the fact that few kingdoms had a standing navy. When kings began to create navies, it marked the end of Viking dominance; the “hundred-ship” Viking fleets that did come together occasionally had no cohesion, formation or coordination, being mere masses composed of smaller fleets led by individual chieftains or clans. </Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_MONOTHEISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Monotheism is, simply, the belief that there is only one god (or goddess). This belief can be dated back to Zoroastrianism, and is still found today in Christianity, Sikhism, and others.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_GREAT_HEATHEN_ARMY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the year 865, thousands of Vikings landed in East Anglia, supposedly led by three vengeful sons of the legendary Ragnar Lodbrok. This “Great Heathen Army” stomped across England, taking what it could and breaking what it couldn't. The Anglo-Saxon King Alfred, known to history as Alfred the Great, finally brought the Great Heathen Army to defeat in 878. It wasn't all bad news for the Vikings, however—the treaty that followed gave much of northern and eastern England over to Viking rule.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_KNARRS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Viking knarr was a heavy, freight-carrying cargo ship that could haul a couple dozen tons of goods and crew on long sea voyages. Routinely venturing on trading voyages across the Mediterranean, Baltic and North seas, the knarr also carried Norse colonists to the likes of Iceland, Greenland and Vinland. Though it was neither sleek nor picturesque when set aside a longship, the knarr was the true workhorse of the Viking fleets.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_LONGSHIPS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Viking longship design evolved over millennia, from the prehistoric Scandinavian umiak to the clinker-built Nydam ship of the 6th century. By the 9th century the longship was graceful, long but narrow, shallow-draft (able to navigate up rivers), and lightweight (for portage). The speedy wooden ships made the Vikings masters of the seas, and the sight of longships on the horizon caused fear through much of Europe until the 13th Century.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_PORTAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The technique of portaging (or "carrying ships overland from one body of water to another") has been around since the first caveman on a raft fetched up against a rock. Obviously, this is easier to do in some places than others—recognizing and establishing a portage was essential when Viking longships were involved. In the 8th and 9th centuries, Viking adventurers exploited a network of portages connecting the Volga, Dvina, Dneiper and Don rivers to establish and enrich the Rus kingdom. (No particular technique or technology was necessary for the act of portaging … just a strong back.)</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_HACKSILVER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Vikings had little use for coinage. Instead, the Norsemen preferred to horde their wealth in “hacksilver”—cut or bent silver items with which they traded or took as plunder. Once the blood was washed off, it took much less effort to chop up silverware, jewelry and crucifixes than to cast actual coins. Vikings preferred hacksilver for many generations—silver was by far the most common precious metal, and the easiest to work.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_LANCES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The lance—a long pole with a sharp point for skewering people—was the primary weapon used by heavy cavalry during the Viking Age. Few of the Norsemen used them, but many of their foes did. The Byzantine cavalry bore lances (known as 'kontarion') during this period, couching them either overarm or underarm. But it was the Europeans that perfected the full-gallop, closed-ranks charge so effective against enemy infantry … and anyone else in the way.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_MEAD_HALLS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The ancient Scandinavian mead halls from the 5th through 11th centuries were combination tribal feasting chambers and occasional residences of Viking lords and their retainers. Norse sagas and legends are full of the many uses to which a mead hall could be put—celebrations, ceremonies, festivals, war councils … even murder! (The 'Ynglinga' saga recounts King Ingjald's construction of a mead hall in which to burn his subordinates as they slept.) The Vikings couldn't get enough of their mead halls, for the mythical halls of Valhalla and Sessrumnir allowed let their fun continue even after death.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_TECHNOLOGIES_PAGE_TECH_SHIELDWALL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mentioned in both Nordic sagas and Christian chronicles, the shield wall—evolved from Greek and Roman formations—was a simple battle tactic involving overlapping shields to form a barrier against light missile fire, massed infantry, and even cavalry charges. It was a favorite formation among some Viking clans, and used as well by their Saxon and Germanic foes. Though Viking raiders preferred axes for many reasons, they were ideal for cleaving legs below a shield wall. In the late Middle Ages, the tactic was abandoned in favor of long polearms. These required two hands to wield and were even more effective at keeping both enemy infantry and cavalry at bay.</Text>
		</Replace>
	</LocalizedText>
</GameData>
