<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<GameData>
	<EnglishText>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_DARIUS_III_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Darius III came to power when the Achaemenid Empire was the functional equivalent of a fully-laden chariot at a cliff’s edge, horses long since fled in separate directions, balanced upon its one remaining wheel. It was left to Darius to reconcile the highly independent (and occasionally openly rebellious) satraps who used their distance from Persepolis to flaunt their independence.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_DARIUS_III_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Unfortunately for him, Alexander the Great arrived to relieve the chariot of anything valuable and give what remained a good, swift kick. After a series of humiliating defeats, Darius eventually fell victim to a coup and was left for dead on an ox-cart.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ATHENS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The city of Athens is known for both its longevity and its cultural contributions that would help define western civilization. Serving as a cradle from democracy from the 5th Century BCE, a fiercely independent Athens allied with other Greek city-states in times of crises. After famously holding off the invasion of the Persian king Xerxes, Athenian fortunes briefly fell to the Spartans during the Peloponnesian War, and then more permanently in 338 BCE when Philip II ended an independent Athens for quite some time. However, it remained a beacon of culture and scholarship for centuries to come.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MARAKANDA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Known to the Macedones as Maracanda (and in the modern times as the Uzbek city of Samarkand), the capital of Persia’s Sogdian satrapy was conquered by Alexander the Great in 329 BCE. Revitalized by its new rulers, Markand was home-away-from-home to Alexander’s forces while he put down a Sogdian rebellion. Markand is where Alexander declared his coming invasion of India. It was also where he hurled a spear through Cleitus the Black, one of his generals, on the heels of a drunken dispute. Poor luck for both Cleitus and India.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PATALA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The ancient city of Patala existed in what is now Pakistan, but there is no clear consensus on exactly where it stood during the time of Alexander the Great—possibly Hyperabad or Thatta. Ancient texts suggest it was a city on the Indus River near the outflow to the Arabian Sea. (The Indus River’s fluctuation over the course of two millennia helps explain the geographic confusion.) Capital of the Patalene, the land of the Indus delta, its king wisely submitted to Alexander, who based his troops there while he explored a route to the Arabian Sea, the southern boundary of his empire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_ANTIGENES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The one-eyed Antigenes began his career under Philip II, served faithfully as Alexander's general throughout his campaigns, and was eventually rewarded for his service with the satrapy of Susiana. Unfortunately for Antigenes, he had the misfortune of siding with the wrong successor state, and ended his career burned alive in a pit.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_COENUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Coenus was a reliable general who preferred to lead by example. His temperamental similarity with Alexander is likely why he was handed command of the right-most phalanx, a crucial part of the Macedonian hammer-and-anvil. Coenus had earned such respect that he ultimately swayed Alexander to return from his Indian conquests.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_CRATERUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The capable Craterus was one of Alexander’s more reliable commanders. Early successes at Issus and Tyre led to him serving as a supreme commander alongside Alexander during the Persian campaign. He was not above politics, such as accusing his rival Philotas of treachery, but was unwavering in his loyalty his king.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_MELEAGER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Though Meleager never rose to prominence among Alexander’s generals, he was a reliable officer who commanded a phalanx division throughout his king’s campaigns. Perhaps it was his blunt manner—when asked to calm unhappy soldiers following Alexander’s death, he ended up joining (and leading) a mutiny against his fellow generals.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_POLYPERCHON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Polyperchon commanded a phalanx under Alexander until the time of his king’s death, though he is better known for his involvement in the subsequent succession wars. Successfully navigating the constantly shifting loyalties during at least three wars of the Diadochi, Polyperchon was thought to have survived through the 3rd Century BCE.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_SELEUCUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Seleucus was a contemporary of Alexander who trained with the best and brightest Philip II’s Macedon. He commanded the elite hypaspistai during Alexander’s campaigns, and his responsibility for protecting Alexander’s flanks continued long after his death, when Seleucus ultimately founded the Seleucid Empire, which stretched from modern day Turkey to Afghanistan.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_CLEITUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Cleitus the Black served as a cavalry general under Alexander the Great. After saving the young king’s life near the beginning of his campaigns, Cleitus has the dubious distinction of being repaid with a spear drunkenly hurled through the chest—years later, and to Alexander’s apparent dismay after the fact.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_ERIGYIUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Erigyius was so loyal to Alexander that a suspicious Philip II had him banished from Macedon. Upon the old king’s death, the new king needed cavalry commanders—and Erigyius was up to the task. He served faithfully through Alexander’s campaigns, but was ultimately killed in battle with Bactrians.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_HEPHAESTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Hephaestion, Alexander the Great’s closest friend since childhood, would eventually command the hetairoi during Alexander’s expeditions. This wasn’t favoritism—Hephaestion was an unquestionably brilliant and capable commander. His sudden illness and death was a severe blow to Alexander, who spared no expense for his funeral and planned multiple lasting tributes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_LEONNATUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Leonnatus was a loyal cavalry general of Alexander the Great who was trusted and skilled enough to become one of the king’s personal bodyguards. He served throughout Alexander’s campaigns. After Alexander’s death, Leonnatus was caught up in the wars of succession. He met his end at Athenian hands in the Lamian War.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_PERDICCAS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Though Perdiccas began his military career as a phalanx commander, Alexander the Great eventually appointed him the commander of the hetairoi (Companion cavalry) after Hephaestion’s death. On Alexander’s deathbed, Perdiccas was made supreme commander and regent—a position he squandered through poor politics, leading to the first war of succession.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_PHILOTAS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Philip’s general Parmenion supported Alexander’s ascension to the throne. In return, the new king elevated Parmenion’s son Philotas to general in command of the Companion cavalry. Despite his capability on the battlefield, Philotas’s rebellious streak led him to plot treason, which brought about the death of himself and his father.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_ALEXANDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Alexander had a reputation for leading from the front, endearing himself to his soldiers by sharing in the same (or more) danger than they did. He would often lead the hetairoi (Companion cavalry) into battle, and was once so impatient to storm the walls of a besieged city that he and a few troops found themselves cut off and surrounded by the enemy. Though he suffered a grievous wound, he survived the seemingly impossible situation, and his soldiers loved him all the more for his courage—which the sly Alexander certainly used to push them beyond their limits.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</GameData>
