<GameData>
	<LocalizedText>
		<!-- Indonesia --> 
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_CIVINFO_INDONESIA_LOCATION">
			<Text>Đông Nam Á</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_CIVINFO_INDONESIA_SIZE">
			<Text>735,358 dặm vuông</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_CIVINFO_INDONESIA_POPULATION">
			<Text>Ước tính 263.51 triệu vào 2017</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_CIVINFO_INDONESIA_CAPITAL">
			<Text>Jakarta</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>At its height, the Buddhist-Hindu kingdom of Majapahit (in what is now Indonesia) flexed its might across 98 regional tributaries, a formidable state which once resisted the mighty Mongol Empire. Here, the monarch was not only its ruler, but its guardian, empowered by the people. But what if the people felt the leader no longer deserved being empowered? </Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Between 1293 and 1500, the Southeast Asian kingdom of Majapahit encompassed what is now parts of modern-day Indonesia, with its center in Nusantara (regions throughout Maluku and Sumatra). Theirs was an absurdly wealthy kingdom, which, of course, earned them both regional enemies and internal rivals.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>We know that the Majapahit emerged from the Javanese-Hindu Singhasari Kingdom (1222-1292), who were themselves preceded by the Kediri (1042-1222).</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>As for the Kingdom’s origins, we can use the historical record from their many temples, as well as the documentation from their regional rivals. But some of the most important primary sources about the Majapahit are translations of the epic poem 'Nagarakretagama' (also known as 'The Book of Kings'). Given that the 'Nagarakretagama' was composed by a Majapahit court poet, one should assume that some of the details might have been slightly embellished in the cause of a great story.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>According to legend, the Majapahit rulers were descended from the orphan Ken Arok, born to a human mother and the god Brahma. Ken Arok made a name for himself ruling the Kediri—before he was assassinated.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>And yet his line survived, down through Raden Wijaya, who was crowned the first king of the Majapahit in 1293 (known by his royal name Kertarajasa Jayawardhana). Wijaya would begin his empire in a small village named for its local bitter maja fruit.</Text>
		</Replace>		
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Instead of settling into village life, Wijaya would marry the four daughters of Kertanegara, last king of the Singhasari. Singhasari's closest advisors weren't partial to an insider coming in, marrying all of the eligible princesses, and taking over the kingdom, and so Raden Wijaya's rule was largely marked by putting down rebellions, while also repelling the Mongols of the Yuan Dynasty, who sent some 100,000 men aboard 1,000 ships to halt his predecessor's expansion. All this in order to avoid being the first and last Majapahit king.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>The Majapahit would build their empire with grains of rice (some research suggests that up to 80 percent of the population was involved in rice production) and the spice trade. Their seaways would provide links between India and China, and the kingdom kept the coffers filled by charging duties on goods traveling its throughways. </Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>And they weren't afraid to flex their naval might: bas relief carvings from the period depict Majapahit naval raids against nearby kingdoms using impressive armadas. Using their massive jong ships, the Majapahit would move people and products, spreading rice from Eastern Java as well as the Malay language.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>Under the negara or mandala style of governance, divine power emanated from the king outward, extending military protection as well as participation in the religious life of the capital. Villagers and regional nobles would send tribute to the Majapahit capital, Trowulan, and in return the king would restore temples, grant gifts, and send members of his family to far-flung regions to rule. </Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>The kingdom would, for a time, survive regional rivalries with the Johor Sultanate and Siam (Thailand), by staging numerous raids on Malay Sultans in the 15th century. At their height, the Majapahit’s reach would make it the largest pre-modern state in the region.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>After his death in 1309, Raden Wijaya would be succeeded by his son, Jayanegara, whose own reign between 1309 and 1328 was cut short by a small case of assassination. He was succeeded by his half-sister Dyah Gitarja, who would then hand the throne over to her son, Hayam Wuruk in 1350.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_13">
			<Text>And it's here that we enter the golden age of the Majapahit Kingdom one hears so much about. Hayam Wuruk (also known as Rajasanagara) would begin his reign at the age of 16 and with the help of his 'pati' (prime minister/grand vizier) Gajah Mada, would expand the reach of the Rajasa dynasty across the continent.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_14">
			<Text>A skilled archer raised to be king by his mother (and said to be very, very good-looking), Hayam Wuruk would extend the power of his family and become the center of Majapahit’s mandala.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_15">
			<Text>But the love between the people and their king would not be enough to save the kingdom from a bloody (and expensive) civil war of succession, wherein the king's concubine-born son, Bhre Wirabumi would attempt to wrest the crown away from his recently coroneted brother-in-law in the years 1404 to 1406.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_16">
			<Text>If that's not enough, its trade routes - for so long the source of its power - would become its ultimate undoing. The eastern islands became ports for European traders, moving the consolidation of power away from the empire to these smaller communities. The port city of Melaka (on what is now the Malay Peninsula) would rise to replace Majapahit and become the most important trade center in Southeast Asia, as the Majapahit merchant class would turn to Islam in order to better ingratiate themselves to the commercial life of Melaka’s Muslim majority.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_17">
			<Text>The people, it seemed, would no longer need their leader.</Text>
		</Replace>
    <Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_INDONESIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_18">
      <Text>Successive years would see traces of the Majapahit wiped away: by the Sixteenth Century, the Hindu-Buddhist kingdom would be completely replaced by a sultanate, drawing Islamic influences from the Western islands such as Aceh and Melaka. The sultans, too, would struggle to keep control of the region. Their reign would ultimately be cut short by incursions from Dutch and Portuguese colonialists, hopelessly addicted to Southeast Asian spices and vying for empire in the Sixteenth and Seventeenth Centuries.</Text>
    </Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_TITLE">
			<Text>Gitarja</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_SUBTITLE">
			<Text>Tribhuwannottunggadewi Jayawishnuwardhani, Hoàng hậu nhiếp chính Javanese, hay còn được biết đến là Dyah Gitarja</Text>
		</Replace>			
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_QUOTE">
			<Text>Khi đất đai không còn đủ, hãy buông thuyền. Đại dương sẽ tiết lệ cho chúng ta nhiều thứ hơn.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>How does one go from being a princess locked in a tower to a warrior-queen regent of a Fourteenth Century spice empire? First you start with a little assassination.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Much of what we know about Gitarja's reign comes from the epic poem 'Nagarakretagama.' Written by court poet Rakawi Prapanca, this mix of history and myth should be taken with a grain of salt. But 'Nagarakretagama' tells us that Gitarjah, the Duchess of Kahuripan's story truly begins with the murder of her half-brother, King Jayanagara.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Queen Regent Tribhuwannottunggadewi Jayawishnuwardhani, also known by her familiar name Dyah Gitarja, was born sometime before 1309, daughter to Raden Wijaya, father of the Majapahit empire and the queen consort Gayarti Rajapatni. She ruled the Southeast Asian spice kingdom from 1329 to 1350, succeeding her half-brother, Jayanagara (also known as Prince of Kadiri) during a time of open revolt and chaos for the Majapahit Empire.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Legend has it Jayanagara was so beset by enemies that he even saw his sisters as threats to his throne. So he locked them away in a palace, out of reach of potential suitors. What he didn't account for was a jealous palace physician, who killed the king in 1328 after learning that Jayanagara had seduced his wife.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Because Jayanagara spent more time wooing his subjects' wives and less so siring an heir, the queen consort was able to appoint her daughter, Dyah Gitarja, to the throne in 1329. The newly crowned Queen Regent, would now be known by her official title of Tribhuwannottunggadewi Jayawishnuwardhani.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>That same year, she would appoint Gajah Mada 'pati,' or prime minister of the Majapahit Empire. The histories paint Mada as a vigorous expansionist of the Majapahit Empire, loyal to the Rajasa dynasty across three monarchs, and a palace schemer. It remains to be seen whether the rumors of Mada having anything to do with the assassination of King Jayanagara are true, and the historical record is mum on whether Dyah Gitarja was aware of her pati's possible hand in a little regicide.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>That same year, free of her icy tower of loneliness, she would take the noble Chakradhara as her consort, and together, they had a son, Hayam Wuruk, in 1334.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>The Queen Regent's reign would see her quell rebellions among the Sadeng and Keta regions. She's said to have ridden into battle alongside her cousin, Malayapuran king Adityawarman.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>But history will remember her reign for the Majapahit conquest of the island of Bali under the martial skills of her prime minister. Gajah Mada would end the line of the local Balinese leadership, allowing the kingdom to fall under Majapahit domination.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>Gitarjah's reign came to an end not through warfare or palace intrigues, but through an unfortunate quirk in Majapahit succession. Her mother, Gayatri, was responsible for granting Gitarja the title of Queen Regent, meaning Gitarja ruled at the pleasure of the queen dowager. But when Gayatri died in a monastery in 1350, Gitarja lost her patron and was forced to abdicate the throne.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>Gitarja would be succeeded by her son, Hayam Wuruk, who would usher in what some Indonesians consider the golden age of the Majapahit kingdom. Depending on the historian, Hayam Wuruk took the empire which his mother was able to secure and saw its borders pushed beyond present-day Indonesia and out to some of what is now Malaysia.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>As for Dyah Gitarja's life after the throne? The record is silent on the facts of her later years, or even when she died. But she'll be remembered for expanding the boundaries of her empire and increasing the majesty of the Majapahit.</Text>
		</Replace>
    <Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_CHAPTER_CAPSULE_BODY">
      <Text>Gitarja is the queen of all the islands and coasts, with cities spreading out onto the water and protected by Indonesian Jongs.</Text>
    </Replace>
    <Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GITARJA_CHAPTER_DETAILED_BODY">
      <Text>Indonesia wants to find coastal shores with lots of bays and inlets. Such land is ideal territory for placement of most districts to maximize their adjacency bonuses. As soon as Shipbuilding comes online, Gitarja's builders can augment those cities with off-shore Kampung stilt houses, reducing the need for farmland to grow large cities. Indonesia should try to maximize [ICON_Faith] Faith generation which can be used to either fund a huge Jong-powered navy, claim critical [ICON_GreatPerson] Great People, or power toward a religious victory using her water-crossing religious units.</Text>
    </Replace>
    
		<!-- Indonesia --> 
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_CIVINFO_KHMER_LOCATION">
			<Text>Đông Nam Á</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_CIVINFO_KHMER_SIZE">
			<Text>460,000 dặm vuông</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_CIVINFO_KHMER_POPULATION">
			<Text>Ước tính 2,000,000 vào 1150</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_CIVINFO_KHMER_CAPITAL">
			<Text>Nhiều, bao gồm Mahendraparvata, Hariharalaya, Koh Ker, Yasodharapura</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Between the Ninth and Fifteenth Centuries, the god-warrior-kings of the Khmer Empire dominated Southeast Asia. Theirs was a formidable agricultural-martial kingdom whose wealth impressed even the mighty Chinese to the North. Unfortunately, all of that gold and rice would prove too attractive for their regional rivals, ultimately making the conquerors of the Suvarnabhumi the conquered.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Archaeology and Chinese historical records tell us the Khmer Empire can be traced back to the Mekong region in Southeast Asia during the First Century CE. The Chinese called this region and its disparate collection of peoples the Funan Kingdom (offhandedly putting a diverse, often warring group of principalities under one umbrella).</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>According to Khmer legend, these people were the product of the union of Cambodia's first king, Indian prince Preah Thong (Huntian, in the Chinese record) and Neang Neak, a divine serpent [naga] princess from a magical seas kingdom. The region is said to have been a wedding gift from the princess' father, who drained the waters around Nokor Kauk Thlork Island, making it habitable for the happy couple and their descendants.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>The legend speaks to the tremendous influence of Hindu culture in the region. The Mekong-based people of Funan was the perfect waypoint for Indian travelers and traders headed west. The Indians would end up bringing Hinduism, their laws, commerce, and Sanskrit with them, ultimately blending with local animist traditions.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>The people of Funan's Indian-influenced mini-principalities battled amongst themselves for centuries, and although they would briefly sustain centralized governments, it would take the firm hand of Jayavarman II in the Ninth Century to usher in the Angkor era of centralized rule.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>The first conqueror king of the Khmer Empire got his start in the Ninth Century. Until that point, Jayavarman II was either a guest of the Javanese or their prisoner. Whichever the case, once he returned to his homeland, he seemed eager to get about the messy process of crushing the competition in the Mekong.</Text>
		</Replace>		
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>That messy business out of the way, the only thing left to do was to declare himself 'Cakravartin' or 'universal ruler' during a ceremony atop Mount Mahendra in the Kulen Mountains. And in 802 CE, that's precisely what Jayavarman II did, granting himself the backing of the gods in establishing his empire.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>There's something to be said for his approach: at the height of their six century empire, the Khmer would dominate what is now modern most of Thailand and half of Vietnam, with over a million people living in the capital. By the Tenth Century, the empire would stretch from the South China Sea, with the Mongolian and Tang empires penning it in to the North. Not a bad spread if you wanted to maintain control of trade in the Mekong.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Between 1296 and 1297, Chinese official Zhou Daguan would visit the Khmer Empire. In his chronicle of that visit, 'A Record of Cambodia: A Land and Its People,' he would say: 'It has long been a trading country.' Zhou would describe a land of gold and stone towers, with cloth flowing from Siam and Champa and silk for locals' parasols from China.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>The vast wealth of the Khmer would come from the constant flow of raw materials in and out of the Empire. The empire would feed Southeast Asia's need for rice, with some 80% of the Khmer population participating in either the production or trade of this staple food.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>This would be the golden age of the Khmer Empire, when Suryavarman II would start construction on the temple complex at Angkor Wat (it would be completed 27 years after his death). Angkor Wat would mirror the shape of the mythical Mount Meru which was said to be the convergence of the physical, metaphysical, and spiritual worlds. In this way, the Khmer kings would try to mirror heaven on Earth.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>This wasn't simple piety; these Hindu (and latest Buddhist under Jayavarman VII) royals were eager keeping the gods on their side. A king would do his best to maintain a bearing which would best reflect the gods, and build temples which would emulate the shape of the heavens. Under the Khmer's rule, the more powerful and attractive the king, the more followers and land he would have.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_13">
			<Text>Of course, that would mean a weak king whose bearing wasn't sufficiently divine would no longer be worthy of his kingdom.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_14">
			<Text>Ironically, the wealth and majesty of the Khmer Empire would prove its undoing. Between the Twelfth and Fourteenth Centuries, the Tai people in the North (now modern Thai, Laotian, and Shan) were contending with the ever-expanding Mongol Empire. So they pulled up stakes from their rugged, mountain lives and moved south, creating the smaller kingdoms of Sukhothai, Lanna, and Ayutthaya, which gnawed at the periphery of the Khmer Empire.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_15">
			<Text>The Khmer were unable to contend with the Northern invaders as well as longstanding rivalries with Champa in the East. So by 1431, the Thai kingdom of Ayutthaya would take Angkor and the Khmer kings retreated to Phnom Penh, the current capital of Cambodia. </Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_16">
			<Text>The empire may be gone, but their temples still stand. And to this day, the people of Cambodia still speak of coming from the sea, of their ancestors, a Brahmin and a Naga princess.</Text>
		</Replace>	
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_TITLE">
			<Text>Jayavarman VII</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_SUBTITLE">
			<Text>Vua đế chế Khmer</Text>
		</Replace>			
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_QUOTE">
			<Text>Provide for your people. To do less is to be less.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>He oversaw a truly staggering amount of infrastructure building and rival kingdom-smashing during what many consider the golden age of the Khmer. Meet the people's king, Jayavarman VII.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Born in 1123 CE and the son of King Dharanindravarman II, much of that we know about King Jayavarman VII comes from inscriptions on the temple at Räjavihära (now Ta Prohm) as well as at Phimeanakas. These inscriptions offer a rich, yet still incomplete history of this beloved king.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>However, what we do know is that when King Jayavarman VII's reign began during a period of crisis for the Khmer. To the north, their control over distant vassal kingdoms was eroding away, while the Mongols (and later the Ming Dynasty) were expanding their trade interests throughout Southeast Asia (trade of raw materials being how the Khmer remained fabulously wealthy). To the South, revolution was brewing in Malyang. And looking east, the Empire was entering year 14 of their war with the Champa (occupants of what is now central Vietnam).</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Jayavarman VII would spend his 20s and 30s at war, supporting King Yasovarman II (a relative of unknown origin) in war against the Cham. An interesting side note: according to legend, King Yasovarman II was attacked by the frankly horrifying divine being Rahu (a floating head which ate suns during eclipses), only to be saved by one of Jayavarman VII's sons.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>By 1178, the Cham, under King Jaya Indravarman IV, would invade the Khmer Empire twice, destroying the capital at Yaśodharapura on the second attempt and sacking the temple city of Angkor Wat.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Now it's unclear why, but around this time, Jayavarman VII was said to be living in Vijaya, which is in central Champa (given the history of the period, he may have just been a guest). He would march west and regain control of Khmer—with Cham forces in tow.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>This is according to Champa inscriptions, by the way, which are not wholly clear on why these Cham forces would ally themselves with a foreigner. Or why, ten years after he took the throne, a Cham prince would help King Jayavarman seize the Champa capital of Vijaya and assist in the capture of King Indravarman?</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>By 1181, with a little diplomacy (and some help from his Cham allies), Jayavarman VII had repelled the Cham invaders. Once hostilities died down, he crowned himself king. He would, of course, celebrate the start of his reign by establishing a new capital at Angkor Thom.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>At this point, you would expect your newly-minted monarch to begin his period of land-grabbing and expansion. And while King Jayavarman would keep up the conflict with Champa, going as far as to install a puppet king in 1190, his reign was notable for turning inward, beginning an unprecedented period of construction and infrastructure building.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>King Jayavarman VII saw himself as a warrior for his subjects, and not just one who rode into battle to fight foreign foes (although he did a bit of that, too). In a break with previous Hindu-Khmer kings, which centered the throne in state affairs, King Jayavarman adopted a Buddhist mode of thinking, one which centered the population in the state.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>Mahayana Buddhism is believed to meld both compassion (personified by the Bodhisattva Lokesvara) and wisdom (Prajnaparamita), and it was King Jayavarman's aim to create a place of safety and paradise for his subjects.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>He would actually make Mahayana Buddhism the state religion, breaking with 400 years of Khmer Hinduism. And to mark the occasion, he would initiate the construction of numerous temples, 102 hospitals, stone-paved highways out of reach of flood waters, the 54 towers at Bayon, and extensive irrigation projects. Another documented project was the construction of rest houses every 15 km throughout the kingdom.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_13">
			<Text>Additionally, the nearly 40 years of his rule would also be marked for its tolerance; while endorsing Buddhism, King Jayavarman VII kept a role for Brahman priests within the palace, a role that continues today in Cambodian kingship. </Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_14">
			<Text>We don't have many details about the final years of King Jayavarman VII's life, or even the year in which he died (but it was somewhere between 1215 and 1220). However, after his death, he would be given the name Mahäparamasaugata as a tribute to his greatness. As for the Khmer Empire? It would fall into what looks like a precipitous decline. By 1222, the Cham were able to retake the land Jayavarman VII had conquered during his reign.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_15">
			<Text>Still, it's hard to undo all of that temple-building and goodwill-spreading. King Jayavarman VII and his people-driven reign remains fondly remembered in Cambodia, where he figured prominently in state-produced education materials well into the 20th century.</Text>
		</Replace>
    <Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_CAPSULE_BODY">
      <Text>Jayavarman's Khmer Empire features populous cities of devout Buddhists, especially those along rivers where all their abilities can come into play.</Text>
    </Replace>
    <Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JAYAVARMAN_CHAPTER_DETAILED_BODY">
      <Text>Jayavarman wants to take advantage of his river start bias and place his Holy Sites along rivers where they will claim nearby land and provide [ICON_Food] Food and [ICON_Housing] Housing.  These cities will then bloom when the Khmer reach the late Classical era when both Aqueducts and their unique Prasat temples come online.  If neighbors crowd them in, they can use their Domrey unique unit to besiege a few nearby cities, probably grabbing additional sites along rivers. With a populous empire based around the Buddhist faith, Jayavarman can pursue any victory type moving forward into the later game.</Text>
    </Replace>
    
	<!-- Rest -->
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_INDONESIAN_JONG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If you wish to dominate the high seas, confront the enemy with overwhelming force. This was the philosophy behind the massive jong ships, the schooner of the Majapahit. This vessel allowed the Empire to control Javanese waters through a combination of size and strength.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_INDONESIAN_JONG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Majapahit sailing vessels differentiated themselves from Chinese junks with the addition of a second rudder, which made the 600 ton jong fast yet easy to control. This wasn't the only extra maneuverability option for the jong; if the winds were low, a row of oarsmen could move the schooner beyond the range of enemy fire or around seaborne obstacles.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_INDONESIAN_JONG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>While primarily used as merchant ships, jongs also served as military transports. All of that weight wasn't just for show: the addition of four-layer wooden masts offered protection against incoming cannon fire, and a jong under attack could return the favor with its own opposing ordnance.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_KHMER_DOMREY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If there aren't enough horses for your cavalry, why not use the mighty elephant to crush and terrify your enemies?</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_KHMER_DOMREY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Khmer joined a long tradition of employing war elephants in their military campaigns. Research suggests that the Indians first used elephants in their military campaigns around 1,100 BCE, tuning what was at that point a farming helper animal and turning its 12,000 pounds of might into sound and terror for their opponents on the battlefield (at least until the invention of gunpowder evened the odds). </Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_KHMER_DOMREY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The mount of kings, military leaders would ride elephants into the battlefield, using their lines to stampede through enemy forces.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_KHMER_DOMREY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Khmer riders would use the precision of double crossbows to supplement the raw power of their elephants. However this domrey variant adds a bit more sheer force with a mounted ballista to impale the bold soldier not wise enough to run away.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_KAMPUNG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the densely-packed islands of Southeast Asia, local rulers faced the challenge of how best to house their people while also keeping them safe from floods and wildlife. Their answer – communities of tightly-clustered houses on stilts, or the kampung.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_KAMPUNG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>While the term is a general one referring to a neighborhood, Indonesian kampungs were famous for helping Java achieve the highest population density of any island in the world. Indeed, foreign visitors were so impressed by the efficiency of Indonesian and Malay kampungs that they adopted the term in the English ‘compound.’ </Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_PRASAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When not dominating the Mekong and the mainland of Southeast Asia, the kings of the Khmer empire would turn their attention to their faith. And what better way to venerate the gods than through erecting massive temples?</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_PRASAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>These holy sites at the center of Khmer worship would serve as both symbols of their warrior-kings’ piety and their engineers' brilliance. The earliest Khmer temple on record is Prasat Ak Yom (c. 800), its design reflecting the South Indian tradition of 'ratha'-style temples, towering edifices terminating in a crown at the top. Of course, the Khmer would add their own flourish, adding prangs, or towers to the structures.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_PRASAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The construction of these temples would become an enduring feature of subsequent Khmer rulers, first facing east in honor of the Hindu god Shiva, while later construction would turn west after Jayavarman VII introduced Mahayana Buddhism to the Empire in the Twelfth Century.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_ANGKOR_WAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>It has stood for nearly 1,000 years, a monument to a god and possibly the final resting place of the conqueror king who built it.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_ANGKOR_WAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>And still, the temple at Angkor Wat endures, its central tower rising 213 feet above the surrounding jungle. Constructed by the Khmer King Suryavarman II in the Twelfth century in what is now northern Cambodia, it is one of the world's tallest religious monuments.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_ANGKOR_WAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>A pilgrim to the city-temple of the Hindu God Vishnu would first cross a 650-foot wide and 14-feet deep moat surrounding the structure before entering a 'gopura,' a three-towered entrance leading to a raised walkway. Inside the temple complex proper, they would find four smaller towers surrounding one central 213-foot tower, evoking the sacred Mount Meru.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_ANGKOR_WAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Khmer Shaivist temples typically face east, but because Angkor Wat faces west, the final resting place for Suryavarman's remains would be a temple honoring Vishnu. </Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_BUILDING_ANGKOR_WAT_QUOTE">
			<Text>“The temple is surrounded by a moat, and access is by a single bridge, protected by two stone tigers so grand and fearsome as to strike terror into the visitor.”[NEWLINE]– Diogo do Couto</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_HA_LONG_BAY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>How many natural formations are featured in the creation myth of a nation? According the Vietnamese legend, it's here that the gods sent jade and jewel-spewing dragons who created the rocky islands dotting the bay and creating a defense against early Chinese invaders. In fact, the name means some variation of 'descending dragons,' or 'dragons descending into the sea.' </Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_HA_LONG_BAY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Ha Long Bay is the name given to a collection of karst islets, natural limestone formations created after millions of years of erosion, featuring ridges, towers, and caves. To see and explore it today, is to trace a network of around 1600 limestone isles and caves stretching across 120 km of modern Vietnamese coastline.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_HA_LONG_BAY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>As far back as 16,000 BCE, it was the home to early tribes of fishers, while throughout history, it has stood as a natural bulwark against invaders: in 1288, it would be the site of a Mongol defeat, where Vietnamese General Tran Hung Dao impaled Mongol ships on steel-tipped spikes, stopping their advance.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_HA_LONG_BAY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Since 2000, Ha Long Bay has been designated a UNESCO World Heritage Site.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_FEATURE_HA_LONG_BAY_QUOTE">
			<Text>“Behold the wonders of the Heavens and Earth. The clear aqua blue serves as a looking glass, thousands of turquoise crows tinged with a touch of black.”[NEWLINE]– Nguyễn Trãi</Text>
		</Replace>
	</LocalizedText>
</GameData>
