<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<GameData>
  <!-- FEATURE_BARRIER_REEF was renamed to FEATURE_BARRIER_REEF_EXTENDED... -->
  <LocalizedText>
    <Update>
      <Where Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_BARRIER_REEF_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1" />
      <Set Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_BARRIER_REEF_EXTENDED_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1" />
    </Update>
  
  		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SYDNEY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The colonial British foothold in eastern Australia first took root with the founding of Sydney in 1788. From its humble beginnings as a penal colony to its transformation into a free society, New South Wales has always been (or felt it should be) at the forefront of Australian affairs.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CITYSTATES_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SYDNEY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The discovery of gold in 1851 did much to make New South Wales as powerful economically as it was politically. Upon Australia’s transition from colonies to Commonwealth, rivalry between New South Wales and Victoria for the national capital led to compromise: the city of Canberra would be built in an empty area between Sydney and Melbourne, then promptly overlooked by most Australians.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QUEENSLAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The lush northeastern portion of Australia is known for its natural beauty and—according to Australians who aren’t from Queensland—unnaturally straight bananas which require bending before export. (Choice responses of Queenslanders are too colorful to share here.) It once had the largest Aboriginal population in Australia, but this changed with the arrival of British colonists, their diseases, and a series of bloody conflicts in the early 19th Century.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QUEENSLAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>When Queensland broke from New South Wales to become its own Crown colony in 1859, Brisbane—originally founded as a penal colony in 1824—had the good fortune to be selected as its capital. This proved especially so with the discovery of gold in Queensland, leading to multiple gold rushes through the back half of the 19th Century. In addition to its numerous national parks, the Great Barrier Reef can be found along most of Queensland’s eastern coast.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_WESTERN_AUSTRALIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The entire western third of Australia’s continent comprises the aptly named Western Australia, called that because “Blasted Hellscape (and Perth)” was too risqué for 19th Century maps. Western Australians are nicknamed after a particularly resilient burrowing locust called a sandgroper, which is either a tribute to their tenacity or a subtle way to say they have their heads in the ground.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_WESTERN_AUSTRALIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The settlement of Perth was founded in 1829 and soon became the capital of the Western Australia. Located in the temperate southwest corner, where the vast majority of Western Australians would come to reside, Perth was so isolated that it could take a week to reach Melbourne by sea.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_WESTERN_AUSTRALIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Western Australia is known for its vast and desolate Outback which is at best sparsely populated. Most West Australians keep to the coasts—and with so much coast to claim, fishing was always a significant part of the colony’s economy.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VICTORIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The mostly temperate southeast region of Australia has long earned its reputation as a garden state. Although cabbage production is year-round, not every Victorian is personally responsible for maintaining their own patch.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VICTORIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Melbourne was founded by John Batman in 1835. It wasn’t the first settlement in the region, but it grew important enough to be named capital in 1851, when the new Crown colony of Victoria split from New South Wales. Good luck for the Victorians who discovered a massive quantity of gold that same year, kicking off a gold rush that would bring many fresh faces to their colony.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VICTORIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Those who had no luck panning or mining were still living in a moderate (for Australia) climate around the people who had struck it rich, allowing them to extract the gold directly through services or skullduggery. With the exception of a particularly painful economic crash in 1893, Victoria’s fortunes remained up.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SOUTH_AUSTRALIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The central southern region of Australia is comprised of temperate coastal land, less temperate bush, and the unforgiving Outback. Despite a colonial reputation for consuming crows in the absence of other food, this is a myth—hungry South Australian colonists stuck to parrots and cockatoos, which were much tastier.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SOUTH_AUSTRALIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>South Australia was the only colony created by an act of Britain’s Parliament. Deliberately designed as a free colony that forbade penal labor, it welcomed poor immigrants who wished to start anew, insisted on a principles of religious freedom, and guaranteed land rights for Aboriginals. From its 1836 inception in Adelaide, the colony largely stuck to its principles.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SOUTH_AUSTRALIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Outback stations reared sheep throughout South Australia. Although there was never a true gold rush in the colony, its extensive fields of wheat would come to support much of Australia by the end of the 19th Century.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_AERIAL_SERVICES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The advent of radio and the airplane transformed life for remote Australian settlements. Education and medical care was suddenly viable to Outback residents who previously had to fend for themselves. Though their homes were distant, such cutting-edge 20th century innovations brought far-flung Australians closer together.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CROWN_COLONY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>By the middle of the 19th Century, the Australian continent was no longer a collection of remote prison camps fraught with dysentery and other dangers, but instead an alluring distant land in which one could start anew and (perhaps) make a fortune. Though self-governed to a degree, they remained undeniably British.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_CRUISE_LINES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>For the first half of the 20th Century, ocean travel was the only reliable and (mostly) safe way to reach Australia. As the newly formed Commonwealth of Australia spent federal money on national parks, Australian passenger liners brought people to experience their splendor and made the Antipodean tourism industry possible.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_FEDERATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Commonwealth of Australia formed at the dawn of the 20th Century. Australians gained a national identity, a less confusing tariff policy, and essential governmental institutions (Parliament and a High Court). They also gained Canberra, a national capital partially designed to keep Melbourne and Sydney from arguing for the privilege.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_GOLD_RUSH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>By 1851, the fortunes won in the California goldfields were known throughout the world. When Edward Hargraves and John Lister discovered a significant amount of gold in New South Wales, the Australian gold rushes that imported population, exported wealth, and caused significant social tensions regarding the “desired ethnicities” of immigrants.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_GREAT_WAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Though the battlegrounds of World War I were far from Australian soil, the Commonwealth nevertheless sent more than 400,000 volunteers to fight on behalf of Great Britain. With troops in the Middle East and on the Western Front, Australia entered the war as federated colonies but left as a nation.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_PASTORAL_LEASES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As the Australian colonies formally surveyed lands suitable for livestock, they began leasing these lands to graziers. Typically encompassing enormous amounts of terrain, the Outback stations required the space to adequately support grazing land without causing droughts—a hard lesson learned by squatters in the late 1860s.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_PENAL_COLONY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The earliest Australian colonies were built by British prisoners shipped halfway around the world. Unfortunately, telling petty thieves to farm, mine, or provide medical care does not imbue them with such abilities. Yet despite their hardships, most convict colonists were eventually able to form the bones of viable colonies.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_SHEEP_REARING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Britain’s growing desire for wool in the 19th Century turned the sheep rearing business into an important part of Australia’s colonial economies. Wool was one of the few commodities that wouldn’t degrade during long sea voyages, so distant colonial wool production served British interests—and the accounts of Australian graziers.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVICS_PAGE_CIVIC_WORLD_WAR_II_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Unlike the Great War, the outbreak of World War II saw a threat of invasion on Australian soil. Though Australian troops once more supported Great Britain’s forces, their disposition was handled with greater independence by the Commonwealth. This allowed the Australian military to coordinate closely with Allied forces in the Pacific.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_PANTANAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The lush natural region of Kakadu is home to such unique varieties of flora and fauna that many remain uncategorized in modern times. It is also home to Aboriginal people thought to have lived in the area for at least 20,000 years. Extensive rock art, some of it thousands of years old, reveals the history of the local Aboriginal people. Multiple attempts at European colonization in the 19th Century failed due to Kakadu’s inhospitable terrain.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_PEDIA_FEATURES_PAGE_FEATURE_TSINGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Near the southwestern coast of the Australian continent are a series of strange rock formations reminiscent of fingertips reaching forth from the sands in which they are situated. These limestone formations are formed from decomposed marine life of an earlier era, though no one theory reveals how they came to exist in their current form. Until their incorporation into a national park in the 1960s, their most common living visitors were kangaroos.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOURISM_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Designating National Parks can greatly enhance [ICON_Gold] Gold and [ICON_Amenities] Amenities. National Parks are designated by Naturalist units, which may be trained or purchased in your city after researching the Conservation civic.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOURISM_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>A National Park's [ICON_Gold] Gold output is equal to the total Appeal of all the tiles included in the park. Additionally, the city that owns the park receives 2 [ICON_Amenities] Amenities, and the four closest cities in your civilization receive 1 [ICON_Amenities] Amenity.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_PENAL_SETTLEMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A nation with colonial aspirations, distant lands claimed in its name, and a creative approach to criminal justice could institute penal settlements. This system of indentured servitude sent prisoners to distant, harsh lands to do the grueling and dangerous work of colonial establishment. Commonly led by a governor who served as warden, the prisoners had nowhere to escape. However, there were incentives to work off their societal debt—ownership of what they had built.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_COLONIAL_GOVERNMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When a penal colony became self-sustaining it needed more than a governor with absolute authority over indentured servants. Harsh colonial justice was not exactly a selling point for accomplished tradesmen and those wishing to change their fortunes. Consequently, a true colonial government provided limited local and regional rule to its residents. Political offices expanded as the colony did, allowing the colonial capital to provide for (and more importantly, to tax) outlying settlements.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_STATE_GOVERNMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The establishment of federated states established regional self-governance within a national system. The clear policies of a federal constitution, enacted and enforced at a federal level, permitted state governments to administer local matters and influence national policy through national representation. Essentially state governments kept their fingers in a variety of pies, worked to add free fingers to new pies, and loudly insisted on parity when another state was observed having more pies than themselves.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_LAND_GRANTS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Colonial governors could grant land to colonists in good standing, though they would often turn a blind eye to convict squatters who worked the land.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_FIRST_FLEET_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Six convict ships, two naval vessels, and three supply ships arrived in Australia in 1788. Fishing was initially the only way to supplement the dwindling colonial stocks</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_REWARDS_OFFERED_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Australian gold rush of 1851 led colonial governments to offer lucrative rewards for ore from the goldfields. Everyone with a pan became a prospector.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_TERRA_NULLIUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The 1835 declaration of Australia as "no man's land" without a recognizable sovereign allowed colonies to claim territory as their own—despite Aboriginal presence.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_COLONIAL_ARCHITECTS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>After initial haphazard development by penal colonists, colonial governors appointed a variety of skilled and specialized craftsmen to plan the development of the colonies.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_PARRAMATTA_ROAD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The first and oldest Australian road connected the colonial cities of Sydney and Parramatta. Such infrastructure development led to an extensive colonial highway system.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_TICKET_OF_LEAVE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A document of parole was issued to convicts who could support themselves, or as a reward for good behavior, and permitted work in colonial districts.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_MOUNTED_STOCKMEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mounted stockmen worked the vast rangelands granted to Outback stations. They were masters at dealing with the herds scattered over expansive amounts of land.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_TRANS_AUSTRALIAN_RAILWAY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>After its transformation into a Commonwealth, construction of the Trans-Australian Railway allowed for reliable, regular transportation from western Australian Perth to eastern Australian Sydney.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_FEED_THE_TROOPS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>AIF troops needed a steady supply of food during their campaigns in distant lands. Long-lasting (and tooth-cracking) hard tack kept soldiers fed at Gallipoli and beyond.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_GALLIPOLLI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Though Gallipoli was ultimately a defeat for Allied forces, the hard fighting of the AIF troops captured popular opinion on the Australian home front.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_SCHOOL_OF_THE_AIR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The prevalence of radio meant scholastic programs could be broadcast to remote Australian regions. This allowed for education in the furthest reaches of the Outback.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_FLYING_DOCTORS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Flying Doctor Service used a combination of aerial transport and radio to support the medical needs of people in remote areas of Australia.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_MILITARY_MATERIEL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Australia’s war economy required raw materials to build armaments, military vehicles, and warships. The prioritization led to increased mining efforts that fed the nation's vital war needs.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_INVASION_THREAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Fear of Japanese invasion led to a policy allowing the deployment of conscripted militia beyond Australian borders, as long as doing so aided Australia’s defense.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_SEAFOOD_PRESERVATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A post-World War II increase in immigration led to a significant expansion of Australia’s fish industry. Prawns and rock lobsters became valuable exports.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GOVERNMENTS_PAGE_POLICY_PARK_RANGERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Australian park rangers are responsible for vast swaths of parkland—both the land’s natural attributes and the well-being of visitors who come to experience it.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_RESOURCES_PAGE_RESOURCE_GOLD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Though it was discovered in the early 19th Century, Australia wasn’t sick with “gold fever” until 1851. So much gold ore was recovered that Britain opened the Sydney Mint, the first time British coins were allowed to be struck outside of England. Gold has consistently remained a lucrative Australian export.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_PROSPECTOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Since the 19th century discovery of Australian gold, prospectors have long sought their fortune in antipodean ground. Unlike fossickers (who sift mullock heaps for gold, silver, or opal as recreation), striking it rich is within the grasp of these “professionally amateur” miners—as long as they stake the right claim.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_GRAZIER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Graziers are fixtures of Outback stations, tending the herds and cultivating livestock-friendly crop on pastoral lands—which are typically vast to support cattle or sheep in Australia’s less than hospitable grazing land. Whether making cheese, shearing sheep, or killing dingoes, graziers are the first step in Australia’s profitable livestock industry.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_FARMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The trials and tribulations of Australian farmers are many and diverse. Soil erosion, the dreaded scotch thistle, and plagues of rabbits, to say nothing of land prone to drought. Yet this difficult life can be quite lucrative to those who put their backs into it—and know where best to settle.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_FISHER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Be it Australian lungfish, Murray cod, or western carp gudgeon, a skilled fisher can catch them all—a somewhat difficult proposition in Australia, the driest continent on earth. The daring rock hoppers forgo freshwater woes by catching marine life from coastal rocks … and avoid saltwater crocodiles out to catch them.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Language='en_US' Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_EXPLORER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Colonial explorers in Australia were often intrepid, ambitious people who sought fame and recognition for their efforts. Unfortunately for them, the Outback had little sympathy for their desires. Of the many who headed out into the bush without basic understanding of its dangers, few would return unscathed. Some wouldn’t return at all.</Text>
		</Replace>
	</LocalizedText>
</GameData>
